Welcome to Peer to Peer.
Where you can hone your
skills by watching live coding videos.
Our guest today is Jamie White.
Who's a Ruby a JavaScript
developer at With Associates.
And a co-organizer of the London Ember inaud
I'm your host Drew Neil
And the challenge that I set for Jamie is called
DN: OK Jamie, would you like to
start by reading out the challenge?
JW: This is how the sequencing should look.
And a sequence is
connected by guests and hosts.
DN: Effectively yes.
JW: So let's have a look
at the data to begin with.
I've already got this stuff.
I'm looking at past episodes to begin with.
I'm interested in the ones that
do form parser sequences already.
We have episode one where the host was you
and the guest was Tom.
That sequence moves on to two .
where Tom the guest becomes Tom the host
Camille becomes the guest.
And then this one leads on to here
where Camille goes from guest
to should have been host.
DW: Unfortunately Camille was ill today
so I'm standing in as host.
DW: In fact, this data is slightly stale
We could have changed it so that we have a branch
Where I interview Tom and also you.
But we're going to pretend that Camille is acting as host today
and stick with the sample data that we came up with.
We can always adapt it later.
Thinking of the nouns in this description
The data structure is composed of collaborations
The description is quite explicit about that
Now, at the moment an episode
isn't strictly a collaboration
A collaboration should have an episode
but not necessarily be an episode.
And it is not explicit in this data
inaud sequels.
But we know that we can
determine those from the host and guest inaudible..
I am going to use ember for this
A bit like reaching for rails,
I won't use all of it to begin with
but it gives you plenty of
directions to go in once you set up
Let me see what version of Ember I am running.
Cool .... leading edge inaud
Let's call this:
inaud all the dependencies we need.
DN: OK.
JW: It will take a while,
there's quite a few of them.
Because I'm using a local copy of inaud
inaud
I got it off GitHub
With inaud, what you tend to do
when working on packages that you're adapting.
Is to .... you do MPM work and it will similar cup
your copy of the repository to the node modules.
or directory
I cant use it straight away,
I need to first enter the ember mpm link cli
And that says also use it inside this project.
Now, if you follow the
trail in this local project.
You'll find this sim-link here going to local modules. inaud
inaud links to my very own copy of it.
It's a nicety of mpm.
Let's just make a quick change
and make sure we're
doing what we think we're doing.
OK, it seems to work.
I am inclined to ....
Get the data in first, and get it in the browser,
and think about it that way.
Pick up the data and put
it down again as much as possible
until some way to handle it emerges.