Welcome to Peer to Peer.
Where you can hone your
skills by watching live coding videos.
Our guest today is John Wiegley,
who's a researcher at BAE,
and author of many useful Haskell libraries.
Our host is Ollie Charles.
And the challenge that he set for John
is called Building a Basic Calculator Language.
OC: OK John, would you like
to start by reading the problem out?
JW: Sure, we have implement a system
that parses BC expressions and evaluates them.
Basic Calculator [which we're calling BC]
is a calculator language, used for scripting
and as an interactive mathematical shell.
Here is an example expression:
we've got 1 + 9 x 20 divided by 5, should equal 40.
The program should parse a
file, evaluate all expressions,
and print the results to standard output.
OC: And you should have a couple of example files
which we're going to aim to parse in this session.
Yes, those are the ones.
Would you like to open those up
and see if it all looks clear enough.
See if you have any questions on the syntax.
JW: It looks pretty straightforward to me.
OC: OK.
[John contemplates the problem]
Chapter 2: Handling Primitive Operations.
JW: Alright, the first thing I'm going
to do is keep these files in this directory
and I'm going to turn this
into a git repository in here.
We'll make a file and call it Parser.hs.
And look to see if the first expression
we want to parse is an addition operation.
I want to model this after I parse it into a
data type that I will run the evaluator against.
So my expressions are going
to have to include an add operation.
And that will need two numbers.
Which I think will be sub expressions in the future.
So I will say: the addition
operation takes two expressions.
Which means I will need a number...
[Silence]
To parse that I'm going to use Parsec.
Which is a library designed for parsing in Haskell.
When I want to parse something,
I have a Parser that will return an integer.
We'll call this num.
And the number a Parser will take...
Let's see...
Many instances of some number.
I'll do it the dumb way first.
I often forget what the whole Parsec interface is.
It's telling me oneOf is not in
scope, so I'm going to hit [inaudible].
You can see I have the syntax
checking happening behind the scenes.
If I press Control C Control H it will do a Hoogle
query, on whatever keyword is under my cursor.
I have Hoogle running locally so that
it works whether I have internet access or not.
I see right away that's in the Char sub module,
so if I go up here and add Char,
then oneOf should be fine.
Same with many, many is in...
looks like Parsec.Prim.
I've said I want a Parser that returns
an integer. This Parser will return characters.
So I need a way to turn that into an integer.
Which I can do using an applicative form of fmap
Actually, I can use the
applicative definition, it will be fine.
There we are... everything parses.
Let me see if I can load this in...
GHCi REPL
I want to run this Parser on sample input.
I need to go into Parsec to find out how to do that.
There is one that will let you do a test parse.
OC: I believe it's in the index,
that may be easier to find.
JW: It's in the Prim module
Yes, that's the one I was thinking of.
It takes a Parser and an input string.
So if I say parse test. I may
have to import the Prim module.
If I say parseTest, then I should get my integer.
Next, I want to parse the add operation.
And that will yield an expression.
Again, I'm using the applicative style to call...
Well, I only have 'add' expressions.
But I need something that's
going to branch based on what it finds.
So I need something higher level.
We need something that says,
I'm going to do a choice...
one of the num parser or the add parser
And the add parser is going to recursively
call the expression parser.
And GCHi does not know, so let's see what it's called.
Choice, as in combinator.
You always have a long
setup of imports with Parsec.
OK, so num says "I don't want to return an integer".
I don't want to 'read' here, I don't want to 'just read'.
I need to wrap that up in my constructor.
And then that means
this returns expression as well.
OC: So what we're saying here is
expr is a Parser that can either
parse addition or a single number.
JW: Correct.
I've forgotten the plus symbol here... so I need to have...
The 'add' is going to read in an expression.
Then it wants to read a plus,
and then another expression.
So in front of the second expression,
I'm going to say that I'm looking for the string plus.
And I'm going to use an
applicative operator that says
"throw whatever you found away and keep reading".
Now if I do 1 plus 2, [I need to make my thing show-able].
The Parser is aborting, it's not recursing.
OC: Is that because it's hitting white space in here?
JW: It's hitting the white space but
if I look at my Parser for expression,
I see that I've said the num Parser should
be first, and then choice only parses once.
So I could say "many choice" to get a list
of expressions, but that's not quite what I want.
I want a chance to parse add
first, but it's still not accepting it.
Because it's trying to go into
add and it's failing to parse it.
I think your right, its the white space.
OC: let's try GCHi without the white space.
JW: Oh! I'm still passing the
num Parser to parseTest [laughter].
Here I have an infinite loop,
because I have no termination condition.
Let's see if the add
expression is also an infinite loop.
OC: What if we change the expr
that you have in add to num?
So we don't have any kind of possibility.
I imagine you're right and
we are going to need two expr.
JW: We have the correct parsing
there, but we want our recursion.
Let me think about why
this is infinitely recursing here.
[John thinks].
Ah! Because the very first
thing that add does is call expression
and the first thing that expression does
is call add which then calls expression.
So it's never consuming anything.
I need to have some way of knowing
in expression what the next step will be.
OC: I think you were right by doing num first before,
but we were simply calling
parseTest with the wrong Parser.
So now we're seeing parse
errors that you would expect.
Right, so now the...
JW: If I call add without white space, I get what I want.
Let's first add the notion of white space.
So I want to have a Parser that says white space,
[It's not going to return a value,
we're just going to throw it away].
And we're going to say "many which says
zero or more", and then I'm going to throw it away.
And then I'm going to say, after
the first expression I will accept white space.
I need to flip this around.
I want that after the operator.
Now I can accept white space whether or not I have it.
We still have the problem
that the choice is not correct.
But if I remove them I have an infinite loop.
We need to have a proper
top level expression Parser.
OC: So it did recurse again, I take it?
JW: Right.
There is an eof Parser which
tells me when I'm at the end.
So we're going to have a requirement be
that our string has to go to the end of the file.
OC: OK.
JW: And there can be white space at the end of the file.
Now when I do parse I get that plus is not expected.
The reason was because we parsed a
number and it thought it should be at space.
Because we wanted to have
space or the end of the input.
OC: Oh, yes OK.
[John thinks].
JW: Why is this happening?
OC: What does parseTest with just add
do now? Now that we've got the white space in there?
JW: It is not parsing correctly.
It did call expr.
OC: Usually when I'm parsing
grammars like this, I use something like chainl
which factors out the
left recursion automatically.
So we might be getting
problems with left recursion here.
Maybe if we change add for
now to take just two numbers.
And we can move on and see if
we can write an evaluator for addition.
Keep the Parser simple for now and
we'll come back and add a bit more logic to it later.
JW: That's working correctly.
Let's write our first evaluator.
Which is going to take an
expression and reduce it to a number.
It's a requirement of our calculator that
it's going to produce numbers in the end.
When we have a number, that's easy, we can get a number.
And when we have an addition between two things,
we have to recursively evaluate
those expressions and add them.
OC: Yes.
JW: And now in GHCi if I eval expression.
Could not match.
Oh! Because parseTest is not in IO.
So if I go over here to...
[Silence]
So parse will say "take a Parser".
And it returns...
And source name, let's see what that is.
If I have an error it will just yield the error.
And if I have a value, then I will
print the result of evaluating that.
And I will do a show here.
There we go, I get three.
This is a lot of code to retype all
the time so we're going to call this test.
OC: We are probably going to need the
exact same code when we read from the file.
JW: So for now our test is just going
to take a String, and it's going to parse it.
[Silence]
Oh! It wanted Text.
[inaudible]
Ah! I don't have recursive parsing yet.
Let's just do right recursion.
[Silence].
It's not liking that at all.
It's not the white space.
[Silence]
OK so mark right recursion on add.
We're going to need recursion
on those steps at some point.
We really need to figure out what's going on here.
OC: I wonder if that trailing white space
might cause us some problems on the expr Parser.
That might be introducing the ambiguity.
JW: It's possible.  We can certainly remove it for now.
But I have a feeling that's not the problem.
The problem is the left recursion here.
Let me think.
It needs a way of knowing if it
should descend into this add branch.
Which means it needs to know
if there's going to be a plus there.
Another thing I could do is go ask the Internet.
Although I don't know if I have internet access here.
Let me check, let's see:
How to rate recursive math expression parser.
Parsing expressions by recursive
decent... the classic solution.
So E is T and a plus and a minus
are a T. T and F. F is a P. P is a B and a T.
The top level only recurs within parens here.
[Silence]
OC: Maybe look up chainl and see what that's doing?
[Silence].
JW: So, parse one or more
occurrences of P separated by op.
Return the value obtained by left associate
application of all functions returned by op.
to the values returned by p.
This can be used to eliminate left recursion
which typically occurs in expression grammars.
That is exactly what we need to use.
So why don't we try that.
I also want to find out what the non-chainl
solution is, because I've never had this problem.
OC: Surely you normally have parenthesis,
and it's they that break up the recursion.
JW: But it's perfectly legitimate
to have one or one plus one.
Without having parenthesis
to have that make sense.
OC: Right.
[Silence].
OC: Because ultimately we're going
to be removing this thing anyway.
JW: Right.
Clearly we cant re-curse all the way back to the top.
[Silence].
This is the problem we're
running into, as you indicated.
So left-recursion removal.
OC: You have to explicitly do left factoring.
You have that X Prime thing which starts
with addition. And that again is breaking it for you.
JW: Ah, that's what it is.
We left off here trying to
break the infinite recursion we have.
We have a left recursion in  a top down Parser.
Which is going to infinitely
re curse without parsing any input.
We solve it by having a term Parser which
knows how to parse numbers, for example.
OC: So what we're trying to
do is break that ambiguity.
JW: Right.
Our main expression Parser is
going to call the term Parser first.
We'll do it in monadic style here.
Now we have the term we can
look at what the next thing will be.
And for example, if it's a plus,
we know it's a descendant to addition.
So if that's the case we have to put a branch on this.
So we will take a look at what the next token is.
We know that it could be, say, a plus.
[Silence].
And then if Y is that, then we are going to return
Eadd X and then call again into expression parser.
Otherwise if it's not plus, then at the
moment we just have an unrecognized operator.
Over here again, we have the white space problem.
We'll allow white space to be
thrown away here... and here.
[Silence].
Without white space.
Oh, we're still having a problem.
OC: There's no termination condition here.
So even when we see an addition sign we expect another one.
JW: That's true.
So we can have plus or we can have
eof, but eof is going to return nothing.
So in that case, we're going to return the String.
At the moment... to work around that.
Unrecognised operator...
OC: Maybe use Just for the operator
and use Nothing for end-of-file.
JW: Excellent.
'y' is a Maybe so I'll call it 'my'
If Nothing then
we'll return just our X
Otherwise then we'll say is Y a plus.
Now we've got rid of our
infinite left recursion problem.
Now you were telling me about a
function called chainl, which I have not used yet.
But in Parsec is designed to solve this problem.
OC: That's what I'm telling you.
JW: That's right, but we will say we want
term, chainl1 and...
which in this case... let's see...
The addop is going to be...
Oh! I see that's the
symbols that it's expecting to see.
Let's do this, just like they have here:
we'll say the add operation, and now if
we see add we're going to return the function plus.
OC: I think you want EAdd there rather than addition.
JW: That's right because I'm
not doing evaluation in the Parser.
So I have term chain addop.
I  will still need to deal with white space.
I believe that symbol skips trailing white space,
so I don't need to worry about leaving white space.
OC: Do you need to worry about
that if you're using symbol everywhere?
JW: Perhaps not.
OC: I suppose our num parser is still...
JW: Let's say that there can be white
space after terminals, for the moment.
[Silence].
Now the add Parser is going to go away.
And we're going to have a new Parser for expressions.
And now all this gets to go away.
OC: It might be a Parser as a function to
expression to expression to expression, in addop...
because you have EAdd as your return type.
[Silence].
JW: Their version of white space
here is too fancy for what I want just yet.
Parsec allows you to describe what tokens look
like and what the white spacing comments are.
I may use that a little bit but not at the moment.
Symbol is applied to too few arguments...
Ah! This symbol is coming from that fancy library.
I don't want symbol. I want string and
I have to build in my own terminating white space.
[Silence].
OC: That's a lot simpler.
JW: Much cleaner.
Based on the example that they gave,
we want to extend this to more operations.
So we will go ahead and add those,
because Math operations tend to be easy to put in.
We're going to say we want
subtraction, multiplication and division.
It's all still going to be on numbers.
Now we have to make three more versions of addop.
We're going to have subop.
We're going to have mulop.
We are going to have to worry about precedence
because, what would it mean if we said this:
In what order do we evaluate?
We know we want the division to happen first.
How do we make sure the Parser enforces that.
The way to do that is to
structure how we do our traversal.
OC: Because now the Parser is just running from left to right,
and basically just standing on the left.
JW: The expression evaluator
is going to be equally trivial.
OC: Can we not just work with 'int' anymore?
JW: Ah true...
we want the fractional numbers...
And now our num will have to say... I always
forget what the conversion operations are called...
OC: I wonder if it's easier to use doubles everywhere.
In some of the later codes it assumes
you can assign to floating point numbers.
We want a number... followed by...
[we're going to have to do
this in a different style here].
OC: I feel  that Parsec may already
have a pre-built Parser for doubles.
JW: True, but I want us to write our own!
So we want the part before and
after to be numerical parsing.
So this is our numerical parser.
We're going to say a numerical Parser is some number.
And then we want an optional period character.
And it's optional, so we will
get a maybe value out of it.
[John thinks].
Then we will take our X and
append it with yet another number.
Otherwise, just return a number.
It's complaining because there
are two definitions of optional.
[John thinks].
OC: The definitions are completely equivalent...
we aren't making a choice about which ones we hide.
Fairly arbitrary, right?
JW: Right.
I think it may be re-exported nowadays.
They have the same definition.
OC: I believe we need to use that dot
character between the two num Parsers.
JW: Yes.
OC: Now we are consuming a dot
but we're ignoring it when we emit a string.
JW: Oh yes, we have to add
it back in. Very good point.
[John types].
I can't do sections like that.
[Ollie mumbles in agreement].
JW: So now cannot deduce this being double.
So we will say if double... there we go...
and now we get ... 13.0
OC: Can we try to parse 1.5,
something like that?
[John tries this].
JW: We can even multiply something in here.
That did not work. Because
we haven't tied in the Parser.
OC: These are all doing EAdd as well.
JW: True, they're not plugged in.
Now we want to extend our
parsing chain the way that they did.
He did precedence by having it be at the same level.
[John mumbles as he types].
We're going to follow suit.
[Silence].
Now we want chain in the addop...
And then we'll say...  a little snipped...
A lot of good coding can come
from just copying. [laughter]
We don't have parens yet...
So instead we will call...
[John thinks]
We will just say... our own term...
What am I going to call this for now...
I'm going to call it sub expression.
[inaudible mumbling].
If I say that I get
correct multiplication.
If I add the 5 to the back it works as we'd thought.
But it also works the same if we add it to the front.
Chapter 3. Parsing Files and Handling Parens.
I would like to have parenthesis so that we can do this...
And if we add them, we will have
satisfied the first three lines of our file.
OC: I wonder now if we could
try to hook this in to read from a file.
and maybe try to parse the entire
file and watch the Parser eventually fail.
JW: OK.
OC: We should be ready to
parse the first two lines I think.
It might eventually
start emitting some evaluation.
JW: So let's write a function that we
can call from the REPL... called testFile...
and that will take a FilePath,
instead of just a string.
And then we want to get the contents of the path.
We're going to parse the same
expression but we're going to do many of them.
We could also cut the file up.
But I want this expression
Parser to take in the whole thing.
OC: Yes, We can give it the whole
file and it will evaluate it line by line.
JW: Right.
So... this will be a series of xs.
Again we need this case here.
So we're going to say for every x that we have...
[Silence].
I'm going to call it ex.
forM_ is not in scope, this comes from Control.Monad.
If I didn't do this, if I said Control-c and Control-m...
it would suggest to me all
the modules that it knows about.
If I select Control.Monad
it will put it with the explicit.
OC: Is that coming from
the normal Haskell mode for Emacs
or is it an extra extension you have?
JW: Let's see...
ghc-ins-mod is providing that feature.
I use Haskell mode and I use ghc-mod and hdevtools.
And the code that jumps to the local
Hoogle is a patch that I did on ghc-mod's code,
to jump over to the Hoogle
I have running on my local machine.
So parser providing too few arguments.
I definitely want to pass the
name of the file to the Parser.
getContents... Ah, I want readFile.
[Silence].
I did the case one level too far.
[Silence]
So let's say here...
I'll do it in point free
just because I know you [laughter].
I need to pack the string.
[Silence].
So, the actual type...
OC: So I guess parse is a pure function?
JW: Yes, we're working with
pure functions here. Good thing!
And then this is a right value, not just value.
I have no idea what this is going to do [laughter].
Not all of this file will parse so we
will take a cut out of it and call it test.bc.
Then I'm going to run this on test.bc
And we go into an infinite loop [laughter].
It would be nice to know why, so let's add some tracing.
I tend to add a lot of tracing
when I'm initially developing.
The main thing I want to trace into is
I want to know when expr is being called.
The tricky thing about doing traces is
that it's not like 'print' in an imperative language.
It's not going to print a
statement as soon as it enters expr.
It will cause that string to be
printed when expr's result gets evaluated.
Which sometimes can be rather distant.
Action of debugging at a distance.
OC: So this is where Haskell's laziness
is more of a pain point than a benefit.
JW: Right, it makes it harder to
find out when things are happening.
So we are seeing that the
expression is only being called once.
Our infinite recursion is happening elsewhere.
My first version of many parsers will
have tracers on every function [laughter].
So I can watch what's happening as it's going.
So I will go ahead and put this in.
After a certain point I have a keyboard macro.
Now I can say control E and control... alright.
So we get to addop and we stop.
So addop...
[Silence].
Let me add traces deeper in.
[John mumbles to himself].
Ah! the minus symbol. We don't have a minus symbol.
OC: What happens if we just
shorten this file even more... yeah.
JW: We're getting no output whatsoever.
Oh! there we go, same place.
OC: And if we run our test again?
JW: Interesting...
I don't have support for parens.
But there are no parens in this line
OC: Maybe it's the new line that's the
problem... at the end of the file.
JW: Right. Let's say that we want
there to be an eof at the end of the file.
We don't even get there which means we
have infinite recursion happening somewhere.
[Silence].
Let's split the file up into
lines and do this differently:
[Silence].
Now we would expect that
we would get the 2.0 as a result.
And if we go back to what we had before...
It's failing parse these comments.
OC: Maybe the empty strings as well. JW: Yes.
JW: Cool, we don't have parentheses.
So we definitely want to strip out the comments.
Let's write a function called massage.
That will take some input text and
strip out anything that looks like a comment.
First we'll say stripComments on text.
And then we want to say whether this
yields a balanced string or not.
[Silence].
And now we want string comments to say: given some...
[John thinks]
I'll go to Data.Text library
to find out how to partition a string.
[Inaudible].
Partition is not what I want, I want break or split.
Split, is it on or is it at, now let's read it.
We're never going to have
the hash be a valid character.
So we're going to say take one not equal to...
It's going to be tiresome to always type
that so let's allow a little disambiguity.
That's shorter!
And were still dieing on empty lines...
No we're not!
so we want to first case on massage.
[Silence].
We'll be nice and put out an empty line.
[John mumbles as he types].
OC: That's the parentheses again.
I think we're skipping
over comments successfully now.
And those two outputs do match
what we would expect from the input file.
JW: OK, so we have now got
parsing of expressions and files.
We know we have to do parens
and a couple of other things.
What I would like to do next is do it in a REPL style.
So that I could use this on
the command line for example.
OK, so we want to have a function called REPL.
And this will just loop forever.
And I will say that forever I am going to get...
I can't remember what the function
is to get input from the command line!
Is it getLine?
OC: I think there is a getLine, Yes.
JW: It's not something I use.
OC: You can also use interact.
That would be interesting to look at.
JW: Yes, let's hop over to interact:
String to String to IO.
And then the output string
is going to be what it prints.
So we're going to get an input
string, and run it against our test.
[Silence].
This one is in IO, which is unfortunate.
There's no reason this function should
be in IO except when we're printing.
So let's break this into two.
And have this be text to text,
and it's going to return pack show.
Or it's going to return show of evaluation.
And now test... what will we call this...
Eval string...
I guess it would be more
appropriate to call it evalText.
And our test is going to putStrLn
the result of eval-ing.
And you can see I have this ...
That's not really a Unicode character.
OC: That's actually the ASCII 'dot'.
JW: Yes but Emacs has this way to say
'when you see this type of character in this context,
then show me this other character instead.'
Like, when I type: not A or B...
I'd like to see the mathematical notations.
OC: And you're doing the same with
the arrow and the double colon above.
JW: And this arrow and a few other things.
I have one for the proc incoming arrow.
I interact with evalText, which simply needs
to pack and unpack because I'm using data.text.
There's no particular reason I'm using Data.Text.
OC: I think interact already runs forever.
I think the idea of interact is you get
a lazy string of all of standard input.
And you deliver a lazy string of output.
So you might want to split that int
lines again then evalText over each line.
JW: Right.
Well if I'm going to be on a REPL...
Let's take a look at the definition
of interact here.
Oh yes you're right, it takes the entire input.
That's not really what I want then.
I want to have my own forever because
I want to see the result of every line as I type.
So we want our input to come from getLine.
And then we are going to evalText the result.
Actually, now that we're in
IO we can just run test on the input.
It just has to be this.
Alright, we can be a little bit fancier now.
[John types and thinks].
Alright, were dealing with packing and showing.
[John thinks and types].
I have to add in an
extension called OverloadedStrings.
OC: And when you type that
have you got a templating thing for Emacs?
JW: There is a module called YASnippet.
And I have a snippet called 'lang'.
So if I type 'lang' and hit tab
it will expand and then ask...
It actually has gone to GHC and asked it.
I'll show you what that snipped looks like.
Let's see it's in Haskell mode what is it called...
[John thinks].
Yes, here it is.
It inserts language, it requires and
then it says haskell-yas-ghc-language-pragmas.
That is a function that will go out to GHC,
and ask "what are all your extensions?"
Actually I think the command
was right there: ghc --supported-extensions.
And that will tell you what you can use.
[Silence].
Going back to our example code.
So now we have this compiling.
No this is not compiling yet.
It still didn't like that.
[John thinks].
It wants a character?
[John thinks and occasionally mumbles inaudibly].
Oh! I don't want to use return.
It was interpreting it in the
List monad... I was confusing that.
Right, so now if we have a REPL I can say 1+2, I can say 1+5.
This makes it much easier for me to do little tests.
OK, so let's do parens.
We want...
What are parens?
For this one I can use a Parsec feature.
[John thinks about what it's called].
It's in the combinators library,
and it's called 'between' I think.
Yes.
[Silence].
I like this notion of symbol.
A symbol can have white space on either side.
[John types].
OC: Maybe it would be better
if we passed a Parser in as well.
So symbol is a kind of Parser transformer
that takes a Parser and gives you...
JW: But then I would find myself
constantly doing things like that.
I would rather just say this:
So now I will go to all the places where I've done this.
And now I can say symbol
without having to have this nonsense here.
The symbol function that comes with Parsec...
I'm returning the wrong thing... oh no.
the one that is in the token module,
relies upon a definition of what
the tokens of your language are,
which would include the commenting.
We've handled commenting,
pre - input to the Parser.
But Parsec does have the ability to say this is what...
OC: So rather than sanitizing the input,
you could have dealt with
comments as syntax themselves.
JW: Right.
If I go to the contents of the Parsec module.
[John mumbles inaudibly].
We have a module called token.
In token there is this notion
of a language definition.
Which you call makeTokenParser and
you pass in a definition of your language.
And that definition defines these things.
How do comments begin and end.
What does a single line comment
look like. Can they be nested etc. etc.
And finally you have
reservedNames and reservedOpNames.
That way, when you say symbol
it has to be something from...
I don't think it has to be
from your reservedNames list,
but it won't confuse that as an
identifier name; it's been reserved.
This is a very handy thing to use,
but we're not going to be using it right now,
because our language is so simple.
We want symbol, symbol, between...
We want a parser for expressions between symbols.
OC: I think between still needs a
third argument which is the Parser to run.
[John types].
JW: There we go, it types
OK, symbol is applied... again.
[Silence].
Expected string... Oh string is returning a ...
You know what, I never
actually want the result of this.
[John mumbles as he types].
Now let's run our REPL again:
1+5 and I'll say 1+5x3.
OC: Excellent. So we should be able
to call the function that's reading the file.
And get a little further this time.
JW: Previously we were using
testFile on test.bc which is a shorter file.
There we go.
OC: It looks like it gets all the way to the end there.
JW: Right. Now we're going to
test.bc and add in the next thing:
Phi as a constant.
As we're in a working state here,
I'm going to go ahead and commit this.
So parser handles a simple expression in REPL
There we go.
Chapter 4. Handling BC Variables.
JW: Now how are we going to handle let binding?
We will start by writing a parser for let bindings.
So we'll call it letBinding
and it's going to be an expression.
I don't know what it's going to be yet.
Actually let's put a type hole there.
We want to represent this in our language.
We're going to say,
"A let binding has a variable name and an expression".
And then we know that we
will have let in our constructor.
And we are going to parse...
I can't remember whether
oneOf can take a range.
Oh, actually, I can just say I want letter.
I'm going to have some letter.
OC: So some is like many but it requires one or more.
JW: Yes, and we want, of course...
[Silence].
And of course we're going to get some conflict here.
Oh! That's because letter returns a character.
And then the aggregate raises a string and
then I need to pack it because we want to test.
And then we want to tie
the let binding in to our Parser.
OC: Do you need to introduce
the let keyword there at all?
JW: Excellent point.
So we're going to call that symbol.
OC: Is there an equals between the keyword...
JW: Let's see what your specification said.
[John types].
This is starting to go a little out in to
space here so let's write it more monadically.
We want... some letter... to be our name
and we want to pack the name.
And then we want to parse an equal.
And we want to get a body of an expression.
and then we're going to return
ELet name body
And body is...
[John thinks].
What is going on there?
[Silence].
Why would it think that the type of body...
OC: Is that error out of date because
you don't have that last line of code any more.
JW: Oh, that's true. Sometimes
the background syntax checker...
I'm getting a little ahead of it so
it's showing a result from a while ago.
In the evaluator, we need
to do something with this let.
We want to take in an environment.
And that is going to be a map of names to expressions.
We want the let to add an entry into
that map that we can later evaluate,
if anyone makes a reference to it.
We want to have Data.Map in scope.
We don't JUST want a map of text to expressions because that would mean
every time the variable was
referred to it would be re-evaluated.
We want a function in there.
We want our evaluator to be recursive.
OC: OK.
JW: I will need to have this be a little trickier.
Let's go with the dumb way first.
and build this up incrementally.
It never pays to be too fancy in the beginning.
And we will say ELet main body.
We need to pass in the environment
and return the mutated environment.
Which is the perfect job for state.
Which means we need to bring in State.
And I bring in from transformers...
OK, which means now we are monadic.
So all these have to do returns.
Do returns.
Now we are going to say "get the environment".
Oh, actually this modified the environment
OC: modify is from Control.Monad.State.
JW: So env is going to be the modified environment.
I'm going to say insert at name body and inside
environments, since that's the last parameter.
Parsec again has its own keyword named State
[John thinks].
I need to getEnv.
OC: Ah, because Env is a new type.
JW: Right
OC: We need to wrap it back up.
Modify returns no value, yet we have been
saying things return as Double all the time.
Yet this sub expression...
Let's say if a let is evaluated...
Oh, Let has one more component doesn't it?
It has the body over which the let ranges.
OC: Which in this fairly simple
syntax, is just to the end of the file.
JW: This is actually an imperative notion now.
This is a statement with no result.
That has an effect on the environment.
Which is not part of our evaluator.
OC: Well, you could still put this in the evaluator
but then the evaluator could return Maybe Double
Maybe running an expression doesn't give you any output.
JW: That's one way we could do it.
Let me think...
OC: We could take the more functional approach
and have the let binding
scope over the rest of the file.
And every time you're introducing
a new let you're introducing some more scope,
that extends to the end of the file.
JW: I like that idea more, but for
now let's go with the Maybe idea.
So in this case we have this.
And here we'll have...
These guys all become 'Justs'.
Syntactic uniformity here...
Ah, these things now...
We're in the monad now.
So for example if we were to say 1 plus let phi equal 10...
Let's have a let be it's body.
OC: Sure.
JW: That makes more sense.
OC: Yes.
JW: We're still monadic here so I'm
going to rewrite this into monadic form.
Now, in another language we would not
name names. I could have said this couldn't I?
And it would have meant the
same thing, but can't do that in Haskell yet.
OC: So that's the style of
banana brackets that you were referring to,
which is still somewhat controversial in the Haskell community.
Now I want to modify and
evaluate expression B and return that.
[Silence].
Ah, I do not need to return
because that is itself monadic.
Now we need to pass in an environment
to our evaluator wherever we use it.
So let's have a way of creating a new environment...
And the new environment is going
to be a wrapper around empty,
which is going to conflict of course.
We want to say with environment and I'll
say with new environment will be...
"You give me an expression
and I will give you back a Double".
And the way I'll do this, I will say
flip runStateT newEnv expression.
"flip is applied to too few arguments"
[John mumbles as he types].
OC: Do we really want that
because you want to pass on this
mutated environment for every step of the REPL.
OC: Do we really want that
because you want to pass on this
mutated environment for every step of the REPL.
JW: This will be a top level function.
OC: OK.
JW: This is for people who are further
down and don't have to worry like this.
So we're going to say
"with new environment"... or we're going to say eval.
We're going to have a new function called eval.
It underlines warnings in blue and
I generally tend to pay attention to them.
I'm getting rid of redundancy.
I don't need so much tracing so this
seems like a good opportunity to delete some.
OC: Those warnings about
redundant brackets are coming from hlint?
JW: Correct.
I'm using flycheck which
is talking to both GHC and hlint.
That will give me a more comprehensive picture.
I have one warning left which
is the import of token is redundant.
So I will drop it.
We did this to do let bindings.
We still can't refer our variables though.
OC: Because we're using a new environment.
JW: So I need a new thing which we'll
call EVar, which will be a variable reference.
I know how I want eval to be evaluated.
I don't yet know yet how I want it to be parsed.
I'm going to get my environment and do
a look up of my name in the environment.
And if there's nothing, I'm going to say error
unknown variable and tell people what the name was.
And unpack it because we're
dealing with Text versus String.
Otherwise if I have a body
behind that variable
This is where I said we we're
going to re-evaluate all the time.
But, so what, you know.
OC: This is because the look up has returned an Expr.
JW: Yes.
And we're storing expressions in our
map Because Haskell is a lazy language
we want to get the map to have thunks in it.
So that the first time you touch the thunk,
only then will it do the work of evaluating it.
From then on it will have that value.
We'll do that next.  Let's see here.
I need to get.Env
Now we have a way to define and reference
variables. We just need a way to parse them.
Variable's going to be a fundamental
term again, in addition to our let bindings.
So we're going to have terms,
and we'll call them num or letBinding or variable.
And what is a variable?
[John thinks].
Variable has the same definition as a name.
[John types and mumbles inaudibly].
OC: So this is the same parser we used
when we introduced a name in the let binding.
JW: Yes, and the only difference is that
we're going to... Actually let's do it this way...
Let's have our name be a parser of text.
A variable be an EVar after varname, and
then back down there where we said some letter.
And then that way if we want to update to
alphanumerics we only have to change it in one place.
Let's say test let phi equal 20. And we get
no parse, of course, so that's what we're going to do.
OC: So that no parse is not coming from our parser.
It's coming from our use
of the read function somewhere.
JW: Correct.
[John thinks].
We can use trace here.
Actually, I don't need to do that because
I have a key binding I use that auto inserts.
I change it to be traces.
I'm going to do this return at the
end because trace has to yield a value.
Sometimes I use printf more
and sometimes I use trace more.
I should have two variants of it.
OK, so let's see here...
We never even get to our let.
It's trying to parse...
[Silence].
We would get the same problem
even if we just use the word let.
[Big sigh from John]
We're never getting as far as our let bindings.
OC: We do have trace lines above which seem
to indicate we have gone into addop and mulop.
JW: I just have to prioritize let binding.
OC: OK.
Because, this is what parsec does.
It read in the first letter of the word let.
Found that it wasn't a number in
the num parser and said "this isn't me".
Choice said, "OK whats the next
parser," but it didn't give back the L.
So you have to use try as
a wrapper around your parser
if you want the input to be re wound to
the beginning of where your last parse failed.
But since let begins with a concrete key word
that we're not going to be re-using as a variable name,
it's safe for us to promote that higher.
OC: Because no other
expressions are going to use that word.
JW: Right, and in fact...
Because variable is going to be a
similar type of parser, let's wrap that as well.
[John thinks].
The REPL creates a new environment.
So we want a different type of test for this to use.
Let me expand this out.
We want to run this forever loop within State.
We're going to do execStateT on this one.
And we're going to flip it
and do it with a new environment.
Forever runs an IO, so we want to go here.
OC: Forever should work on any monad.
I think your problem there was was the
getLine is forcing you to be in the IO monad.
I'll just leave that out there.
So we get our input and we want to run our evaluator.
For that we're going to have to parse it.
I'm getting a lot of duplication here.
But for the time being we'll just let it slide.
So we want to eval.expr.
We need to have our evaluator.
We're going to get the
environment and do a sub evaluation.
[John types and mumbles]
OC: Sounds like it should be possible
to do that without having to runState.
JW: This StateT is over IO, and our
function is a StateT that's over Identity.
We could use the mmorph library's hoist routine.
To swap out between the two.
In fact let's go ahead and do that.
We're going to say hoist liftIO,
evalExpression x.
And then that comes from
Control.Monad.IO.Class
We're going to go from Identity to IO.
It should be just a matter of return.
And getLine is still forcing us
into the wrong monad.
We still need to pack the input.
OC: You might have Data.Text.IO.getLine
which would let you avoid packing.
JW: Thanks.
OC: And you have got T.readFile here.
Another problem is execState is
apparently going to give you back the file.
JW: Something's still... Oh of course...
Something was pushing us into IO.
So execState is giving us back a... Let's just do that.
Just import whatever was there.
It's losing the sense of what monad we're in.
[Silence with occasional mumbling].
Oh I always get a surprise when that type checks!
I didn't think that hoist line
was right but I guess it was.
OC: You were pretty quick so maybe you
were running ahead of your flycheck again!
JW: So we have 1 plus 4.
We have let phi equals 20.
Now I should be able to say
phi plus 5 and I get no parse.
So, again we have been stricken by this num parser.
OC: So maybe we can just do
the same trick twice [laughter].
JW: Well it's worth trying, isn't it.
Hurrah....
So we can define and reference variables.
Now we want the ability to define
not just sub expressions, but functions.
Before we do that I want to do this
trick where we do not re-evaluate expressions.
We want our map to be a map of names to doubles.
And the reason we can do
that is because they are constants.
They can only ever refer
other things inside the environment.
So here, instead of inserting our
expression into the map we we are going to insert...
They can only ever refer
other things inside the environment.
So here, instead of inserting our
expression into the map we we are going to insert...
[John thinks].
Oh I have to evaluate that outside.
OC: Because that might refer
to previously bound variables.
JW: Right, there we go.
Now his is not using any kind of laziness
type trick, it's just evaluating at that moment.
OC: Should we change that last
evalExpr b as well to just return B prime?
JW: In fact we shall, very good.
JW: Let's check this in.
We can now define and reference.
Now let's see if we can parse this in our test.
OC: I imagine we're going to
get a problem looking up square root.
That's my guess.
JW: Unknown variable square root [laughter].
So, we have no way of defining functions yet.
OC: We do seem to have a couple of loop regressions.
Oh, look at that...
We're losing the sense of lines
because we're chopping things up.
So we got two but we didn't get 30.
Let's do this now ourselves, at the REPL.
We definitely have a regression there.
I don't think division is being handled correctly.
I have a feeling that if it's
any other operator it will be fine.
Yes, so it's just division.
OC: We maybe forgot to put a line in our parser.
JW: We have perhaps
forgotten to put a line in our parser.
Let's see what we get when we do this ourselves.
So we go to mulop... Unexpected 5...
[Silence].
Is it because we should be
using symbol rather than string?
JW: Of course that's why. Thank you.
Yes now we have it.
Chapter 5. Handling BC Functions.
OC: Excellent, so I  guess we go back to that read file.
JW: Right.
Yes, we have all of our
current lines. No square root
I guess you we're expecting that to be from a library?
OC: I think the assumption is that
there's a "Prelude" in scope...
JW: Let's call it double
instead, and let's say that double...
Let's see what the syntax for functions was.
So define double of n
to be n times n
Now we need to define that.
As usual I like to start by
looking at my expression tree.
This is a lot like a let binding,
it's just one that needs input parameters.
This is like saying this:
We have an expression that's a lambda abstraction
and we want to define double
to be that lambda abstraction.
So we'll call that ELam.
At the moment we're going to allow
that lambda to take just one variable.
OC: Yes, that's all that happens
in these little example scripts.
You can assume that these are
all functions over one variable.
JW: Right.
So that variable is going to
itself evaluate down to a value.
OC: Yes.
JW: So we can have our lambda
be a host language lambda.
Of expression to expression.
OC: Why expression to expression and not double to expression?
JW: Very good.
Now because it's a lambda in there
and this would be the higher order abstract syntax,
where we're using the host language's
ability to represent functions as values.
In order for our target language
to represent functions as values.
That's the higher order nature.
There can be no automatically
derived Show instance for these.
That's the higher order nature.
There can be no automatically
derived Show instance for these.
This is the tedious part where
we have to do a lot of boilerplate.
We have to say that for every one of these things...
I need to say what it means to print that out.
So I'm going to say that that means...
OC: Do we still need Show instance?
We could just drop that I suppose.
JW: True, but it comes in handy for debugging.
Let's just do a real quick...
[John types]
Lambda is not going to be there,
so we're just going to say or lambda.
[John types]
We have a variable reference.
For now we're going to extinguish that.
[John types and mumbles].
It's not the show it's complaining about
it's the fact that this has to be monoid.
++ does not mean append for Strings.
Pretty soon this is going to be 300 lines
[laughter]
As usually happens in Haskell!
OC: But we do want to be
working with strings here right?
Because show is defined as
a function from something to string.
JW: Ah, you're right.
[Silence].
OC: I think we're OK using show.
JW: Yes because we're defining a Show instance.
Yes, so we want to unpack in these two places.
JW: Now I have my lambda.
The first thing is to decide
how I'm going to evaluate it.
Before I go on to how I'm going to parse it.
So I get my lambda, and
I have an F and now I'm going to say:
that I want an expression,
and call F of my expression.
I need a double. I need a body for my lambda, no?
I need to define what application
means. What it means to call a function.
That's how it gets its argument.
Application takes a form and an
argument. And we're going to show that as...
Show F...
Show X...
OC: Is F here going to be the name of the lambda abstraction?
JW: Yes.
We'll restrict it to being nothing fancy
like an expression that evaluates to a
lambda that can be passed as an argument.
That would be cool but for now we'll
have functions be only reference-able by name.
And then we have EApp be a name and the
argument is going to be the expression.
So we only allow one argument.
We want unpack n.
Now we will go to our handy-dandy
evaluator down there.
We'll say EApp n x.
evalExpr x to get me my real x
Then look up in the map...
[John thinks]
So we can't store just doubles in our map.
Let's just do all our expressions again for now.
We're going to say no function.
We're going to get the environment.
And then if we find it...
We are going to pass F.
[Inaudible]
Now F isn't an expression, so we have to evaluate F.
Let's say F prime as a valuation of F,
and then we have to look at what F...
[Silence].
Now, evaluating a lambda.
There should be no context in which it's evaluating.
OC: Right, that's basically a
type error in our little language.
[Laughter].
[Silence].
So we need to eval expr.
We need to return and I'm going to eval expr this.
And go ahead and store that in there.
It's horribly inefficient but we'll
let it go because it gives us some ease.
Now we need a way to define these two things.
OC: There's a little more syntax to bring in here.
JW: We had that binding before,
now we're going to have fun binding.
OC: We're already having fun binding. [laughter].
So we want the symbol define, is that what you wanted?
OC: Yes.
JW: We want the name and the open parens.
We want also, the argument to be a name.
Then we want closing parens.
And then open curly [laughter].
And then we can have up to many
expressions in the body of the function.
Now, expressions that could end in newlines.
[Silence].
And there is a thing we can
use from parser called text sepBy.
So we want sepBy1.
OC: So that parses at least one
expression that is separated by new lines.
JW: Right.
So we have exprs. This is our body.
And now we're going to return ELam
We want a function that's going
to take in some number and return...
[John thinks].
Let me ask you this question.
What if we evaluate a
function that has let bindings in it.
Those let bindings should probably
not escape outside of the function should they?
And every time you run the function,
it should renew the let bindings.
OC: I think that's a safe
assumption to make.
JW: So a function is not going to return
an expression the way we defined it.
An expression is going to be
a mutator from doubles to doubles.
OC: Yes.
But, we want it to inherit the
environment that it was executed in each time.
OC: So we can refer to let
bindings outside the function definition.
JW: So I'm just going to use that, I'm going to make that...
So instead of using
something as fancy as reader,
we're going to take in environment as an argument.
Alright, so... we have our env we have our arg.
JW: We're going to say eval expression.
We're going to evalStateT
eval expression arg in env.
Now arg is a double.
Oh, we have to bind our name to...
OC: So we put that double into the environment.
JW: Right.
We have to say... "insert at arg"
[Silence].
What will I have... let's call this one X.
It can't just be that.
OC: We need to wrap it up as an expression.
[Silence].
And then this has to be
getEnv and then rewrapped.
Because type-wrapping is just
as much fun as you expect it to be.
OK, so Eval state T returns an identity double.
Then arg is the wrong thing.
It is not the body expression, arg is this...
Now we want to sequence through.
So we want to fold down the body.
OC: You would probably be alright
taking the last value of the expression for now.
JW: But I need to evaluate every one so
that any internal let bindings get established.
OC: Right, OK.
JW: We're going to bind this in.
I'm going to do a flip binding here.
And then fold M inside here.
It's going to go from environment
to environment for every body expression.
Folding down from the environment over the body.
So Env, expected type Double.
And fold M has the accumulator on the left.
[Silence].
Oh, I don't need to fold M that way.
We're going to pass in a double... as it thinks I need.
And we're going to ignore it in each step.
OC: So we're just taking
the last double that's produced.
JW: Right, and then we need the right identity here.
OC: Cool, everything typechecks?
JW: No! Now the functions are differently expressed.
Function application now has
to hand in the current environment.
Which makes sense.
Couldn't match expected type first argument.
This is now just going to be the
value we wanted, so we can just return it.
It type checked!
OC: [Laughs].
JW: I continue to be perhaps incorrectly amazed.
[John types].
I don't like excessively long lines.
OK... let's try this out with test file.
Unknown variable, fine, Ok.
We haven't tied it in yet so we
need letBinding followed by funBinding.
And what else did we define...
Oh, we need to do application.
A naked variable reference could be a
variable reference or it could be a function call.
OC: I think all function calls are a variable
name immediately followed by parentheses.
With no white space between them.
JW:  Right.
So we're going to try to parse a funCall.
Because if there is no paren after
that, we'll back track all the way up.
[John types]
OK, we want the name of the function to come in.
And then we're going to look for this guy
except instead of parsing a varname,
we're going to parse a sub-expression.
And then we're going to say: return that
as an application of name to arg.
"Type error says Ollie!"
OC: [Laughs] Well I didn't say it but...
So we tried to evaluate a lambda
because we put a lambda in our syntax tree
Why did we do that?
[they both talk at the same time]
Oh that's right, what does define evaluate to.
It evaluates to the body of
the function, which is a lambda.
In that case we're going to
say that functions evaluate to zero.
Sound good to you [laughter].
That just did not work at all.
OC: So we have a zero from our define.
I guess the error is on the let.
JW: Yes, let me put some boundary on there [laughter].
OC: So you're now tracing in our language!
JW: Yes! I see the two, three and zero.
We defined it.
So it's the call that we're having a
problem with... expecting define...
OC: Ah, so I think the problem here
is our function name starts with a D.
And when it sees D it assumes
that it must be going to...
JW: Ah right.
OC: We'll probably have to try unbinding.
[Silence].
JW: Unknown function double, great!
OC: But we did just define a function double.
JW: [Laughter] Yes.
So we need to go to define and find out why
it did not get inserted into the environment.
Ah, that's what it is.
OC: Define gave us Elam...
JW: And the blue line is telling us
"your not doing anything with name".
Elam needs to have:
Just as let did, Elam needs a name.
Now when we go, we won't just have Ollie's type error.
We are now going to...
Ah... now we need something
new to go into our map, right?
We can just put ELam in there.
So we're going to say modify.
OC: It's exactly the same as
ELet but without the evaluation I guess.
JW: Right. It's just going to return 0.
OC: Bit of a hack, but oh well!
[John thinks and types]
Elam should have two arguments.
Oh! The Show-er...
We're going to say... we're going to call...
I like the way Lisp does it.
[Silence].
Yehey! Unknown function double.
This is where we put in a little bit of our tracing.
It never showed it, so we didn't get to there...
We must have done...
Oh, nobody used the value,
that's why the trace didn't get...
Since no one is forcing the value that
means the insert is not happening either.
If it's just returning zero
it can elide out the rest.
OC: But we're in a monad, so it
should be forcing us to be sequenced.
JW:  Your right.
OC: Maybe in our function that reads from the file
we could print the environment after every step.
JW: Oh! Is that our problem?
OC: Yes, the file doesn't do what the REPL does.
JW: Ah, thank you.
In the file parser we need to do the
exact same thing we were doing before.
Which is: to call... Let's just copy and paste.
[John types]
That did not work.
For every line in the input, we parse the line,
and then execute it within
our state and print the result.
OC: Can we just flip back to the error we had again?
JW: Now we have a much different error.
We have regressed.
Let me see what version of
the code we were using previously.
Oh, the massager! We're not using the massager.
So I'm going to go ahead and use the view patterns.
OC: So view patterns here let us call
a function before binding a variable.
JW: Yes, I could just do this.
That's actually a silly use of view patterns.
Except that it's going to be a Maybe.
So we have to lift one level out and say...
"if it's Nothing, do nothing,
otherwise we have some String".
OC: We could use forM_ again there.
You can use forM_ over a maybe.
I think we have to use data.foldable
which in real world projects
that's exactly what I do.
Look at that! We evaled it.
OC: Wonderful.
JW: So we have Phi equaling 1 plus double...
We even have an error... We are missing a parenthesis
and yet we didn't get a syntax there.
OC: [Laughs]
JW: Let me see what happens if I do that directly.
Might as well do it this way.
Ah! The parse stops.
Because it has reached a
token it doesn't recognise, it ends.
Other parsers like Trifecta,
I could coax it to tell me what
the remainder of the input was.
I don't know how that's done in parsec
and I don't think we should worry about it just now.
[John thinks about what to do].
We can restrict our parser on the line by
line parser and say we want it to terminate at EOF.
OC: So that requires that we
successfully parse a line?
JW:  Right, so now I get unexpected.
Of course the line numbers are all
off, because we do this line by line.
There we go! So 1 plus 10... leave it...
5 times 5 is 25 OK.
So 26 divided by 2 should be 13. Alright!
I would say that's a good place for us to check in.
Function definitions and calling now work.
OC: Awesome!
OC: Now we're getting near the end of the session,
I wonder if we might try to
implement that Fibonacci function.
It's in one of these example files.
We should only need to redefine phi,
but we do need a square root operation.
Maybe we could introduce that
as a primitive in the language.
That should allow us to get all
the way to the bottom of this file.
JW: We should be able to do that easily.
Because we chose the higher
order abstract syntax notation.
That makes it easier for us to inject
what we would call built-ins into our language.
So all we need then is a parser,
and we're going to have an option...
let's extend funCall.
funCall will say: if name is 'sqrt'...
[John types]
I don't want to do it at call point, sorry.
I want to do it when we define the environment.
So new environment.
Instead of having an empty map,
we want a map where we can insert into square root.
And Elam, I just remind myself that ELams have a name.
And they go from an environment,
which we are not going to use,
and then we are going to call square root.
And we need to do this on an empty map.
We can call this a singleton.
See I have hlint down here
suggesting that I could say const sqrt
because I'm ignoring that parameter.
I still have an error, saying
I'm not using that language pragma.
Now we can say test what is the square root of 9.
OC: Excellent.
JW: If we go over to our file,
and we see now that we have...
[I was doing a lot of work in this little scratch file]
Phi should be fine.
Oh! We have a power operator here,
raising something to an exponent.
We need to quickly add that in.
It's rather like a multiplication.
OC: Yes, you can have the same precedence there.
JW: We're going to say EPow and EMul.
We'll use that as the same precedence.
We have EPow, and we're going
to get rid of some of our traces.
We have now reached a certain level of maturity
where we can drop tracing from our parser.
[Silence].
Now we want to go to wherever EMul was.
EPow is going to do star star, right?
Is that appropriate
for doubles? I'll just check.
[John types and mumbles].
I will take a look at this file again.
OC: Do we need a... Oh we have an evaluator I see.
Do you really want the return keyword?
Since the last expression of the
function is defined to be the value of the call.
OC: Yes, I think we're OK dropping that.
JW: We've  got parens, and we've got division, we've got phi and psi...
A global phi and a local psi.
Let's give it a try... Do you think it's going to work?
OC: I'm going to say no,
I don't think it will work [laughter].
JW:  So unknown variable N...
We're now making reference to a local variable.
That's a good thing, to check why isn't that happening.
When we defined...
OC: When we went into the lambda
we don't seem to be... we are extending the environment.
So we got the arg, as the name,
and we extended the environment.
We evaluate within that extended environment...
OC: Are we able to see which
line it's having this trouble with?
We've got quite a few "unexpected"s.
JW:  It's the definition of fib
that seems to be having the problem.
Column 3 or column 8.
It wasn't expecting the word fib after define.
Let me try that at the command line here.
See that works.
Let's reduce the problem here, get
rid of these ones that are before it.
OC: The let binding is definitely
working because we're seeing that.
[John thinks].
OC: This isn't a problem with
the comment dropping those?...
[John thinks].
Let's see if whitespace is consuming.
Oh! Whitespace only takes space into account.
We want it to be space or tab, or return or newline..
OC: Is it the leading
whitespace causing the problem?
Or are we stripping the
leading whitespace out as well?
JW: We should be stripping any whitespace
that occurs before and after the brace.
[John thinks].
Let's see if it would help to have
a semi colon in our function bodies.
[John types].
And that does not help.
I think the problem is outside of this.
We need to bring some tracing
back in... so trace "funBinding..1"
We're getting as far as parsing funBinding
seven, so it's not liking the closing brace.
[John thinks].
OC: That expected F assumes
that the define is a variable name.
And it's trying to do addition on that variable.
[Silence].
OC: Maybe if we just try to
do one expression in the definition
see if that gives us any more progress.
[Silence].
JW: Definitely not...
We're getting as far as seven.
[Silence].
[John mumbles].
OC: Or maybe trace it?
Oh thats right, trace...
[Silence].
No parse... what could that mean.
What do we have in our
show definition that's not right?
[Silence].
JW: Let's try parsing the single expression.
I think it's trying to parse
the funBinding and failing.
So it's trying to parse it as a funCall.
OC: But that's failing because it doesn't
see an open parenthesis right after define.
JW: Exactly and then it tries to do it as a variable.
I'm surprised it's not telling us...
"unknown variable".
OC: It's still trying to evaluate at that point.
We're failing in the parsing.
JW: Right, and because it's a trace, then it's going to...
It should read it as a variable shouldn't it?
OC: It is giving a variable called define.
And the next thing to do
is to look for a math operator.
JW: That's right. That's what
it's saying it's expecting to see.
Unexpected F wanted a math operator.
Because the define expression is failing,
because of a failure to parse "d".
[John thinks].
Ah, you know what...
We don't do multi line parsing yet.
We're handing these to the parser line by line.
OC: We should be able to put it all
in one line and then our test will be simple.
JW:  You would think.
OC: Let's try that first.
JW: So we're going to have to
break it into lines, strip out the comments,
and then put the lines back together.
OC:  If we just modify our test bc file for now
we should be able to join four lines into one.
JW: You mean in here?
OC: Yes.
Because we have a semi colon
between them we might be OK.
JW: I don't know if I kept the semi colon.
Oh I did keep it.
Ah, very good!
So it's 1, 2 and 55, correct.
OC: Yes, almost 55 anyway [laughter].
JW: Close enough for government work.
We don't have multi line working just yet
but we do have a way to do separators.
And since you're probably going
to be typing these at a REPL anyway,
This probably makes more
sense for things to fit on one line.
So, here's our file, we can show that...
[I can get rid of that little devil at the beginning]
We can show for this file, we do
get a close approximation [laughter].
It's just one of those things.
So to wrap this up we need a way
to execute this from the command line.
If I go into my parser and look at
this REPL function we have been calling.
Really that IS our main.
If I now go to bcalc and say GHC
let's compile it with optimization on,
parser is my main module
If I now go to bcalc and say GHC
let's compile it with optimization on,
parser is my main module
I want to call this mybc
because there is already a system bc.
And now if I call mybc...
OC: This is also reading from standard input then?
Yes, in theory, we can pipe that
file we have been working on into it.
Maybe let's see what we get with that?
[Silence].
JW: [Laughter]. Not quite!
OC: I guess our REPL
doesn't deal with comments like that.
Let's try this outside of Emacs, you never know.
JW:  No.
OC: I think our REPL isn't dealing with the
comments within the file, and that kind of stuff.
That's cool, I guess we should wrap up then.
OC: What are the kind of things that stand
out to you: the itches you want to scratch?
JW: If I wanted to build
this into a nice toy calculator
I would first want to get rid of all the
repetition in dealing with calling of parsec.
I would factor that out with some other
function and all these would call as helpers.
The next thing would be...
there are some inefficiencies in here...
The fact that in our map type,
we have a map from text to expression.
So as I mentioned earlier,
we would always be re-evaluating variables.
I would rather have them as constants
that immediately reduce to doubles.
At the point where we're
evaluating our when we see an EVar.
When we see a let, instead of
putting the body of the let into the map,
we could evaluate it, stick it in an ENum and then put
that in the map, and that would achieve what I want.
OC: You would basically be
doing a kind of memoization then?
JW:  Yes, something like that, it hurts not to do it.
So we will just say this:
[John mumbles as he writes].
ENum wants a double and it got
an expression because it wants B prime.
That would be one of the things
I would do... too easy not to do it.
I would switch to using a real tokeniser for parsec
because it would clear up some problems we ran into,
and make the code briefer and easier to see.
You also have the ability to define
languages in parsec so you can say
what's the precedence my
various operators should be,
and it will figure out how to
parse them all in the correct order.
I might move to a functor fixed point
representation of my Expr data type here.
So that my evaluators get easier to write.
Make a pretty printer.
The tool that we're modeling this after is bc.
In bc it will echo back out to you
the expression in pretty-printed form,
So I'd like to do that as well.
And I would like tests that
every expression when printed,
can read back in, and then
reprint as the same expression.
That's pretty much where I would go with this.
But I don't know, if I'm trying
to compete with Mathematica,
so I would be happy with something
that just works nicely on the command line.
OC: Yes, OK that's fantastic. Thanks a lot.
Captions produced by Bonnie Roworth