NARRATOR: Welcome to Peer to Peer,
where you can watch how
experts solve tech problems.
In this bonus material,
independent Agile coach Amy Wagner
introduces the Agile Manifesto.
ANY WAGNER: A lot of things I'm
inspired by come from other peoples work.
Lots of techniques, some principles,
and values from the Agile Manifesto.
And even from the leading
software development world as well.
So the first thing I would normally
look to do, when I'm working with a new person,
is just to step back to the Agile Manifesto.
And this looks very much like an
early 2000 website, as you can see here.
There was a bunch of people who got
together in 2001 and came up with the manifesto
for Agile software development.
And I think a lot of people don't
take the time to go over these things,
When they're delivering projects with Agility.
Sometimes they will go straight to
Scrum, or a very specific methodology.
So let's go through this, just
to remind ourselves what it is.
The high level...
ANNA BOWERS: The principles. AW: Exactly.
So the Manifesto... they say:
We are uncovering better ways of developing
software by doing it and helping others do it.
Through this work we have come to value:
Individuals and interactions
over processes and tools.
Working software over
comprehensive documentation.
Customer collaboration
over contract negotiation.
And responding to change over following a plan.
And what they've got at the
bottom, a bit of a caveat there,
that yes, things on the right here are important,
but things on the left is where the
emphasis should be as they are more important.
So just thinking on that
for a second... working software.
I think that's where the emphasis is if
you just look at the second one there.
Rather than writing a big long
technical specification about building the thing,
we want to get much closer and inaud about making the software, and doing the thing.
People used to put months
or years into designing an upfront idea
Maybe it would be a thing of beauty
that  you would frame and put on the wall.
[Laughter]
And still at that point
it's still something on paper.
And not what we are ultimately aiming
for, which is to build some software
and get it out there to users.
And the other thing worth noting
here is the responding to change part.
I think culturally that can be hard if you
come from a traditional product manager world.
This inaud thing, did you ever hear those words?
AB: Yes, you define it all
upfront and then new things come
and that's called scope creep I suppose isn't it?
AW: Exactly, and we've got mission creep uhm...
But maybe it's like that for a reason, maybe
we're just continuing to try to improve a service.
And rather than sticking to what
we thought the thing was originally
And guarding that project plan or inaud.
This challenges to respond to
change in user needs and the market.
And respond to changing technologies and
language and best practices, things like that.
AB: OK.
AW: So, the other thing I was going to look
at here quickly was the principles of the Manifesto.
There's twelve of these, and
rather than go through them verbatim,
let's just pick out a few that
could be interesting, or worth noting.
The first one, get it out the door as fast as possible.
Early and continuous delivery of
the thing, the software, the content,
all of that stuff that becomes the final product,
rather than delivering documentation about it.
Again, we talked about changing requirements...
we welcome them even late in development.
That's quite a cultural change from
the more traditional design up front.
And then we've got do it frequently, from
a couple of weeks to a couple of months.
inaud we've been a week or two week time period. sometimes a month.
With a preference for the shorter timescale.
Have you though about how frequently you wanted...
AB: Well the other projects I'm working with,
(and I'll be sharing the inaud source,
which is one of the challenges we have),
they work to three week sprints,
so we'll probably be mirroring that.
They're already in sprints with other products
and I'll be mirroring that, so yes three weeks.
AW: Three weeks, ok cool.
AB: We've started off
other projects a little bit shorter,
but three weeks is workable
for our team, so still quite short.
AW: Yes, it is, it's not three
months is it, or three years. [Laughter]
Some people launch after three
years of thinking about something.
Yes, so that's great, we'll get into
to the detail of that in a little bit.
The other thing here is talking
about business people and developers
working together daily throughout the project.
It sounds like your
development team is on site with you?
AB: They are yes.
Do you mean business people as in stakeholders,
other people around the business
that have something to do with the project?
AW: Yes ideally.
As product manager you're going to be the
person who helps to translate those requirements.
But if at all possible, you can bring
the subject matter experts into the room.
And the people who are owning
that strategy for the learning tool.
If the inaud get's a chance to work with him closely on a day to day basis
I think that's the most ideal situation.
AB: That would be awesome.
AW: A lot of people do that by inviting them to
key meetings throughout your three week process.
The other bit here is about motivated individuals.
AB: Lots of sweets! [Laughter]
AW: Or carrots!
AB: Carrots, oh my gosh that's very healthy.