NARRATOR: Welcome to Peer to Peer,
where you can watch how
experts solve tech problems.
Our guest today is Amy Wagner,
who is an independent Agile coach and consultant.
And a co-author of the Minimum Viable book.
Amys' client today is Anna Bowers,
who's a product manager at Dorling Kindersley,
an international publishers.
Anna is managing the
development of a new digital product,
which has lots of different
stakeholders and a new development team.
Her company is used to sharing
physical products on a fixed timetable.
For this new digital product, they're
interested in adopting a more agile methodology
and they're keen to get some coaching from Amy.
In this Peer to Peer session, we'll
see how Amy coaches a client on a new project.
She'll work through 3 Agile techniques
that she felt were appropriate in this case:
the Spine, Inception, and Impact Mapping.
[Chapter 1]
AMY WAGNER: So Anna maybe you
can tell us a little bit about your product.
ANNA BOWERS: Yes, so I work
for a publisher based in the UK.
And I sit on the web team as a product manager.
And we're just about to
kick off an exciting new product.
And we've done about 3 or 4 months of
discovery work, and we're looking to get into sprint.
It's going to be an online learning tool.
It started with a print element and we're
going to take some of that and put it online,
so there's a digital element:
and that's the bit I'm working on.
It consists of a course book
and some practice books.
We need to host audio files
that go with the course book online
And we also need to put
some practice exercises online.
And potentially monetize
them and create user accounts.
And track progress of the users.
AW: If you were to describe your
product in one sentence... how would you do that?
AB: Alright, let me have a go.
So it's an online self study tool for adult learners...
that let's them track their progress.
[New Chapter]
AW: Right, so Anna, let's
do an exercise called the spine.
The spine is something that you should
be doing with your team and your stakeholders