[Chapter 02: Executing a build by hand.]
So we have the code checked out over here.
So we've got a couple of files.
I know we're going to need
coffeescript and also uglify,
so let's make a package.json
with those things in it.
[Silence]
TS: What will the package.json allow you to do?
JG: Package.json is what npm
the node packaging system uses.
And one of its functions is
to manage your dependencies.
There are two sets of dependencies,
dependencies and dev-dependencies.
Dependencies are things that your
program uses in run time in production,
and dev-dependencies are things you use
for testing or examples, or what have you.
So coffeescript and uglify are
not going to be part of the tool,
they're things you can run with the tool.
They'll be part of the examples so I'll put them in dev.
TS: OK
JC: So save that, and if you run
npm install it should install them for you.
So that's good.
Packages that provide executables
npm puts those in `node_modules/.bin`.
And they just sit inside the project.
So we should be able to compile each
of those things into a javascript file.
And then minify them and concatenate the results.
So were going to need to do...
[James thinks]
Let's make another directory inside there and move...
Can I do it that way? We'll soon find out.
TS: Looks like it.
JC: OK so those are in source,
we'll make another directory called lib.
So I want to run node modules.bin with coffee...
I want to compile and put the output in example lib.
And compile example source
with complimenter coffee.
TS: So what's that done?
JC: That should have compiled that
file in to the example lib.directory.
So that has showed up.
Look at example source
complimenter that has some code in it.
So example lib complimenter should
look the same, but in  JavaScript.
That does look reasonable.
And then we'll do the same with the other file.
[James types]
I'll use hello.
[Silence]
So that's compiled it.
So the next thing to do with those files .... [he thinks].
Given that one of the requirements of
the brief is that the build should be lazy,
and only do steps when they're required.
The way that make does that is, any
intermediate results, you put in files.
Because  it can then check
the modified time of the files,
and if it's less recent, than any of the
inputs to that file, it will rebuild it.
So, to minify something...
Again, we can use inaud run uglify.
I think it's these flags.
Those flags have compress which is...
Let's see what the help says.
inaud
[Silence]
So – C enables compressor options.
You have to tell that to make it minify the file.
TS: Right.
JC: The option called m has not been found.
It's up there... It's mangle... Which means
it will do things like shift variable names.
And – O is for output inaud file.
TS: So is uglify going to be responsible for concatenating these
or does concatenation
come after the uglification?
JC: That's the bit I'm not sure about actually.
Whether you can give it multiple input files
and have it write them all to the same place.
TS: It seems that the
coffeescript compiler is one to one.
You give it one coffee script
file and one JavaScript file.
JC: Exactly.
So the first line here says the usage
is that they contain multiple input files.
So why don't we try to get it to do that.
I'll just remove those.
cmo example/bundle.js
example/lib/*
And we'll see what goes on in there.
OK that looks like it has some code in it.
It will have mangled all the names and everything
so whatever I was looking for in here...
It will only reduce the size of local variables,
because it doesn't matter
what those are externally,
but method name should stay the same.
So I think there is a say... yes inaud same method... and its got that going in if we want it.  So this looks like the output that we want to produce.
TS: Whats the trade off between concatenating and minifying them all in one step versus...