Welcome to Peer to Peer
where you can hone your skills
by watching live coding videos.
Our guest today is James Coglan.
Author of JavaScript Testing Recipes.
And creator of open source projects such
as Faye and web socket driver.
Our host is Tom Stuart.
And the challenge that he has set
for James is called Building a build tool.
Chapter 01.
The Challenge.
Tom Stuart: So James would you
like to start by reading the challenge?
James Coglan: Sure, so the challenge is:
Create a tool for automating the
steps required to build a javascript project.
A sample project is
supplied with coffescript files.
These need to be compiled to
javascript then minified and concatenated.
The build tool should be able to accept
generalised instructions for
carrying out each of these steps.
Where possible the build tool should be lazy, only
running steps if they if they produce fresh output.
So this is quite a lot like the make build
system so I'll be taking inspiration from that.
Like figuring out how you implement those steps,
if you were to do that sort of thing yourself.
There's coffeescript,
so we'll need the coffee compiler.
And it has to be minified so I'll
use uglify.js for that... and concatenated.
either uglify will do that, or I'll use cat,
or something like that. [James thinks]
But I suppose a good thing to do
first is to run these things by hand.
TS: Right.
JC: And see that they work
before we try to automate them.