Chapter 12.
Returning fresh mtime from a regenerated Target.
JC: If we go back to our code.
What do we need to do? We've got
these mtimes so we need to store that.
Ensure updated dependencies.
We've said in our test that calling build
on a dependency will return its' mtime.
So let's store that in here when we build the
dependencies and call map so we get the values.
And then here we can say return unless any of
the dependent times are greater than our own.
I think that will be OK.
What I do need to do for this to work...
The build method will need to return mtime.
But I haven't written a test that requires that yet.
I'm just thinking how I would force myself
to do that, but we'll get to that in a second.
"undefined method `>' for nil:NilClass
So that must mean that I've
stubbed mtime to somehow return (hmm)...
So this is Target spec 33.
What's going on in there?
Oh yes, in this test those build
targets are not returning anything.
TS: So they're getting nil back and
then trying to compare it to something.
JC: Exactly. I think this is the point where I need
to put a value that actually makes sense in here.
[Silence]
Now everything passes.
This is a bit of an illusion because it doesn't (hmm)...
I'm surprised that the integration test
works because build isn't returning the mtime.
[James thinks]
TS: It's the integration test of the previous
behaviour that you're expecting to break?
JC: Yes.
That's probably because in the integration
test we're building things that don't exist.
So it isn't hitting that code path.
TS: So we don't have an integration
test for this laziness behaviour right?
JC: No.
Dependent targets.
[James thinks]
When one target depends on another...
We could put a context in here that creates one.txt
and then sees if the second one will build.
context when one target
already exists do file one.text.
Let's just make it include one rather than from
where the files it was previously derived from are.
No let's not do that. I don't want this test
to get into setting mtimes on various files.
They're going to be created in a certain order .
But the time resolution on those
time stamps on the files is only a second.
So sometimes, depending on whether your
test execution overlaps a second boundary,
there will sometimes be the same value and
sometimes not. The ordering is not predictable.
To be safe, I'm going to make this have the value
that it would have if you had built it from source.
Builds the final target successfully.
I suppose successfully is implicit
when you're writing any sort of test but...
Yeah...
I could just do that.
This is still saying when you build the second
target it should have that content based on that.
But this ought to trigger the
first target to try to check the...
No, the first target will try to check the
mtimes of the files a and b that it depends on.
and it will get nil from their build
methods, so this should fall over.
Yes, so a second error out of that.
TS: So this is not yet a test
of the laziness functionality,
but it is exercising more of the code
than the previous integration test was?
JC: Yes. That integration test makes sure
that you can rebuild a partially built system.
It means you need a test for
build that returns the mtime.
Going back to our unit tests, where did
we have something with a dependency?
This doesn't necessarily mean
there are dependencies.
There's actually two cases for this.
If the file already exists and is up
to date it should return its existing mtime.
but if you had to rebuild it, it
should return time.now, I guess.
So we can build those in to here.
So when the dependencies are newer than the target
it returns the later of the dependencies.
It could either return the latest
of the dependencies build times,
but building a target will take time so it might be
a few seconds later than its' dependencies were.
Or, if its' dependencies were touched a very long
time ago, but they're still newer than you are...
We might get into like... Something
appears older than it actually is.
So I think I should probably return time.now.
He types then pauses..
In this context we've already stubbed out time.
TS: This reminds me of something I was confused about, in the build self we get the mtime of the possibly stale file, but you're talking about not the mtime of that file at that point but almost the end point of that file after its been regenerated.