Chapter 10.
Checking the mtime of the Target.
The other thing is they should be lazy.
So if you run the build and make no changes
then run it again nothing should happen.
Builds take a long time as your project grows,
especially minifying
javascript, it can get very slow.
A simple way to do this is to look
at the modified times of the files,
and if any of the things that you depend on
are newer than your own file, then you rebuild.
Otherwise you don't.
TS: Just to clarify can you talk us through...
You've already addressed one case
about unnecessary work being done.
You've made some change that
ensures something doesn't get done twice.
And now you're making another change which
is also about something not being done twice,
but in a different way.
TS: So the change you've already made,
what kind of case has that dealt
with that hasn't been dealt with here?
JC: If you have a build that has say a diamond shape...
So you have the thing that you want.
And that depends on two things.
Then they both depend on one thing.
So when you call build here it
will call build on these two,
and then they will both call build on that thing.
What I just did was I made it so that
those two builds to the same target
don't cause work to be duplicated
within the same build process.
We're now talking about
when you run your build twice.
That the second time you run it, if you haven't
changed anything, no work should need to be done.
It skips you waiting around for things
that don't need to be recompiled;
or whatever it is that your doing.
TS: OK, Cool.
JC: It's duplicate work within
one build across multiple builds.
When you have things going across multiple builds,
like multiple executions of your build tool,
you don't have that information in memory.
We solved the first problem by
putting a flag in memory on an object
to say don't do this again, you've already done it.
When you have multiple invocations of something
you have to rely on some state
that exists between processes.
In this case that state could be the
modified times of the files you're looking at.
That's why basing this around
files as the primary thing...
It's good because it gives you an almost
free way to check that the files are up to date.
TS: OK.
JC: So we have these tests for when
there's dependencies. We could also have ...
What would we like to do here?
So this is the thing that tells the things to build...
Which is what we want to do.
We should then probably also say that
depending on the result of what those calls is,
what is this target going to do?
So if any of those calls return a time
that's higher than the time that I have,
then I should quit.
TS: What does higher than mean?
JC: (I always get this backwards
in time!). I mean later than.
You have your coffee script
file and your JavaScript file.
If the coffee script file was modified
later than the JavaScript file,
that means the JavaScript file is
out of date, so it will recompile it.
If it's the other way round
that means your JavaScript file
has presumably been generated since
the last time you modified the coffee script.
And you don't need to do any more work.
So let's say... We can have some context inside here.
When the dependencies are newer than the target - do.
OK
So how am I going to model that?
We can say that we allow the first dependency
to receive build and return time now plus 5 minutes.
Likewise with the second dependency
to return time now plus 2 minutes.
The target itself is going to take
those times it got from the dependencies
and then compare them to what it has.
And to do that it's probably going to call file.mtime.
TS: What does mtime mean?
JC: It's the modification time.
The unix file system; every file has
several time stamps attached to it.
And one of those time stamps
is the last time it was modified.
You also get the last time it was
accessed, and some other things.
When you write to a file, the file
system updates that time stamp
so you can tell the last time it was changed.
TS: Is this the point at which it needs the
pathname that you've been passing in all along?
JC: Yes. I introduced that quite prematurely.
This is the first time that we need it.
Maybe the first thing we should do is
assert that it checks the time of its own pathname.
Checks the mtime of its own file.
So we expect file to receive mtime with pathname.
I'll change that up here to
make it less of a generic name.
Or target pathname.
[Silence]
The result inaud sometime,
we don't really care what it is.
So when you call target.build that should happen.
I've just realised this test
isn't part of this context...
It doesn't need these things to be true.
So we can move that out.
TS: Is it something that
always has to happen regardless?
JC: Yes. I'm thinking this
through a little bit in reverse.
Thinking it's going to look at its dependencies
times and then compare them to itself.
Therefore I should write a test to say
that it asks the file system for some information
But I realise that wasn't part of this.
So we can check that it does this and then
given that the dependencies return some values,
that compare with what it knows about itself.
TS: I'm having trouble conceptualizing these
dependencies that were built in the future.
But it's relative to what you're imagining. We're
imagining the Time.now is the mtime of this target.
JC: Yes and I'm just doing that because hard coding
time values always ends up blowing up in my face.
You know, six months later your
build starts failing for no reason,
so I usually do them as offsets
from wherever you are right now.
I could have put them in the past but it doesn't
make much difference, it's the relative offset.
JC: This will fail now because we're not doing that, we're not showing the mtime. This won't work.