Chapter 05.
Unit testing the Target class.
JC: So this is an example that I
should probably turn into a test now.
There's not really enough here that there's
any integration vs unit test separation .
There's only a tiny amount of code.
So I think I'll start by moving target into the
source code of the project and write a test for it.
Let's make a thing called lib,
and let's move scratch target into...
No let's make a directory called  lib.fakemake,
and then move scratch target to that.
Then also name spacer... Like that.
OK.
And we're going to want some
tests, and something to run them.
Go to Bundler and get some gems.
I've got the gem file and put rspec in there.
Save that, and install it into the project.
[Silence]
OK.
Did I make a spec directory – yes I did.
[Silence]
So let's try to write a test
for this file, I called it a target..
[Silence]
Obligatory require 'spec_helper'.
and (not end) which I've not written but...
This will require_relative 'lib/fakemake',
which also doesn't exist so I'm going to create it.
Module FakeMake.
I usually use autoloads for these, so it loads things lazily.
[Silence]
And path.
And then autoload target
from root + fakemake target.
That ought to be enough to load things.
So if we go back to target spec and...
Describe FakeMake target.
Does that at least run.
Yes, it didn't complain about anything.
So, looking back at the code,
there's already a few scenarios here.
The only thing this actually does, I suppose, is that
it takes a list of instructions and executes them.
But now we're coming to a test we can
pass in some alternative output thing.
[Silence]
I'll make that be that - output.
The test I have in mind is if you write
a target with no instructions that's fine.
If you write a target with an
instruction it gets printed and executed.
And if you write one with many
instructions, they all get executed.
Although we should also check to see what happens
if you write an instruction that doesn't work.
So system will return nil if you
run a command that has a non-zero exit status.
Rather than shelling out, running stuff on the
system we can stubb system to work or not work.
So make a few variables.
This value wont really matter
it's just something to pass in.
The target will be target.new, which takes the
pathname and the instructions and the output.
Let's also make an output for it to use.
And then we can have some scenarios.
Let's describe the build method.
When there are no instructions we
said that nothing should happen.
[Silence]
It should not print anything.
And expect output not to receive puts.
And target build.
[Silence]
I'll make a new shell over here.
Ah! I didn't put my ruby on the path.
[Silence]
OK, that should...
I'm not doing the good TDD thing here.
I should probably see this break just
to check if that test is doing something.
So let's have this do output.puts something bad.
That does fail so that's fine.
And it should not execute anything.
[Silence]
We're calling system on target
itself... It's a kernel method.
I could have called puts on target
itself and stubbed it in the same way here.
But that also means... Like at some point
we're going to have a graph of these things.
And you might not have direct access in your
test to the actual thing that's printing something.
So you want to be able to
pass this output object along.
So it's a thing you have a handle on in your
test and you can make assertions against it.
TS: Right
JC: Maybe I should do the same thing with execution.
I could tell kernel to expect to receive system.
TS: And then pass kernel in as another argument, or...?
JC: That's what I'm not sure about.
Because I'm not sure I think I should
leave it for now, until it becomes a problem.
The output thing... I knew I didn't want
stuff printing things in the middle of my tests,
whereas you also don't want the unit
tests to go and execute system commands.
Because I've used a string io here for the output,
those put commands are just going to go
into the ether and not be used anywhere.
We don't have any instructions yet,
but when we do and I write some of the test for
printing, it will then go and execute the thing.
I'll have to stub out system to make it not do that.
But I'm not sure that the object that we're
calling it on is the problem in that situation.
You'd have to do that in any case.
So the target should not receive
the system when you build it.
[Silence]
OK, two passing tests.
So, when there is an instruction
let the instruction be...
It doesn't really matter what it is... Let's say echo.
We're never going to execute it, so it doesn't
matter, as long as it's some unique value.
And that should be an array shouldn't it?
It prints the instruction.
And we expect the output to
receive puts with instruction once.
And it executes the instruction.
[Silence]
With the instruction once.
I go back and forth without
saying something should be called.
Whether I should say how many times...
But in this case I think it's important that you...
Because these things have side effects, the
number of times you call them is important.
[Silence]
And I also said that system
should be stubbed in any case,
even if you're not making assertions on it.
And that should probably happen
in all cases so I'll put that at the top.
TS: So if you didn't do this, one of those tests
you wrote would actually try to execute that?
JC: Exactly... Well, let's run it
and you should actually see this,
because system inherits
standard out from your Ruby process.
And you will see an instruction pop up in the
tests when they're run, because of this, I think.
Undefinable local variable method
instruction... So I made a typo somewhere.
Where did I do that?
Target spec 6... OK.
Oh I've only said instruction there...
OK.
Undefined... Ah yes, right.
I've used instruction everywhere which is what
I mean, but the constructor wants a plural.
So let's do that, and remove the array from here.
And that should be better.
So yes it's printed 'an instruction' while the tests
are running, so it's actually executed that command.
So let's stop it being able to
do that by stubbing system out.
One good thing about calling
it on target and not on kernel,
is that I generally dislike
stubbing out global things.
This is working with files a lot... We're
not directly working with files in Ruby yet,
but you get various gems that will stub out
the file system, or Net::HTTP or whatever it is.
I find those usually get in the way somewhere.
You really want only this test, this tiny
piece of code, to be isolated from something.
For example, if you use something
that stubs out of the file system,
you can't use `require` any more,
so your code stops loading.
So the fact that this only affects the
object under test is appealing to me.
So if we run those tests now it's not printing stuff
in the middle of them because it's not calling echo.
So that's better.