Chapter 14.
Using FakeMake to build the sample project.
TS: So where does that get us to?
JC: Well if we go back to the
original example that we were given,
I was hacking around with the script trying to
decide what the user interface to this should be.
So this will now be lib/fakemake.
[Silence]
Now... With the target... there's two source files.
I will need the target for both of those.
These are in the namespace now.
[Silence]
Was it complimenter? TS: Yes.
JC: OK, so those are two targets with
no dependencies and no build instructions.
They have hello JavaScript. Which is
derived from hello.coffee and you build that.
We could make a target for the lib directory,
not sure if I'll go through extracting that.
Or maybe I will... Yes.
Lib is erh.......
Actually, directories do have mtimes.
Yes, target new example lib;
which has no dependencies.
And is built by calling make dir  p example lib.
Which means you can remove that.
Which means that goes that way.
Let's clone that rather than...
[Silence]
So complementor.js depends on that.
Let's do that one and then...
So complimenter.js depends on
complimenter.coffee. That all looks OK.
And bundle.js depends on two JavaScript files and
you build it by calling that and then you build it.
OK so...
This was in scratch test rb.
As always, let's remove
everything that we had before.
The tree just has the source code in it.
If we run ruby scratch test.
Uninitialized constant target.
Oh, I didn't namespace everything did I?
[Silence]
It's run everything. And
we've got everything in there.
And example bundle contains
the code that we wanted.
If we run it again, because we've
made it lazy enough, it should happen.
And indeed nothing happens.
Because we've made it this recursive structure. If anything does need rebuilding it should rebuild it but not rebuild everything. So if i use touch, which sets the mtime on a file to now, and creates it if it's not there. If I touch example lib hello.js. Or rather, let's touch hello coffee. Sorry.
TS: So this is simulating you having edited it?
JC: Yes. So if I touch that. Hello.js is now up to date. The compliment.js isn't. So I should run the coffee compiler once and then run uglify. Because the whole bundle is out of date as well because you changed the source file. So it should recompile what needs to be recompiled but only those files.
TS: Ok.
JC: And we see there that it has run coffee once on hello.coffee. but not on complimenter.
TS: Right.
JC: So that seems to be doing what we want. I'm just going to check because I haven't revisited this file in a while. It is the changes we made that made it do this.
If I delete this line, then it should become unlazy. It should do all the work every time.
It does, you can see it churning away there. I'll reinstate that line, and it becomes lazy again.
TS: Excellent.
JC: So that seems to do what we want.
TS: That's great. Well congratulations on getting it working, that's really good. That seems like a good place for us to stop. Thanks very much, I've really enjoyed this.
JC: Me too, thanks Tom.