Chapter 09.
Being lazy within a build.
TS: So what next?
JC: We've got dependencies so the
next thing to do... The build has to lazy.
And once you have dependencies, and
you know what your file depends on,
you can tell if your file is up to date because you
can ask your dependencies if they're up to date.
That also introduces the problem of... When a target
builds it tells all the other targets to build.
So what If multiple things
depend on the same target?
In that situation something will be told
to build multiple times, which is wasteful.
So we could write a test that says if you call build
twice on a target, it only runs its' command once.
That would be good.
And we also want a test that says if you try to build
a target that's newer than the things it depends on.
Then that should also not do anything.
So I think I'll deal with the first of those first.
So if we go back into our tests:
spec/fakemake/target_spec.
We have dealing with dependencies.
You don't necessarily need
dependencies for what I was just talking about.
You just want to say if you call build
twice, it should run its' instructions once.
So we can put that into the
case where there is an instruction.
So it only executes the instructions once do.
So that's essentially this test over again.
Except that we call this twice.
This ought to fail.
Which it does.
One thing about this test (I'm glad
I did this); it should receive this once.
It's a side effect we care about
how many times it's called.
But rspec says it was called 2 times.
That ought to be reasonably easy to fix
if we go back into our source code.
If we look at build self we can
store a flag in here that says
I've been built you don't need to do anything.
So return if already built.
And then set that to true.
And then that's passing. So I think I'll commit that.