Chapter 13.
Returning original mtime from an up to date Target.
So, that was one case, we did the case where when you are forced
to rebuild yourself, you return your regeneration time.
If you are already up to date you
should return your target, your original time,
so that you don't imply that you're newer than
you are and force things downstream to get rebuilt.
So where was that; lazy build exe.
When the dependencies are newer than
the target it returns a new time at the file.
When the dependencies are older than the target
it returns the mtime of the unmodified file.
In that case we expect
target.build to equal the target time.
[Silence]
So... It's not.
TS: Do you think this was a rather unfair test
because actually those two times would be the same
if you hadn't run the instructions,
the mtime of the file wouldn't have changed.
So you've set up the test in such a way
that you've assumed that the mtime changes.
JC: What I'm testing, by accident, is that
it returns the result of the second mtime call,
which I've said in the thing is
the original time plus 10 minutes.
But what it's done is returned me...
Expected 1712, got 1722 just because
it's returning the value of the second call.
TS: Which would be fine, but it's not fine.
JC: No. [Laughter]
So, is that what I really mean?
Is that an accident or is it what I really mean?
That it returns the result of the second mtime call.
Because what else can you say; you're
not actually interacting with the system.
You're not running these commands;
we're not actually changing any files.
Is there some other way that I can say
"it should return the same time as before"?
I guess, if you decided not to run the build, you
don't need to run the File.mtime a second time.
TS: Right. I suppose it does depend on whether
you care about mtime being run twice or not.
Do you feel that it's important it only
gets run as many times as necessary?
JC: Well, this feature that we're working on is all
about doing as little work as possible I suppose.
I mean it is a very cheap operation, but it
still hits disc, and you know hitting disc is bad.
I'm probably worrying about it more than I ought to.
The question that I actually have is how
you test this in an accurate way.
It's not just working by
accident, it's actually correct.
TS: Is it possible to get it to have the
behaviour that you specified in your test
or are you gonna have to relax your
test in order to do anything?
JC: Well I could stub it so that it
returns the same value both times
but then if it does that, from reading the test
you can't tell which of those values it's returning.
So that is not helpful.
I could make it so the code caches the first call to mtime
and returns that if it decides not to do any work.
TS: Right. Oh, so mean that you could have an instance
variable where your initial mtime gets stored
and then if it does the build it updates that mtime
and returns whichever one of those 'won'.
JC: Yes.. I think I'll do that.
I've accidentally swapped my
terminals around. Nevermind!
So if I go back into lib/fakemake/target.
We can make this just return mtime.
Then we can assign that
to an instance variable there.
And make that an instance variable there.
Then at the end of this we can say
mtime = file.mtime with the pathname.
This will now implicitly return mtime [laughter]
because it's the last thing that build calls.
But I want build to be the
recipe of the steps that you do.
[Silence]
Expected two times with arguments.
Yeah, so that's where I've got hmm...
TS: Is this the change you had to
make to un-break the test before?
JC: Yes, maybe I should remove that
and fix this specifically where it is done.
TS: Well previously you amended your test
to say that it always receives mtime twice.
but now you've improved your
code so that it only receives it once
in a case where it only needs to receive it once.
So you've optimized away the second of those mtimes.
JC: Yes.
OK, let's try something else.
In this case it's called twice.
[Silence]
We could make it so this is defined
to be called once in this scenario.
And it just returns that.
So when the dependencies are newer it calls
mtime twice and returns the second return value.
In this case it only returns it once.
No, wait, that's not actually true, it does...
No, it only calls mtime again if the things
are newer, so this ought to be fine.
Time always makes me confused.
TS: Where's this failure coming from?
[James thinks]
JC: There is probably a test...
So we've stubbed it out globally.
We said it was allowed to be called twice.
This is the test that checks the
mtime of its own file, that's that one.
TS: But you only put the twice
in there to stop that test breaking.
JC: That's true. But now I've specified it more strongly
in those tests, this ought to not be necessary.
TS: Well then the change you made in the the implementation was
so that it doesn't get called twice unless it needs to be.
JC: Yes.
OK, so everything's green, so we should
check what we've done and make a commit.
A few things have changed:
we've made build return mtime.
We have then used that
to make it skip building itself.
And then we've made a new mtime at the end.
Oh, there's that method I extracted that
isn't actually needed. Let's get rid of that.
[Silence]
(That's not needed)
Yes. So we've returned mtime.
Made it skip if everything's up to date.
And everything else is tests.
OK.