Chapter 4./nSketching the API of a Target class.
I'm just going to make a scratch
directory here and try something out.
Yes,I'm thinking I want to do
something like this; require scratch target.
And hello_js is a target with a path.
We've not doing Haskel,(whoops).
The minimum... It has a parse name
which is the file it's going to generate.
and then it has a list of commands
that are how to generate that thing.
TS: What do you mean by target here?
JC: A target is a file (I guess I'm borrowing
some nomenclature from make here),
but a target is any of the files in your system.
So when you talk about hello.js is
derived from hello.coffee, hello.js is the target.
However coffee could also be a
target inaud other things.
They can either derived things or
primary things, like your source code.
TS: I suppose in this case hello.js is both a target
and also it's going to be the input to the target.
JC: Exactly. So there's a recursion there.
And you want these things to compose in that
way so you can make targets out of other targets.
[Silence]
In Ruby you could do this, for example
by putting a block here. Like system erm...
What way round do you do this... [he types].
That would work, but I'm leaning toward
making this string be data rather than blocks.
Just because it's quite common to do inaud
Here we've duplicated this pathname
example source hello.js. That's it's coffee isn't it.
The idea here is that we've duplicated.
This is the directory that the target lives in.
If you're doing make you can do that... So $@ is the
pathname of the target your currently building.
And there's various functions so dir is the
function that gives you the directory of that.
I'm not going to get do that yet,
but it means that I don't necessarily want
to provide a block that just runs this code.
I want to provide this code as data,
because it might need to be further
interpreted by the system before being executed.
TS: So if it's a block it's some opaque
code that can't then be modified.
JC: Yes, I want it to be data.
So I'm going to put that in an array.
TS: Is the expectation at this point
that you will pass that to system... Right now?
JC: Exactly
So if I make a target and build
it, then I want it to BE built.
But the name of the thing I'm building and
the way in which it gets built are both data now,
so you could put anything in it.
TS: Why did you make it an array?
JC: That's a good question, there's only one command.
So we possibly don't need an array.
There is one thing I've missed out, when I deleted
that code earlier, I left that directory out didn't I?
So we need to make sure that directory
exists before we compile anything into it.
So let's also make that directory part of the thing.
You can see how this becomes repetitive because
you mention the same things over and over again.
That aught to work from a clean slate now
because that's all the commands that need
to be run to set up the directory and compile code.
I want this script, when it's run, to make that file.
[Silence]
If I run this it will get no such file scratch target.
As I expected, scratch target.rb. OK.
So you need a target class.
And that's going to take the
pathname of the thing we're building.
And a serve instructions.
So: undefined method `build` for Target... ok.
I want to build the thing and like you said we could pass each of those strings into system and it ought to run them.
Types.
And a serve instructions.
So: undefined method `build` for Target... ok.
I want to build the thing and like you said we could pass each of those strings into system and it ought to run them.
Types.