Chapter 03.
Automating build steps with a shell script.
OK so we know the things that we
want to run... We have the rough steps.
So for example, if I wrote this as a shell script...
[Silence]
We know that we want to run
node_modules/.bin/coffee-script
With compiler and put the output in example/lib
with example source complimenter.coffee
And then we also want to do that for...
Have I got coffee?
Before we do that it would be a good idea to
make sure that the output directory exists.
So we'll do that and then compile the coffeescripts.
Once we have those...
Uglifyjs.
[Silence]
Put the examples in there.
We want to combine all the
JavaScript files from example/lib
into a single file called
example/bundle.js so we get all those.
TS: The order of those files doesn't matter?
We're happy just to take them in presumably...
JC: It doesn't matter in this case because
each file... Well if we have a look at the files.
So this file declares a class called complimenter.
And it makes one of them
and it console logs its say method.
and the other one, example source
hello does much the same thing,
it just has a different implementation
for what its say method does.
These files do have side effects because they
log stuff but they don't depend on each other.
If you're expecting the output to be
in a certain order... Maybe it depends...
If I was going to force a dependency
order, I would use node modules,
or the new module syntax that's in ECMAScript 6.
And then get babel or browserify
or something like that to resolve it,
so that the dependency was part of
the source code, not part of the build.
OK, so we have our build script.
Those were the steps that we did before.
If I remove the compiled JavaScript and the bundle,
then running that should produce the same result.
Util.error: Use console.error instead. [James thinks]
It couldn't find ./node_modules/.bin/coffee-script.
Why can it not find that?
Oh it's because it's just called coffee, OK.
[Silence]
I think maybe I should show the tree before
and after because it shows the actual difference.
So move the bundle and the compiled code.
So the tree before has just got our
source code in it. And if we run the build...
And that did something.
And now there are the compiled
JavaScript files in there, and the bundle.
And that is how we were expecting it to look.
TS: Great, does this count as a solution to the problem?
JC: Done! Success.
So a totally reasonable solution to a
lot of problems is just write a shell script.
But there's a bunch of ways that the
shell script doesn't meet the brief, so far.
We had to make it lazy so it won't do work it doesn't need to.
And it has to be able to
orchestrate arbitrary commands.
[James thinks]
What we just did was figure out what needs to be done
and then told the computer to do those things.
Whereas you want a build
system to be smarter than that
and you tell it what your project is and how it's
structured, and it figures out how to build it.
If you haven't changed any of your
coffee script since you last ran the build,
don't bother running the compiler again.
And if you haven't changed any
of your files since the last time
don't bother running the entire process again.
And you want that to be quite granular so it
can figure out which bits of work need doing.
And just run those bits but make sure
you get something up to date each time.
We want a system where we can say
lib/hello.js is derived from src/hello.coffee
and then it can look to see if hello.coffee
is newer than hello.js and recompile it if it is.
TS: So part of that is generalizing
the idea of how do you turn...
Because at the moment you've told it
how to turn coffee script into Java Script twice,
once for each file right?
JC: Right
You want it to understand in general, how to turn
any coffee script file into any JavaScript file.
JC: Right, and to have it understand
this file was derived from this other file.
And like I said before, it can check
the modification time of two files,
and if the output is at least as new
as the input it doesn't need to do anything.
TS: OK.
JC: So there's an intermediate step
there where I've repeated this instruction.
and you can (sort of) solve that with a bash loop.
[Silence]
So if we take that and just
shove file on the end of there.
And get rid of this.
This ought to do the same thing,
if we remove everything.
Check the example, run the build...
Check the example again. It does the same thing.
So we've made a slight improvement
to how much boilerplate we've written.
But this isn't lazy.
It will run this line every time. So as your project
grows this will get slower and what have you.
There's a lot of things that we
still want, so where do we start.
I guess the simplest thing is to
have something where you can say...
There's a file I want to build
and this is how to build it.
And have those be things a user can
specify. So maybe that's the place to start.
TS: So that's ignoring the laziness
stuff you were talking about
and just concentrating on how do I get this
hello.js given that I have hello.coffee.
JC: Well maybe even not given that I have
hello.coffee just how do I make hello.js
and then the idea that it's derived from some
other files, and the system knows about that,
can maybe be the next step.