Chapter 06.
Raising an exception when a build step fails.
JC: The thing that gets trickier about
this is when you have multiple instructions.
You want them all to be executed
but because they have side-effects you
want them done in a particular order.
Specifying that with mocks
can be a bit tricky but...
One thing that we can do, which is a use-case
I've not got to yet: what if any of them fails?
So we can say something like: if the first one fails,
the second one should not be executed
and that implies that there's an ordering.
So let's do that context:
'when there are many instructions'
let the instructions be first
instruction and second instruction.
Again, it doesn't matter what these are
because we're not going to execute them.
'it prints all the instructions'.
Oh no, expect output.
With first instruction once.
And also the second instruction.
When build the target.
And we also want to execute all of the instructions.
That should be the target in this case.
And puts should be system when you build target.
I believe these will work.
They do.
TS: Great
JC: Now we want to say
'when the first instruction fails'.
TS: So you're saying here that it doesn't matter
what order it does it, that's not testing it?
JC: No, rspec will not check.
Rspec doesn't expect things to be called in
the order in which you set up the mocks.
You could switch these lines around.
If I switch those this will still pass.
Even though that isn't what I want.
But specifying that you want
things called in a certain order is...
The way that I program is an uncommon use case
and is awkward to specifying using mocks.
But if you have something where one thing
can prevent the next thing from happening,
then that implies an ordering.  It's enough to
say that one thing happens before the other.
TS: And that's something else
that you want to test anyway.
JC: Yes you want it to abort the
build if something bad happens.
So when the first instruction fails, it
means that I'm going to allow the target
to receive system with
first argument and return nil.
Which is what system returns
if the command doesn't work.
So that scenario...(I'm not going to bother with
the printing stuff, we've done that to death).
It does execute the first argument.
But it does not execute the second.
So that means we expect this... Once.
[Silence]
Do we need to tell it that it will
return nil? Not sure that we do.
We'll find out.
I think I've done something weird.
Oh, I've got caps lock on, sorry!
I'll copy that.
So let me find the second instructions.
And it's not once, It's not.
So let me check this over.
So if the target returns nil
for the first instruction,
it should still execute it, but not the second one.
This shouldn't work because I haven't
implemented anything like this yet.
So expect it to use a target
(that i haven't actually told it to build).
That's quite important. [laughter].
Target.Build
[Silence]
Now it's executing the second
instruction when it shouldn't.
So if we go back to our code we can
say it's going to print the instruction.
And then we could raise failed command
unless system returns something truthy.
TS: So what will system return if it's not an error?
JC: True. We can see this in the shell for a second.
So if you system, echo something,
it does the thing and returns true.
And if you ask it to run a program
that doesn't exist it returns nil.
TS: OK great.
JC: So it's quite handy for having
a high level API inaud system.
inaud
So make an exception and raise that
unless system returns something truthy.
TS: So you've made a decision here that you don't want
it to skip them silently, you want them to actually...
JC: No because a build is just a sequence.
You turn a coffee-script file into a JavaScript file
and you need to put multiple files into a single one.
If the first step fails you can't do the second step.
And you shouldn't try
because if those files don't exist,
like if your command uses a shell wildcard or
tries to interpolate something that doesn't exist,
you might end up constructing a
command that will do something dangerous.
So it really ought to check that everything
you've done so far did what you expected.
So we shall run that. OK so loads of things are
now not working, which is common, and fine.
So let's find out why that was.
A lot of these raised, I was not
expecting them to be raised.
For example, the first one, 33 lets run that.
It's raising,
And it's raising from build.
We said we're going to raise unless
system returned something truthy.
But we haven't made system
return anything, we stubbed it out.
TS: So that will be returning nil by default.
JC: Yes, so we should make that return true and
anywhere else we're saying it should be called.
That's a not so it doesn't matter.
TS: Earlier you said you were expecting these
to inherit the behaviour of the stuff anyway.
JC: That's a good point yes.
I think if you stub something and
then put mock expectation on it,
the thing at the top says if you call
it with anything it just returns true.
The mocks tend to be more specific.
Inaud not to but it doesn't matter
because it's not going to be called.
But here we're saying it should be called
with something and that's a different use case.
I believe in those situations you have
to tell it again what you want it to return.
That's passing, a couple are
still not passing 64 and 69.
[Silence]
TS: Why were they failing?
JC: I believe this will raise and it's supposed
to raise, but I'm not catching that it raises.
I should have another test that
says it raises FailedCommand.
Expect target.build to raise
error and FakeMake FailedCommand.
TS: So the problem with these tests is that
the exception was bubbling out of the tests.
JC: Right.
And then I can just rescue in here.
[Silence]
OK so that's all green again.
TS: Great.
JC: It took a while to get there,
But I think that's enough of a specification
of what the thing does about running commands.
We've now got a thing that can run arbitrary commands
and can do something reasonably sensible with them.
So I'm going to get out of here to make a commit.
So what have we got?
I might just move build.sh to my scratch
directory and keep that hanging around.
So I ought to add the Gemfile things and the
example, although not everything in example.
There are a few things we definitely don't want.
I don't want an example bundle.js or example lib.
Nor node modules, because they
are just for running the examples.
I don't want scratch.
Inaud package either, we're
building a ruby project – although that is...
No that's metadata about the examples
and you will use it to install your node modules.
But you don't want node models... that's fine.
I'll move .js off there. So if I give that
all of this. So what do we end up with?
Git ignore and some gem files and some example code
and our source code and package.json and specs.
Which looks reasonable to me.
[Silence]
OK.