Chapter 11
Specifying Target behaviour
with older and newer dependencies.
JC: OK, now everything is passing,
so the thing does check its' mtime.
The next question is does it use the mtime
to do something useful like skipping work.
So when the dependencies are newer than the target...
And that means... So let's say...
Some offset to base these on...
Let the target time be time.now.
And then we can say, use that here.
And then it's clearer that they are in
the future from when the target was built.
It doesn't matter that it's time.now
TS: So are you using time.now as the most
convenient way to get a real time value?
JC: Yes, actually the current time is not relevant.
So what's the context? When the
dependencies are newer than the target.
That means that the...
Allow file to receive mtime.
So the time the target asks
for will return the target time.
And we need exists to return true as well.
The target will use target time as its' time and the
dependencies have times which are later than that.
The dependencies are newer, so that means
the target should execute its' instruction.
But we haven't given it any instructions.
[Silence]
Let the instruction be echo something;
it doesn't really matter what it is.
System is stubbed out in all these tests,
so I'm not really worried about that.
And also we want that output here because
it's going to start printing stuff otherwise.
Do we have that everywhere? We do, OK.
And that line's got quite long so
I'll use terminator block like that.
So we have a target with some dependencies,
an instruction and an output stream.
So we want to say is that in
this case it executes its' instruction.
I don't want to specify by saying you should
invoke some private method that you have,
because that like over
specifying the implementation. .
I want to specify the effect that it has on the
world which is that it makes a system command.
So, we expect the target to receive system
with the instruction once when we build it.
Now, it will prob do this anyway
because it isn't checking anything so far
because I haven't introduced
anything that will make that test fail.
TS: So you're currently testing
what it would already do.
But what we're driving towards is what happens when
it's NOT out of date, and you haven't tested that yet.
JC: Exactly.
JC: It's basically going to result
in duplicating most of this context.
So if feel I should pull some of this stuff out.
Lazy building.
So if i have that... I want to take this stuff which is going to be needed for all of these tests,
and put it in here. But not like that!
And then...
[Silence]
Is that all back in shape? I think so... Yes.
TS: So what's going to be
different in the other context?
JC: The difference is these steps here,
rather than returning things in the future
will return things in the past; or the past
relative to the targets' own modification time.
And in that case we shouldn't execute
the instruction, but just leave things alone.
So I'm going to copy most of that.
and they are not newer, they are older.
And these can be minus signs.
And we can say it does not execute its' instruction.
And this is the thing that should fail.
[Silence]
So target.system echo high expected
zero times; but received one time.
So that's the thing that needs fixing.