Chapter 07
Specifying dependencies.
JC: OK so we just committed the working target class.
It can't do an awful lot just
yet, it can just run the commands.
So if we go back to...
What did we have in here. My test file.
When I was sketching this out earlier,
down here I told each of the targets to build.
They're all just isolated.
A better user interface would be to do that.
And have everything needed to
produce the final result just happen.
For that sort of thing you're going to need to
know for example, what bundle.js will depend on.
Hello_js and complimenter_js
Whereas these won't depend on anything.
They are their own things.
Although they do arguably depend on their source code.
In order for the build system to be lazy
and work out if any more work needs doing,
it will need to know about that relationship.
So it's probably advisable if we say...
Here we have these target
objects to represent these things.
but for these source files,
we could say that they are...
For example, hello coffee is a
target new example source hello.coffee,
which actually depends on nothing because the
source code you wrote is not derived from anything.
And it has no build instructions and
because you wrote it it doesn't need generating.
And then this could take that as a dependency.
And you can do the same for
complimenter, and what have you.
I'm on the fence about whether to pass
these things around as values or by name.
Because, to pass this by saying
`example/src/hello.coffee`...
TS: What's the trade off there?
Why would you want to do it one way or the other?
JC: Good question, if you do them by
name you can do your target in any order.
This can be beneficial. This is
supposed to be a declarative system.
It can also mean that you make
dependencies on things that don't exist yet.
So for example complimentor.js
won't exist when you start the build.
The target represents something that will exist
in the future so you don't need the file to exist.
But having the pass by name means that you
can do something for example, by having patterns.
Like if you want to say star.js
depends on star.coffee,
we don't want to have to write all these
targets out by hand once the project gets large.
So you may want to have some general
rule for how you get from one to the other.
TS: It sounds like that may
be more complicated though.
JC: Yeah, erh... We can
probably start by passing by value
and if it becomes a problem we can pass by name,
and then have those names be looked up
in something else but turned into the values.
That should be a fairly minor change to make later.
So let's do the pass by value thing.
So if we go back to our spec.
I already had this open
because it was in another shell.
Yes, so... This is all talking
about running instructions.
We also want to talk about having dependencies.
So we've decided that the target is going to
have a new argument, which is its dependencies.
[Silence]
That ought to run but it doesn't... Why not?
[James is thinking]
Oh yes, OK so the tests we need...
I need to write that properly...
Dependencies is some list.
And I like things that line up.
So that ought to be fine.
So these tests are now testing
a thing that has no dependencies.
Ultimately we would like to have
a target that will depend on something else,
and if you build your target it
will also build the other thing.
Maybe this is where we get
into integration tests scenario.
Because I'm going to have two target
objects maybe writing unit tests against those.
I could write a test to say when you call
build on this call build on this other thing,
but maybe that's specifying
implementation too much.
So I'm going to try and write...
Spec/features is where I'm
going to put my generation test.
Dependent targets spec.rb.
[Silence]
No that's not how you write specs is it?
Describe dependent targets do.
[James thinks]
Say when one target depends on another.
As something simple, I'm going to say that if you have...
what's something simple we can
do with files, just like catting them.
So if you have file c that is...
I'll write it in code, that might be a bit clearer.
So if we say...
Not quite sure how to phrase this yet but...
let's say that we have...
There exists a file called a.text that
just contains an a with a new line in it.
And likewise there are some files called
b and c that have their letters in them.
[Silence]
So if there are those files,
then you have your first target.
And let's add these somewhere... Like in spec temp.
[Silence}
So if the first target is spec temp 1.text.
And that's new with that.
And it has no dependencies, or rather
it does have dependencies which are...
Sorry I got a bit side tracked.
So file_a.
TS: So we need targets to represent these files
even though there not going to be built in any way.
There will be some nicer user
interface around this at some point.
But it makes this a bit more
complicated as far as those values,
because you have to make values
for thing that are just primitive files.
TS: Whereas if you identified things by name,
the assumption would have been if I've named
something by name it isn't a target it's just a file.
JC: Yes.
So these have no dependencies in them,
no build instructions, so they can be done like that.
That's b that's c.
So if this depends on file a and file b,
And works by catting spec temp a.text
spec temp b.text into spec temp 1.text.
And the second target is called second.
And that works by depending
on the first target - file c.
Then that is going to work by taking 1.text
and c.text and putting that into the second.
I suppose this could be our before block.
[Silence]
TS: So you haven't actually built anything yet?
JC: No.
If we just build the second target – as he writes – because everything has been concatenated together.
I'm going to  make some helper functions here, so if I use this file helper here, I just need to define that.
Ive made this helper because I want everything to be cleaned up automatically afterwards. This helper is going to make the file with that content and keep track of it so if there's inaud remove all of them.
TS: OK.