Chapter 08.
Making Target dependencies build.
JC: So in order for that to work, we just need to....
The second target has been
given its dependencies as input,
So we should just be able
to tell them to build themselves.
So if we go back into our target class then build.
And we've got this dependencies
thing that we've not stored.
[Silence]
So build could call update or...
Not necessarily going to update them,
I'm going to make sure they're up to date.
ensure-updated-dependencies
And then let's inaud extract...
call build inaud build self.
So build is now a sort of sequence of high level
things you need to do, and this is how to do each one.
[Silence]
We have def ensure_updated_dependencies.
So we should be able to go in
and say dependencies each build.
And they will build themselves.
These things here, which are
primary resources we already created,
they don't have any build
instructions and should work OK.
This is why I made it so it was
OK to have no instructions,
because you need to be able to
model things that already exist.
This should go off and tell file a and b
to build themselves, which will do nothing.
And then this will tell the first
target and file c to build themselves.
The first target will run this command here and
once those are done, run this command here.
And everything should be OK.
It works. Hurrah!
TS: Amazing!
JC: Right, so we've got an integration test
and all that we've changed to do that
is quite a lot of things. (Laughter)
I don't know if all these unit tests should
be on the build method, or on build_self.
I don't want to specify the
implementation of target
but I want to specify it's
relationship with other things.
The important thing is when you build one target, it
will tell those dependencies to build themselves.
That's the minimum abstract
thing that needs to be checked.
I don't want to tell it how its
private method should be organized.
It's more about, what's its interaction with other
stuff and that is that it calls build on them.
In terms of unit tests...
fakemake target_spec... so build.
This is all about running instructions and stuff.
But before we get to running
instructions we have dependencies.
I'm not sure if it makes sense to write
a test for when there are no dependencies.
These tests are already implicitly
for when there are no dependencies.
And if there are none there's no other target for
you to say that it should or should not call build on.
So let's make a test for when there are dependencies.
[Silence]
We can have several of them and in
this case the order shouldn't be important.
Or rather you should construct your
dependency tree so the order doesn't matter.
If c depends on a and b, but b has to happen
after a then you should just say b depends on a.
That will ensure that that happens first.
So... The first dependency is a double.
And the second dependency is also a double.
This does let us check that if the first dependency
fails then we don't call the second dependency.
That isn't really a requirement, it's
accidental because the order doesn't matter.
So we should say it should tell all
its dependencies to build themselves.
So we expect `first_dep` to receive build once.
And likewise for the `second_dep`.
And, what's our target here?
Our target is FakeMake::Target.new
with a pathname (that won't matter yet).
And the dependencies, second dep and no
instructions because we're not testing that here.
That looks OK, so when we call target build it
should tell each of the targets to build themselves.
Oops, I've lost my other shell.
Path again...
[Silence]
OK that looks good.
This is a good place to commit. It's a new
feature: we have dependency management.
Let's have a look at what we've changed.
We've added dependencies to target class and made
it so that the target will build its dependencies.
If you have a tree of targets
they will recursively build themselves.
And we've added tests for those things.
[Silence]
OK.
TS: I was surprised to see when you ran that unit test,
it looks like there was some output
on standard out during the test,
which wasn't what I expected to see.
JC: You're right we're printing the commands.
We'll still have an issue with system, because
system inherit stood out from the ruby process.
Cat happens to not emit any output; well it does,
but we're binding it to the files, so it's fine.
Bur we are still echoing stuff.
TS: But this wasn't happening before right?
When you ran the unit test before
it was just a line of green dots.
JC: Yes.
I've let these targets in the
integration tests use standard out.
and I can maybe stop them from doing that.
It's a bit frustrating in that I could have
used puts and set dollar stood out inaud output.
It's one of those isolation things.
I want this thing that prints
stuff to print a black hole.
And I want the tests that are running the
process to still be able to talk to stood out.
We can get around that by passing
it an output like we did before.
Well call it stood out here to make
it a bit more clear what its' role is.
And then that can take it as an argument.
Although not all of them will need it.
Only the ones that run code need it.
[Silence]
I'm not having a very good typing day today. [Laughter]
Private method puts called for; that's interesting.
Oh! I've called it output sorry, I forgot what
I called it. It's called stood out in this test.
OK that's better, outputs gone away.
TS: Great.