NARRATOR: Welcome to Peer to Peer
where you can hone your skills
by watching live coding videos.
Our guest today is Paul Battley.
Who is a veteran Ruby developer,
who has worked with agencies,
startups and Government departments.
Our host is Jamie White, and the
challenge that he has set for Paul is called
Encoding Images As Quad Trees.
Jamie White: OK, so how about
we start by reading the challenge?
Paul Battley: OK, so...
Write a program to convert a given binary
image into a quad tree and serialize it to disk.
Write another program to take a
serialized quad tree and turn it back into an image.
The quad tree for an image is generated
by splitting the image into four quadrants
then successively splitting each
of these into further quadrants.
When a quadrant consists of a single
color, it may be considered a terminal node.
JW: I have provided this beautiful
binary image for you to work with.
PB: Not quite the right time,
depending on when your watching this.
JW: It's in a Windows 1Bit bitmap format.
So, it's up to you how you make use of that.
[New Chapter]
PB: So the first thing we want
to do is pass the bitmap file.
If I recall correctly, that's a bunch of
bytes, and huge bits of each byte is an image.
I don't know which order it goes in so
I'm going to look it up on Wikipedia and find out.
Inaudible.
So I'll look up the BMP file format.
Been through that, OK what
have I got... Pixel array inaudible.
I hope it's not compressed. I guess we'll find out.
If it is we can find some other way of processing it.
1 bit pixel. Each bit is
indexed into a table of two colors.
That's interesting, so inaudible
colors even though there's only two.
We don't really need to...
In our case it doesn't really
matter, as long as we're consistent.
So... I suggest that we look
at the file to see how long it is.
[Silence]
Ls - L on whatever .bmp
8256 bytes.
And... do we know the size of it?
We can find that out with identify.
Inaudible.
256 by 256 would be 64K except that
we're less 8 bits of a pixel... so 8 pixels.
Sorry pixels per byte, so inaudible so 856 sounds just about right.
So it's not compressed.
And according to this, it's just
the end of the file so I can probably...
ignore the header and just take the pixels.
So I'm going to write a bit of
code that reads in this bitmap,
and spits out the pixels as,
maybe hashes and spaces on screen.
That should give us an idea of whether its working.
Inaudible and a bit wierd, but we'll work it out.
So I'm going to play around, and call this print-bmp.rb.
And now I'm going to say something like...
I can load it all into memory... bits = File.read.
I could use ARGF here but I'm going to use
ARGV first because I want to specify the encoding.
JW: So ARGF gives you the final pass
into the command rather than inaudible
PB: Well it gives you both so you can either inaudible something or it will give you the first one.
Its very handy but I'm not
sure how that would handle inaudible.
I know that we need to be
able to handle the inaudible.
ARGV, I think it's...
Inaudible encoding...
[Silence]
ASCII 8 Bit,
which is not ASCII actually but...
Let's say that's byte.
And then I can say "print how many bytes I have got".
Which should be something like 256, if that works.
So I'm going to split this screen.
Actually, no I'll make a new inaudible.
Quad trees...
Now if I say Ruby and print
bnp and give it a style of bnp.
Inaudible array to string.
ARGV [They both talk at once]
OK so I'm going to read inaudible, that seems right.
I'm going to hard code the width and height.
So I'm going to say width
equals 256 and height  equals 256
And then I'm going to say
that image bytes is bytes from...
Actually let's just say minus
width, width x height to the end.
Then if I go... make that one image bytes
[Silence]
Put some space in there.
I can run this at inaudible percent.
Inaudible.
And define the length nil nil class by 5.
[Silence]
That's interesting.
Apparently image bytes is nil.
Let's see if that's really true.
[Silence]
Yes, why is that nil?
I know that bytes works.
[Silence]
Maybe it's confused by...
JW: Is that all bytes are like a string?
PB: Your right, exactly.
[Silence]
PB: So in that case, maybe I should
just unpack it into an array of bytes.
[Silence]
Inaudible again.
JW: I rarely use the unpack method.
That notation... what does it mean?
PB: If I recall correctly, that C means that
each byte will be unpacked as its byte.
So you will get an array of integers
that are the byte value of each character.
[Paul thinks]
Let's just try saying leave bytes
and just take 10 of them or something.
In fact, I'm going to say take 10 and
see if I've got something sensible there.
[Silence]
Yes, that seems useful.
In fact I could also say bytes dot...
Yes, in fact...
So I've got an array...
Where is 256?  Ah, there is my problem, right there.
The width is the number of bits.
I want it to be the number of
characters, so it's width x height.
And let's say bits per pixels... is that what it says?
Hard code here, I think we know what 8 is.
Width x height, this is all assuming
it's multiples of 8 and in this case it is.
8192 that's the number I was
looking for, that's the power of 2.
JW: Would you mind printing out the
difference between bytes.length and image bytes?
Just to see how big the header is.
PB: Yes, that's a good idea.
So bytes.length minus image bytes.length.
[Silence]
64 bytes.
That's good so let's see... inaudible.
So in fact... I could say header - bytes.take 64
and then I could say image bytes.drop.
I'm not sure if that's sensible though
because the header might change.
So instead I'm going to say
header equals bytes.take... that much.
So I've now got the image
the bytes and the header.
Now let's try to draw the image
So I'm going to say...
(What's the best way to do this...?)
Say height.times do - that can be Y
and width.times do and that can be our X.
[Paul thinks]
Then we should in fact...
inaudible it's not going to do it.
[Silence]
So then our byte is going to be the image bytes.
And the index of width over 8 x Y.
[Silence]
Plus X.
And then we want 8.times do,
what shall we call this one - i.
Inaudible
So for each of these I'm going to say...
I want to find the inaudible bit of it,
but I don't know which way round they are do I?
JW: Ah, that's true.
Inaudible
PB: Maybe it will say in Wikipedia.
[Silence]
It's probably reasonable to assume
that the most significant ones on the left,
Like numbers are.
Yes, so if I start off with my, (a kind of ugly
way of doing it but it will work for now).
If I start off with my bit mask, I want to be...
[Silence]
Yes, in fact this ought to work well,
so bitmask wants to be Ob1OOOOOOO.
Then my bit is just bitmask white shifted by i.
So that's going to be starting
from zero and then increasing.
And I can take that and inaudible that with the byte.
And then take the whole thing...
[Paul thinks]
And then right shift the whole thing by 8 bytes.
So my first one will be a
right shift by nothing inaudible.
Yes, so my first one will be right shifted
by 8, which means it's the least significant.
It;s like program C isn't it? [Laughter]
OK, so now I am just going to say print bit to S.
[Paul thinks]
Or maybe I'll do print bit equals 1 # space.
That should be more readable.
And then at the end of each row is a put
Alright... we will see.
Let's try this again.
We got all zeros.
JW: The features in the image are down towards
the bottom so presumably we didn't hit them yet.
PB: That's true, it might be
worth shrinking the text size.
No that's definitely all zeros.
So have I got this right...
[Paul thinks]
JW: We could just try printing the bits to begin with.
PB: Yes.
[Silence]
There's the zeros.
inaudible line banks which looks about right doesn't it?
I'm not sure how many
characters I've got across actually but...
1234567890
Yes, it looks about right for the length
of the line. That seems inaudible.
How about instead of this, I just print out the byte?
JW: Yes.
So I'll skip that and just say print byte.to S
That looks promising.
Hey, I can kind of see the shape. In fact if
you squint maybe you can see the hands there.
JW: Yes.
PB: In fact if I did that to S16 inaudible and the same width.
that should give us an even better indication of ...
[laughter]
The zero is still there but you get the idea.
JW: There's an image in there somewhere.
PB: Yes, we can see something inaud and long, which is...
In fact, let's go back to that.
Now this makes me wonder... it's upside down isn't it?
JW: Oh yes...
PB: I think inaud is the case with
bnp which is upside down.
But that doesn't matter for us, as long as it says
our output is upside down, it should be fine.
OK so bytes are OK, bitmask is OK, let's just get rid of...
[Silence]
We'll get rid of that entirely
and see what results we get.
[Silence]
OK that's a bunch of different things except...
Yes, I think that's right, the last row has...
There's a lot of white space at
the top so we would expect...
This also means our inaud as well.
Again, as long as we're consistent that's fine.
OK so...
The easiest way of doing this then is
to just say if it's zero, zero acts as one
Or rather...
[Silence]
Yes, I think that's modularly inaud shrink list. [Laughter]
JW: Awsome.
So... we know that we can get
the bitmap in and in a format which,
whilst it might not look exactly how we
want to see it - it seems to be flipped basically,
for the purpose of taking an image and
processing it and exporting it again, that's fine.
JW: Looks like a good time to commit.
PB Yes, I agree.
[Silence]
Don't know what I typed there... some junk... right.
That want's a simple BMP printer.
OK, now that we've got rid of
that lot it would be nice to wrap this
in a method that we give a
file and it gives us the bits.
[Paul thinks]
Yes, I think that would be good.
If I had a bunch of small test images,
I would write some tests for this,
but given the size of the image... I don't know how easily if I can make a bnp inaud
inaud def read bmp.
And inaud file object.
[Silence]
And... get it to take this stuff.
In fact I'm going to make a bnp file construct.
In fact, I will put something in
class, I think that will be easier.
Because it's got a header and other things,
I think it's best to keep it all
together in the same class BMP which...
[Silence]
And I can say def initialize.
inaud file some kind.
inaud, the interface below is going to be something like...
BMPImage.new
inaud first encoding.
Something like that will give me the
power to inject a file that's alright for it.
Nothing... should be able to say...
[Silence]
In fact, if I say that it will be file.open.
And I can say file.read.upack.
So now I'm going to put this in initialize
I might want to move it somewhere
else later but I think for now that will work.
[Silence]
inaud
Then say pixels.
And...
In fact, let's have width and height as...
[Silence]
inaud height, while we're here I'm just
going to change width to width... yes yes yes.
And do the same for height.
Strange how my hands type a completely
different word as the one I was intending to.
inaud
[Silence]
And this one...
Width height pixels in there, inaudible and put this in a private method.
[Silence]
inaud and say private section and say def image bytes.
I will cache that and say image bytes inaudible.
And I'm going to say def header,
and the reason I'm doing this
is because I know we want to write one
out later, so it's helpful to keep the header.
[Silence]
Again I can say header...
bytes.take... that's got to be at bytes.
at bytes.length and inaud bytes.
So we've inaud bytes, OK.
Here we have image bytes available to us inaud moved up the top somewhere.
Or can it. It doesn't mutate it does it inaud?
[Silence]
So at the moment pixels is still doing
that puts stuff, so for now I'm going to do
dot pixels,and see if I get the same sensible result.
[Silence]
inaud because I haven't given it the width and the height.
inaud
At a later stage, I could probably
work out where to find those in the header,
and read them but that's not the
most interesting thing we can do today.
OK, seems good.
inaud yes, that seems good.
OK...
[Silence]
I'll commit this before I change it slightly.
Make a BMPImage class, this
is still a work in progress so...
I think everything will be a
work in progress today actually.
So now I want to make this return, in fact
what I think I want is an array of arrays of pixels.
I think that's the most sensible thing to do.
It might not be the most
helpful thing later on, but for now...
Height I can map...
because each of those inaud
I would like to do the inaud style of functional things with the braces.
Width over 8.
Now this one... I need to do something like a flat map.