NARRATOR: Welcome to Peer to Peer
where  you can hone your
skills by watching live coding videos
Our guest today is Ollie Charles
who's a Haskell developer at Fynder
and the author of 24 days of Hackage.
Our host is Steve Purcell
and the challenge
that we set for Ollie is called:
Steve Purcell: So Ollie would you like to start
by reading through the question description?
Ollie Charles: So it's write a
program that solves word chain puzzles.
OC: So that seems pretty straightforward to me.
I guess that we've got a restriction there,
that the start and the end words
will have to be the same length?
SP: Yes they will.
OC: You've given me this dictionary as well.
And I see that some of these are different case.
Is that going to have any impact on the problem ?
Do I need to preserve case or
or lower case everything?
SP: I would like the resulting chain
to include the original case
of the word from this file,
and if you ask for a chain
between two particular words
they should be present
with the same case in the
word list file in order to be considered valid.
OC: OK.  And is changing case
going to be considered an operation ?
So if I have something
that starts with a lower case A
and an upper case A is that a difference of one ?
SP: I think so, I think a word will
either be capitalized
or not in the dictionary.
I don't think you would
find the same word in there twice,
once capitalized and once not.
OC: OK, Yes. Well,
I suppose we'll see what happens.
The first thing to do
is get my environment set up.
I want to have a Cabal file
so I'll treat this
like a proper project.
I'm going to be using nix  shell
to work with that
kabal file to do builds
and bring down
dependencies and stuff like that.
OC: So I've got a terminal here,
I should be able to run kabal in it.
So let's call this Word Puzzle.
It doesn't really matter about the version
and I'll just use another license.
I'll leave that blank ... and all this blank.
SP: Yes it will probably become executable
OC: And we'll go with word puzzle (inaudible) the main part
So now I believe I have my spell bar (inaud)
So I should be able to use the space bar (inaudible)
OC: I'm using the UNIX compile command there
to use the kabal file to do a build
OC:  I'm just going to see if that compiles.
Hopefully it's configuring.
And it looks like we've got something.
I'm going to have to (inaudible)
OK, so that seems to be happy
compiling something like that
and we can also subject that to the terminal
and run that .... yes.
OC: I think the first thing I'm going to do
is work with loading the dictionary words.
so we've got some data to play with
I'm going to start by making a type alias
for the dictionary and for our purposes
the dictionary is
just going to be a list of text values.
And the text there is the type from Data.Text
And I think I'll make a new function, dictionary
which will take the file path
and give me back a dictionary.
I'll take that out for now.
We're going to need
the Data Text library as well.
So I'll add that to the Cabal file.
And because I'm using nix
I'm going to need to add it to my nix file as well
so that's going to just pull down.
Let's scrub that out for now.
SP: So the underscore
you're leaving there is the hole?
OC: Yes, so if we expand the compilation
it says that there are two holes in this program
We need to provide some type of computation
that's going to be an io action
that will return the dictionary.
And we also have another hole for main as well
SP: And this is a new feature in the latest GHC?
OC: yes. I think this came in GHC 7.8
So  I'll leave the hole name for now,
because it's probably going to be
one of the last ones we fill in.
I'll work on reading this dictionary.
I think I'm going to
switch over to Hackage now,
and look at the
documentation from the Text Library.
This module has all
sorts of IO routines that are
going  to give us text values back,
and the one that I'm interested in is readfile,
which takes a file path
that gives us back a single text strength,
and then we can split
that up into a dictionary later.
The first thing I'm going to do ....
The text library tends to work best
if you use qualified inputs.
So I'm going to import Data.Text as T.
SP: So your just avoiding the confusion
of clobbering the built ins in the mode.
OC: Yes, the prelude has things like
length, filter and stuff like that,
but text also has length and filter.
So to avoid ambiguous names
I'm going to call that entirely qualified.
SP: So it's about hiding the symbols.
OC: Yes, I'm probably not going to be
using the prelude stuff very much,
but that will save me some hassle.
I'm going to have a type hole in there
so I've got some well formed syntax.
And now I have a hole
that needs to be in the dictionary
and I have available
dictionary contents which is a piece of text.
So I need to split this
single text string into a list of lines.
I believe we have a function to
do that in the Text Library as well,
which is un-line. (Inaudible)
Which is going to break
the text up into a list of texts.
SP: It's the exact analogue
of the lines in the prelude.
OC: Exactly. The text type itself is very
similar to the string type in the prelude
except the string type is quite inefficient.
It's just a link list of characters,
whereas text type is more
efficient in terms of representation.
SP: So you make a point
of defaulting to the text type.
Now I can just take
the lines of dictionary contents,
Now I should have
a way to read the dictionary.
I'm going to switch back
over to the terminal at GCHi
and then
we can have a play with that.
I need to refresh my shell to
bring down that text. (inaudible)
We've still got these holes here
which prevents me from using GHCi.
But, I can use another feature of a list
produced at GHC called defer-type errors.
Which is going to let me load code
which doesn't strictly type check
but as long as I don't run
something that doesn't type check,
I can still evaluate the program.
I can work around the fact that
I've got an incomplete bit of code in there (inaudible).
SP: So does it effectively replace that code
with undefined (inaudible)
OC: We can find out.
It's the main function that we have to find
well actually it doesn't
terminate at all (laughter).
But we do have the dictionary (inaudible)
so why don't we try:
I'm going to bind that into - no I'm not
SP: It's not going to print it straight off is it?
OC: No, because of the size of the dictionary,
I want to put that in the variable so I can
try and read out a few things from it.
So we'll take the length of the dictionary.
it's a pretty large dictionary,
We have to be quite efficient in the way
we search through this.
SP: Yes
But we do seem to have got some stuff.
I guess we've got some
windows and other things there.
Which is going to be annoying.
I'll probably
want to trim that stuff out.
SP: Feel free to convert the file,
If you want to change the
line endings that's fine with me.
OC: Maybe if we just
filter those character terms out
that might be easy enough.
Let's see if that's any better.
So I'm happy with that.
We're just filtering out character returns
on the whole dictionary string.
So it looks like the
dictionary has loaded up fine.
So now we're ready to start solving the problem.
There's no real reason
to restrict ourselves to the IO here,
this feels like it should
be solvable by pure functions.
SP: Yes.
So I'm going to introduce
a top little function called ....
we'll go with word puzzle,
which is going to take, 2 text strings
which are going to be our start and end strings,
and the dictionary. I think I'll bring that in.
So a possible solution
is going to be a list of words,
but I imagine there
are multiple possible solutions
for some of these
problems so I'm going to return
a list of list of words.
And because
that's getting a bit confusing
we'll introduce a types in there called solution.
SP: Perhaps a word chain?
OC: Yes, good we'll go with word chain.
Which is going to be a list of text.
SP: So you'll have
a list of possible chains
from the first word to the second word.
OC: And if it's not
possible to solve the problem
then we can just return the empty list.
that there are no possible word chains at all.
I'm going to try to solve this
by pattern matching basically
and try to break the problem down slowly,
hopefully we'll get
to the solution that way.
And there's one really obvious pattern:
you gave me the restriction that
the words have to be the same length.
So if the words aren't the
same length then there's certainly
no word chain between them.
I'll get that case out of the way.
I'm going to use a pattern after that:
Then I'll just return nothing.
Otherwise I'll leave that.
It seems to be solved.
OK so what have we got there?
It seems to be happy with that,
we've got a hole on
line 19 but that's not a problem
so if I try now and solve
the word puzzle with our dictionary,
between Hello and Haskell.
Whoops the dictionary
escaped, I'll just put that back in.
I need to use an extension here from GHC
called overloaded strings.
Normally when we inaud a string,
it's as the type
strength but obviously
we are working with text values
so the overloaded
string extension is going to
let us use literal strings
but they will have a type text.
And as we would expect- Hello and Haskell
don't have the same length
so there's no solution at all
We can move on now ....
so you actually try to find some solutions.
SP:  Might I suggest another case where we
might be able to rule
out other possible solutions?
OC: Sure.
SP: So if either of the
words are not in the dictionary
I don't know if you
want to handle that now.
OC: No that seems reasonable.
I've just had a thought that
I might want to have
a more efficient dictionary type,
but we'll come to that later.
So were giving two words A and B:
I think that's what we want.
See if that compiles:
SP: You'll probably find that
Haskell will not be in the dictionary.
OC: OK well we can check that .........
It is in the dictionary ! (laughter)
SP: It's a respectable word !
I guess then we
probably need to deal with case,
or maybe I should case sensitive an A.
Capital Hello is not in the dictionary.
Lower case however, will be. Yes
I think I'll leave that for now.
SP: I think that's how it should work. Yes.
OC: OK
SP: Let's presume
that the input would be exactly
as it is in the dictionary
or it's strictly considered invalid.
OC: OK.
And I expect
there's another obvious pattern,
which is, regardless of the dictionary,
we have two words
A and B, and they are the same,
and were done......
so that has one possible solution,
and I think I'm still
going to put that solution
in the word chain.
So if we go from
hello to hello, the solution will be
one word chain
which contains just the word hello.
so we can try that on two.
So let's see:
It does indeed have one solution
which is the word chain hello. Good!
So, beyond that
we've ruled out the obvious case
and we need to start doing some real work.
And I think a useful
function that we're going
to need is something that's
going to determine the distance
between two words.
Which is going to
be the amount of changes
you have to make
to get between two words.
SP: Yes, or at least whether they are
one step apart from each other.
OC: Yes
The neighbours are going to be words
some distance away... by one
So let's have:
Distance is going to take two text values
and give us back a number.
So if they are the
same then of course,
the distance is just zero.
So how we going to do this next.......let's see.
Yes, I'm probably
going to break the string apart
and treat it as if it were a list,
and I will compare the head,
and see if they're
different, and if they're not
the distance there is zero
but if they're different
the difference will be one.
SP: Are you once again assuming
that A and B are the same length?
OC: Yes I'm going to assume
for this function they are the same length.
and if not, well it might actually
work even if they're different lengths.
SP:  What comes to my mind is
zipping the characters of the two together
and seeing how many pairs are not identical.
OC: Yes, that sounds like
the kind of thing we could do.
I think now because were zipping,
even if they're different lengths
we can probably just
drop the extra characters.
And I think we have
a zip function already
in the text library ...... we do.
that's going to compare characters.
It works on text so we can only
use it to zip two pieces of text
which is not so useful.
So take A and B and
we will zip A and B
so I'm going to use type (inaudible) here.
OK, So we need to have
a function which takes a list
of pairs of characters to a number.
I think first thing we'll do is map over those,
so we can consider each
pair of characters independently.
Oh dear, I'll ignore that for now, next type hole
we have a pair of characters,
which have to produce something.
So if x is equal to y ......... then zero provides ....
That's one possible
correction we have to do.
Now we need to take
a list of things like a number.
I don't know why it hasn't ....
Oh, because B could be any type of numeric.
Ok, so that's good.
So it's hacking into our distance functions
we can switch back to GHCi
and see what it makes of that.
So let's see if the difference between
dog and cog is indeed one.
That's what you would expect. A basic example.
Let's see if we can
fit this into our word puzzle.
We're certainly going
to need the dictionary. (inaudible)
So I'm going to start with the word A
and we need to
find the neighbours of word A.
Let's filter the dictionary
so we don't have A in it.
That's going to give me a
dictionary that doesn't have A in it.
Maybe if we pair
every word with its distance
so I can take every word in the dictionary
and find its distance against word A,
and then I can take
the ones that just have a distance of 1
and that again feels like
I'm zipping 2 lists together.
SP: OK.
OC:  First we need to map that for every word.
We're going to keep
the word and I'm also going to keep
the distance between A and W.
Actually this is like what I'm saying.
Let's say:
And now we've got this map
and we need to filter this for all things
that have a distance of exactly 1.
So let's filter:
It's a bit long there...... I'll re-format that slightly.
Bit of a hole there, we can come back to that,
so (inaudible) build.
OK, so what have we got here?
Ah, OK, so I've filtered this
but I also need to map it
just so it will take the word, so that's A.
and once more, and take just the word
and the (inaudible) distance.
SP: Is there a function for that, is it fst?
OC: Yes, we can use first now.
Good, so we're
back to compiling once more.
So I'll give that a try.
Let's find neighbours of dog.
We need the dictionary there as well.
It doesn't seem quite right to me (laughter)
SP: I think this is probably a result of zipping,
and not taking into
consideration that if the lengths
of the two words are
different, then zip would finish
at the shortest sequence. OC: Right.
SP: And so, all of these like 'downfall'
would be only
one letter away from 'dog',
so maybe you should
only look at the first one.
OC: Maybe we should be
filtering the dictionary first
on getting words
that are only the same length.
We certainly have done that here.
SP: Yes
OC: I'm going to bring
in some smaller functions there.
The idea here is I'm probably
going to use the Applicative Syntax
to combine 2 operations together
so I want to take
things that are not equal to A.
SP: And also the slash equals operator?
OC: Oh yes, of course,
in fact we'll put that (inaudible) in there.
So we need it to satisfy 2 conditions.
We should be able to do this:
I think we'll probably be
able to tidy that function up as well.
So I'll take those back out,
and we're going to
need to import Control.Applicative.
SP: So I notice here that
even though you presumably knew
that you were going
to import Control.Applicative
your habit is to immediately try compiling
and have the compiler to tell you that.
OC: Yes.
SP: So this is really an
analogue of the TDD work-flow
where you are going for the failing test?
OC: That's right yes,
And I have to context switch again.
I've used length from the prelude here,
but we have text values
and length cannot be used on text values.
inaudible strings so we need to use T.length.
So hopefully were back to compiling that.
So let's try that one again.
See if it makes more sense this time.
That looks a lot better to me.
OK!
SP: Now Ollie could
you explain this section here
where you've used
the operators from Control.Applicative.
OC:  We're working
under the reader applicative here,
which is basically
an applicative functor
that works for function arrows.
So what I want to
do is, take the same argument
as I filter over the dictionary
for every word in the dictionary.
I need to check  that
that word is not equal to A.
And I also need to check that its length
is equal to the length of A.
So I need to do an
operation on the same value.
SP: Right
OC: So I could have introduced a lambda here
and banged that to a variable called W
and said W is not equal to A
and that the length
of W is the length of A.
But by using this syntax here, it's going to
implicitly thread that argument
through to both the functions for me.
So I don't have to worry
about passing the right argument in.
By using the right structure
here that kind of comes for free.
And there's one other
thing I want to tidy up
this is looking a bit weird,
and we've got some helpful
functions in the Data.Function library,
that comes in the base library of Haskell,
so I'm wondering if
we can use something there.
I'm going to have a quick look at the base library
just to see if anything looks useful there.
SP: Do you tend to use Hoogle?
OC: I do use Hoogle occasionally but that's more
when I know the function
that I'm going to work with,
whereas in this case
I just want to look at the types
and see if anything stands out.
SP: Because in Hoogle
you can search by the type.
OC: Right yes, but here
I suppose I'm not entirely sure
what type I'm
going to be looking for.
I want to just look through it
and see if anything comes intuitively.
But if we don't find
anything then I will leave it for now.
But it's these combinates down here, like 'on'
which is probably going to be the most useful.
So, you can see that 'on' as a typical usage
lets you call the same function
on two different arguments.
So let's see if we can use that.
So we're certainly going to be doing 'on'
well it takes 2 arguments
and: .....it takes a function of two arguments
and also a function of one argument.
Well our function one argument is T.length,
and our function two arguments is just equality.
So we need the check for equality on length.
So you can normally use it
with infix notation like this,
but that's when
you've got two arguments to supply.
We're only going to supply one argument,
so I think
I'm actually going to switch this back round
and do a normal prefix notation.
So 'on' equality, T.length against 'A'
and it's going to
supply us with  a second argument
for each word in the dictionary.
SP: Right.
OC: So compile that
and we're going to be told
that we need to import it,
so let's bring that in..... and that's in.... Data.Function,
Good! So that's back to compiling
and we're back in the hole here.
So I think I'm happy with that,
it's a fairly
clean readable description.
We do have quite a lot of loops going on there,
but I'm going to ignore that for now,
maybe we can
optimise that later, but for now
that's certainly solved the problem.
For our actual
word puzzle problem, we know
that the words
are different, but the same length.
I'm going to find all
the neighbours around the word A,
and then try and find all of the solutions
from all of
the neighbours of A.
See if any of them gets us to B.
In which case (inaudible) solutions.
OC: So we'll start by taking the neighbours of A.
(inaudible) dictionary (inaudible).
I've got a hole here
so I'm going to write some sort of function
that will take all these neighbours.
Let's have a look at the type of that.
We're going to
have a list of text and we need
to go to a list of word chains.
so that list of text
is all the possible neighbours
So I'm going
to map over that and now
I have the function that
goes from  text to word chain.
SP: OK
OC: So how is best to do this.
Even though this has
the same type I want to see what we get to.
We're going to be using the same dictionary
and were going to go to b and  (inaud) and N to B.
That's probably not going to type check.
We could have matched a list of text with text.
Oh! that's because
the word chain is a list of text
so it's expecting a single word chain
but we've actually
got many word chains.
So I think
the problem here is that if we
put another
type hole there, well see that this
could actually typecheck,
provided we
had a function that went from
a list of lists word
chains to just a list of word chains.
Which is of course 'concat',
and we have a
function in the standard library
(inaudible) that hole.
There's a function
in the standard library that does
these two things together.... Concat map
that just such a common operation.
Concat that there...... and
I guess we'll leave that ,
there's a hole for now (inaudible) GCHi again.
By loading the dictionary, I should be able to know
(inaudible) problems.
Let's try word puzzles dict. and dog to cat.
That is impressively slow right now (laughter)
And I'm not sure if that's because this doesn't  terminate
or because were being so inefficient.
SP: No,
by the time you go from dog to dot
one of the neighbours of dot is dog
OC: So we're actually
going back on ourselves probably
SP: (inaudible)
That sounds very reasonable to me. Yes.
so we need to probably
carry some extra state around.
So I'm going to put this down here.
We probably need
to remove something from the dictionary
which I guess
is going to be when we go here.
It will probably want to be a dictionary
without the word N itself and also not A.
I've already removed A here
so I'm wondering
if maybe that should be done
further up here.
We'll try it anyway,
let's just try it here.
So let's filter the dictionary
for stuff that's not to equal to N.
It's still having (inaudible)
That's better but apparently
we now have no solutions at all,
at least we do terminate. (laughter)
SP: So termination we're wrong
is better than no termination.
OC: I think so.
At least we know that it will eventually
deliver and so give us the right answer.
So what I want to check now,
we expected
this sort of chain dog, cog,
cot to cat,
so maybe if we just try cot to cat
see if we get that solution.
OC: For the smallest (inaudible)
that was cot to cat.
Again that seems to have no solutions.
It does indeed contain
cat but it's right there at the start,
so we should certainly be seeing that.
So let's see,
The neighbours around A
and for each of those
We've got a word puzzle
Save target
SP: So here your excluding
words that are the neighbour
OC: Yes
SP: Whereas,
perhaps you should be excluding A.
Because that's the
one you don't want to return to later.
You know that you've got that one.
Yes.
(inaudible)
OC:  So we don't want
to come back to where we started
that certainly does make sense.
And now we go from cot to cat.
OC: Were certainly finding some solutions
but never stopping the search (laughter)
which is interesting. So, what's going on there?
when we loop over there this  ......
Well I'm interested to see
if this will actually terminate at the same length
for all the neighbours of cot.
But maybe this won't terminate.
OK, maybe not (laughter).
SP: The (inaudible) indicated that some where (inaudible) (laughter)
OC: (inaud) we certainly are OK.
So, we're not hitting our base case properly,
which is interesting.
We're certainly getting here because that's
where we return the result.
Maybe if we
take all the solutions of neighbour.
So if we couldn't
find any solutions there then we won't
be able to find any bigger solutions
If we did find a solution
then we should be able to go for it.
Yes, that seems reasonable.
So I think that's largely OK.
We've got an error on that somewhere.
So N is expecting a word chain
that's actually a piece of text
that seems somewhat odd.
SP: So the word puzzle
will return a list of solutions
so do you not need to prepend
each of the items in that list (inaudible)
OC: Ah! of course, yes.
SP: So I think it would be just 'map of prepend.
OC: Yes
OC:  We could also use Applicative Syntax
which is not much different,
(inaudible) something like that
for every S we're going to prepend it with N.
SP: Right
OC: OK,
so we're back to compiling again
Let's see if
we can make any sense of that.
Cat to cat and then
every other word in the dictionary.
We're eventually getting to cat.
That's certainly happening.
I guess that is a valid word chain (laughter).
Is it just that there
are this many possible word chains ? I guess
The first one is certainly wrong though.
That's certainly not a chain from cat to cat.
That should be cot to cat.
SP: Yes
(inaudible)
SP: They are very long chains
SP: Cod to cat was the next one.
They're certainly valid chains though
SP: Yes
OC: So what's going on on that first one though?
We have cat.
The problem is I think
we should have been prepending .....
A rather than N - or possibly both of them.
Let's just see what that is, because we want to go
from the word we're starting at.
and now we certainly
have the right solution at the front
and we can of course exploit laziness,
hopefully just see the very first solution
and it terminates.
and finally that's one word chain
that has certainly got us there.
SP: OK
OC: So we need to
decide where we want to go next.
If we want to
find all possible word chains,
in a short amount of time,
or if we want to make sure
that this is definitely the shortest chain.
At this point,
finding the shortest chain we just need
to sort by the length descending.
But this now
because if we're sorting  the entire list
Is going to have to
consider the entire set of possible solutions.
SP: We probably need to think about
expanding the chains progressively,
and returning first
the ones that are the shortest.
OC: Right so reading
the search, as we go through.
I'm going to try and see how long it takes
to solve the whole list of solutions.
We have a function here, 'sort by' which takes
a list of type A and
if we have a way to compare them
for an ordering we can do something.
So Data.Function also has Data.Ord
So we have  comparing.
So we can say comparing on length (inaudible)
which is just what we want
a word chain as a  list of texts.
So sort by comparing length
and it's certainly not a good solution.
In the original spec of the (inaudible) it said
it should be
returning results in less than a second
but were well over that.
So I think we got
our one solution there from cog to cat,
purely by chance
because cat comes first in the dictionary.
What we're doing here
is basically a depth first search.
OC: So the moment we hit that one neighbour,
we go as far away  as we can
to try and get all the way to cat which is
not really the most efficient use of our time.
We're going to need to
change this from a depth first solution
to a breadth first solution.
What we're going to do
is go over each of the neighbours
and try to expand
that word chain of the neighbour
to go one bigger,
and hopefully we will eventually end at B.
B is certainly in the dictionary itself,
in which case we've finished our breadth first search.
At least to get the shortest path
SP: And since your removing the word each time
eventually you won't be able to expand
your search any further
because you'll run out of neighbours.
OC, Yes.
OC: So I'm going to
leave word puzzle alone for the moment
Instead let's try and use some kind of
expand function.
So that's going to
take a word chain and give us back
all possible expansions of the word chain,
we need the dictionary there as well.
I think that's what I want to do.
We're going to
work from the head of the chain
and try to expand that.
There is
obviously the case where we've got
no words at all in the chain.
That's not really (inaudible) to have the code,
in which case there's no expansions on that.
Otherwise we have
a word on some other words
and now by all
the neighbours in the dictionary
W and put those
on the word chain we've got so far.
So neighbours
gives us a list of words and
that's already a list of word chains.
Find the neighbours
of W but I need to use a  list
(inaudible) there.
I'm going to move away from the top there.
SP: That's not a bad example
of a case for a miscomprehension.
OC: OK.
OC: Sure well let's
try another one of those conventions
(inaudible) we need to go over there
(inaudible) neighbours dict. W
and we'll put that into (inaudible) N.
Now I need to
produce a single word chain here,
that will be NW dot something.
Back to compiling again - good.
I should be able to put the dictionary in...
and expand and type that back up...
word chains,
so why don't I just start with the word cat.
So that seems
to be doing what I would expect,
the expansion is on the front, so now
let's see if we can
feed this back in to our word puzzle.
I think I'll leave this around for now.
So we're going
to  start at word A and we need
to reach word B.
So we'll start with a word chain
which is just the word A
(inaudible)
and expand that
to a list of possible word chains.
Let's see what I need to do with that.
Well that one actually works so far,
but it's certainly
not going to be the solution.
(inaudible)
So that's just one
level breadth-first search.
we need to go a bit further
than that to find something useful,
so I think now
we just need to keep expanding
until we have B at the front of the list.
SP: Yes.
OC: We can probably use iterate to do that.
SP: Or until you don't
have any further expansions.
OC: Ah ! that's one
thing we've not done so far
yes, reducing this dictionary.
Where would I put that in?
so after one expansion,
this is probably returning me
a smaller dictionary as well.
When I expand a word chain
the dictionary becomes smaller.
SP: That would be reasonable.
OC: let's see what we get with that...
so word chain and the dictionary.
SP: The alternative is
that you keep the dictionary the same
each time, but you don't allow the addition
into the chain of a word that's already in it.
OC: Yes, but were
going to  keep
searching through a word chain every time,
it feels like
we just make the dictionary smaller
then our neighbours gradually become smaller.
so we return the possible
list of word chains as before.
Now I'm thinking
it would be nice if we had
a bridger (inaudible) type for our dictionary.
Like a set
or something like that, so I can  do a
set difference and easily
remove a set of words from it.
SP: Yes
OC: That's going to be a bit of a
back jump
but I think it's going to be worth it
so I'm going to import
the Data.Set library as well
and that also works best
when you import qualified.
We need to depend on
the containment library for that.
And to get that I need to put that in there.
Actually  it looks as if we already have that.
Bit of a misnomer there I reckon.
So now that we've got
set imported maybe we can make this like so.
So rather than having a list of text,
let's go with A set text,
and we'll just ask
the compiler to tell us everything
we need to update to change.
SP: Yes
Well, first thing we
need to do is return a set
rather than a list: that's easy enough,
we can just say S.list
which takes a list and turns it into a set.
Next, rather than checking a list to see if (inaud)
use S.member, which checks to see if an element
is a member of a set.
(inaudible) the same here. ......
That has put a hole back there.
That should probably just return.
.....like that .....
The filter is for lists but we
have a set so we ask S.filter to filter a set.
I'll check the type of that in there.
OK, I've some idea
of where that error came up.
Ah yes,  we can't map over a set like that.
Do we have that.. yes we do ...
so we just change that to S.dot map
(inaudible)
Now this is not going to give us a list of text,
it's going to give us a set of text.
SP: There are built in facilities like traversible.
Does that help with
this sort of code where you
change from one data type to another?
There are some gereralised forms of some of
these functions arn't there.
OC: Right. We can't generalise map I dont think
because this is a set and sets have the constraint
that the things inside the set must be orderable.
SP: Ok
We can't map between our 3 types because
we wouldn't necessarily map the same (inaudible)
The filter - there's probably something in Data. Foldable
that will probably let us filter the set.
But I think I'm quite happy working with sets here.
SP: That's fine.
OC: I don't think generalising
would give us much of a benefit here.
SP: Why I was wondering
is because I like to use that myself.
OC: Now we may not be able to
use the list comprehension anymore.
what we could do
though is just go to a list.
We could turn this into a list.
And now were back to trying to solve this.
To recap where
we were, we wanted to have
the dictionary smaller and smaller
we return the
word chain and now we need to
return the dictionary
but without a set of words
that we've already considered.
I believe those are going
to be to the head of the list of chains
that we just expanded
to so that will be all the neighbours again.
Although maybe it's more
beneficial to bring more neighbours out
as a set of binding.
SP: Yes.
So now we can take
the dictionary without any of the neighbours.
I've got a slightly smaller dictionary now.
And let's start type checks.
We certainly want to call in expand and then
we need to work out
what were going to do with that result.
We have to write
a function that's going to take
a list of word chains, the dictionary,
and eventually gets to a word chain.
I think we'll end up using some functions
that are already in prelude anyway
but let's just follow the types manually.
and see what we end up with.
OC: We have some function
F that's going to take a chain
and a new dictionary (inaudible) something
and pull that there as well.
Now we want to expand
every single one of these chains
using the smaller dictionary.
So do something with chain and chain is (inaud).
These type holes are not going to help (inaudible)
just have to
trust our intuition a bit more.
but I should be able to map expand.
I should bring this down a little bit.
Expand takes
the dictionary in first position
and word chain (inaudible) second
so that's going to work quite nicely,
Apart from (inaudible)
so that was a list of chains.
Going in the right direction there.
We need to go from
a list of a list of word chains.
to (inaudible) word chain
So, expand every chain.
I'm going to
have to call F on that again.
So, I think we're
struggling to find a nice kind of way
to repeatedly apply this expand function,
and what comes to mind here is,
it looks like an
unfold which is like the dual to fold,
which a lot of people are familiar with.
When you fold
you have a list and you keep
reducing it into something smaller.
Whereas in this case
we actually want to get something bigger.
Which as unfolding until the point
where we maybe can't go any bigger.
So we have a
function in the Prelude to do that
which is unfoldr.
But that requires
for this function that we have
something that returns maybe any value.
SP: OK
OC: But this actually looks quite a lot
like what we have in expand here.
OC: But we don't have a maybe here,
so the maybe represents the fact that
you can't actually go any bigger,
which is what we were
modeling here with this pattern match,
where we simply said
we have an endless list of word chains,
but that felt a bit weird, so maybe let's try
bringing in a "maybe" there.
SP: Maybe let's maybe (laughter)
OC: Ok, so in this case
there's nothing we can do,
so we just say nothing
whereas in this case,
we have just that result  of word chains.
NARRATOR: We're going to speed through this section
because Ollie and Steve found themselves
deep into a Rabbit hole.
They eventually backtracked
on this idea of using unfoldr,
so let's skip ahead to the section
where they changed course.
SP: You are typing faster than I can think.
(laughter)
OC: Even though we're using unfold,
which does feel
like the right thing to be using
I think we're getting ourselves into
a bit of a muddle here.
And one of the big culprits
is what we're doing
in this expand function
so I'm going to try and simplify that
and see if a
nice solution comes out there.
What I'm going to go with instead ..
expands going to take
a single word chain and the dictionary
and it's going to expand that to a list
of possible word
chains and smaller dictionaries.
SP:OK
OC: So whenever I make one expansion,
I consider all of the neighbours around the
first word of the word chain.
And for each of those new word chains,
I'll have the neighbour at the front,
and we're going to remove that word
from the dictionary because we don't want
to go back on ourselves.
OC: So I have a word chain with nothing in
but there's nothing I can do.
We have to
(inaudible) but otherwise if we have a chain
that starts with the word W,
we have the dictionary and then
we need to take
the neighbours around W
which will equal N, and put that on the
front of the chain, so N is going to be
the neighbours using the
same dictionary around W.
But we also need to return
this slightly smaller dictionary.
Tootle (inaudible) that up with......
the same dictionary,........
but  we'll delete N from the dictionary.
SP: Right
OC: Lets try that......
get rid of our old definition.
You can see this is very similar
to what we had in pattern (inaud) one.
OC: (inaudible) from there smaller one
So ignore this ...........
lets keep that (inaudible) there
and that's expecting
a list of text from the other set
(inaud) list
we're back - good!
So if we load
the dictionary in we should
be able to use expand with (inaudible)
one expansion of cat.
So what we're doing here is
we end up printing the out dictionary as well.
SP: Yes. (inaudible)
OC: Map first over that,
and we see just the one level expansion.
(inaudible)
So we're going
to repeatedly apply this
but we'll keep the small chains.
Then we will have the
bigger chains on the end.
So that's giving us a flattening of a tree
of a breadth-first search. Which I think
is going to be better
than the depth first search
that we saw earlier.
SP: Ok
I'm going to do a little function up here called go.
Go is going to
take a list of word word chains
and the dictionaries.
And this becomes apparent
you can see how I'm
going to pull the cursor backwards
And it's going to
give us back a list of word chains.
and that's going to let us repeatedly apply
that to ourselves
OC: So if we have
nothing in the first (inaudible)
There's nothing we
can do, we simply return that
Otherwise we have
some chains so what we can do
SP: We have some
combinations of chains and dictionaries.
OC: Yes, but for every word chain in the dictionary
we want to expand that word chain
using its own dictionary.
So I'm going to map over chains,
and what we'll have here is a word chain
and the dictionary. We want to
expand the chain in the dictionary.
We're going to have
to concat on that because
expand gives us a list of word chains.
SP: Can you rename chains there ?
OC: Sure (inaudible)
or did you want to drop it entirely?
We're not going to
be able to because we've
pattern matched on one here.
SP: Maybe in pairs
OC: Ok, because of the dictionary.
So that's ok ...
but what we've
done now is, we've throw away
these original chains
we need to retain those as well.
SP: Right.
OC: So we'll keep the pairs,
and then add on
the expansions afterwards.
SP: Yes.
So for the smaller
chains that might already
have finished, we'll keep those.
SP: So then later
you would look at all the chains
starting with the smallest first
and try to select only the ones that
finish on the target word.
OC: Right.
OC: And because in
expand we're putting neighbours
at the front of the list, were going to have to
filter word chains that start with our target
It's a bit weird but
obviously cons is a lot more efficient
to the (inaudible) because we don't
have to traverse the list at all.
SP: We can always reverse the solution.
OC: We can yes.
I'll just check that
that's all the compiling done.
We should be able
to have a play with this now.
(inaudible) GHCi
So we've got go so I'll try ....
to bring the dictionary back into scope.
Word chains plus words, so I'll try cat
and it needs
a dictionary in there as well.
And we'll start with just that one.
And that's going to expand forever (inaudible) go
SP: Ok.
OC: And take the head of that.
There's a lot of possibilities ...
because of the dictionary.
We'll just take the word chains out of that
(inaudible)
So every time we take one more
our chains get a bit longer
SP: Can you see the next one?
Oh ! that's because we've flattened it, yes.
SP: That's not the level
that's just the chains as they change.
OC: Yes
SP: (inaudible)
OC: So gradually they're
going to start getting bigger at some point
(inaudible)
That's not re cursing.
Actually go is never calling itself,
which is the problem here.
So were only ever
looking at one level expansion.
so if we take the original pairs and what we
need to do is go again on the concat map.
SP: Right
So we're going to
keep going to bigger and bigger chains.
But we're always putting these chains
on the end of the list.
So if we go back to taking 20 we should be
back to where we were
and as I take more, you can see we are
starting to get
bigger and bigger chains now.
SP: Right, and all of them ending on cat.
OC: Yes
SP: That's because that was our start.
OC: Yes, were going out from cat
SP: (inaudible)
OC: So now were ready
to put this back into the  word puzzle
to solve the puzzle properly .. again !
So we need to
call go and we're going to be
using the (inaudible) dictionary.
But were going
to have to delete our starting word
from the dictionary.
SP: Right
OC: Because we don't
want to go back to the start.
And we're going to
start with a word chain
that begins at the word A.
And this is going to give us all the chains
that start from A.
But we're interested
in chains that start at A
and finish at B.
So we filter the result of chains
by  taking ........ for each chain.
Sorry, first we should just throw away
the extra dictionaries.
SP: Because the two (inaudible) will come back from go.
OC: Yes, so it will give us two word chains
from the dictionaries,
whereas we're
only interested in word chains.
(inaudible)
Now we've got a list of word chains.
I can filter the list for ones whose first element
is equal to our target. (inaudible)
SP: Right
OC: And I think that's what we need
to solve the puzzle..so that all compiles
Put that dictionary back in
(inaudible) word puzzle using the dictionary
it will go from dog to cat.
And we are indeed getting result.
The interesting thing we're seeing here
is as it's gradually printing results,
we are seeing how Haskells' (inaudible)
evaluation works to our advantage.
So if I only wanted
to get the very first result,
I could simply
take the head of all the solutions
and the result is already done,
it didn't bother
computing all the extra values.
But if I needed the extra results, maybe if I
wanted to find
the first ten shortest chains
I could just take10
and that's going to give you
10 word chains and then terminate,
which is really nice.
SP: Right.
OC: I think that
solves the problem that we had
in the original problem spec.
SP: Shall we try it on longer input ?
How about the words Ruby and Code.
OC: Ok so I'll take the first of those.
It's certainly a lot slower but we do
get a word chain in the end.
So it might be worth trying to improve the forms
of this text (inaudible).
SP: Absolutely,
there are longer examples
such as from house to shout,
we could see if that completes
in a reasonable amount of time.
This one's quite
tricky because the search space
for it is quite large in the dictionary
that I've given you.
OC: This looks like
it's terminating any time soon.
SP: So maybe we
can have a look to determine
where the bottle neck is ?
OC: Yes, well I'm going to leave that one
running in the
background anyway, see if we get a result
while we start looking for some (inaudible).
To me, the biggest source of expense
feels like this neighbours function.
We're filtering twice and the map twice
and we are doing this repeatedly
every single time we expand.
And the set of
neighbours around a word
doesn't really change.
There may be
potential neighbours that we
can't consider because
we've already looked at them once.
and we would go back on ourselves.
But we can probably prune
the set of neighbours afterwards
I'm thinking maybe
we can have an optimisation
where we have a map of neighbours
It's going to be a map
from text to its set of neighbours.
And we should be able to
pre-compute this against the dictionary .
We're going to need the map data type
which comes from Data.Map,
again I'll be importing this from qualified.
Now we look up the list of neighbours.
We can still take the dictionary as input
but rather than just taking that, we can also
take in a neighbours map
and the word to look up
and it's going to
give us a set of neighbours again.
And the reason I'm taking that dictionary
is because we keep making that dictionary
smaller and smaller. We want to make sure
the neighbours we look up from this map
are actually in the dictionary because
we might have made the dictionary smaller
and removed possible names
so we're going to filter those out.
OK, so we've got, I'll call that M and W.
And this becomes straightforward,
we simply do a map look-up (inaudible)
which will throw up an error
if the word isn't in the map
but we'll have to
gloss over that for now I guess.
SP: yes,  (inaud) maybes'.
OC: If I was doing this production code
I would probably want
to keep the maybes' and the
chance of possibly failing
and reflect that in the types
that would add up, but for our purposes
this should be sufficient.
So, this is saying in the map M
look up the word W.
We need to take the intersection
of the set of possible neighbours.
We take the set into section
SP: Is it (inaudible), ?
I can't remember.
OC: From map I believe
it's just a single exclamation mark,
whereas for lists it's two exclamation marks.
So we don't seem to have any compile errors
around this neighbours function.
That's quite straightforward.
We also need a
way to pre-compute neighbours.
So that takes the
dictionary and turns it into a map,
SP: So here your
starting from saying; from right down
in the lowest level of this computation
you would like to have
that extra information available
in a neighbour map.
and you're working your way back up
to the (inaudible) levels to see
how to pass that down into it.
OC: Yes.  We've got a neighbours function.
I would like to be able to test that in GHCi
but we don't have
a way to build a neighbour map yet.
So I'm going to work on this (inaudible)
neighbours function then I can (inaud)
GCHi so I can actually see if
the neighbour map seems to be working
as we would expect.
Then we can work
through the rest of the compile errors
(inaud).  That's what we do.
So this looks like
it should be straightforward,
we just take
our dictionary, which is a set of words,
so if we go set to list.
and  for every word
in here we can map over .....
Ah ! We did need our
original neighbours function
which I have thrown away now
because we want to use that.
OC: So let's see if I can go back to that.
So I'll call this one ............
neighboursLookup
and this is back to how it was.
SP: We could also call this
neighbours and could the old
neighbours function
simply be a function returning
a list of the words
with the neighbours and distances?
OC: In the neighbours function or ....
SP: Yes, so you could - at this level here
where your returning W with distance,
in order to avoid having two similar (inaudible) functions.
Maybe we should continue ....
OC: It's probably worth renaming this though
because we want compile error,
well we're going to get compile errors anyway
because the types different.
I'm going to move this
into preview of neighbours
whatever I do ....
because we don't
have any reason to ever call this
other than inside string names.
SP: And you can rename the top one.
OC: Exactly,
The dictionary is going to be
available up here anyway,
We need to turn our
dictionary into a list of words
move that neighbours over there.
So I need to pair
them up with the original word as well.
There's a fairly nice
function in the Control.Arrow module
which lets us run two
functions on the same argument.
I can say that it and neighbours
so that's the identity
function and the neighbours function
and it's going to Tootle (inaudible) those up for me.
SP: OK.
OC: I think I'll just import that ....
We've got a lot of compile errors.
We apparently need the word A as well. (inaudible)
(inaudible)
OC: So now we have
prelude neighbours but that's
not returning the neighbours from there.
We don't really need to (inaudible)
because were using that in neighbours
Now this is going to be a list of tootles (inaudible)
OC: We can turn that into a map. (inaud)
So we've turned our
dictionary into a list of text
and for every text and for every text value
turned that into the text word itself
and its set of neighbours.
SP: And each word will
be distinct so you don't need
to worry about combining entries.
OC: Right, yes
OC: Let's see what we get from that.
Neighbours is
going to be neighbours look up
so that's ... well, yes
let's keep it as neighboursLookup
OC: I'm just checking to
see if that's the only compile error
we've got, and it looks like it is,
so we've just got two arrows up here.
That means expand
rather than just take the dictionary
it also need to take a nMap.
The order here is dictionary, nMap
I just had a thought there,
because we're always
passing these two things together maybe
I should be combining these.
SP: I was having the same thought.
OC: So I think maybe our neighbour map
could be a data type
containing the full pre-computed map,
but also a set of exclusions.
And every time we
need to drop something out of the
neighbour map
we can do that quite efficiently.
SP: Right.
OC: Or we maybe (inaud) but we'll see
I'll come back to that later,
but it certainly does feel suspect so far.
So I think I better
put this the right way round
...dictionary and neighbour map
This is the dictionary and neighbour map
and now expand
needs that neighbour map as well.
But interestingly,
this doesn't have to be added to go.
Because the neighbour map doesn't ever change
from what we've got so far. So that's just a constant. (inaudible)
SP: (inaudible)the first one.
OC: Yes it did.
And, we need to call that recurser map (inaudible
and you can use pass in here as well.
So here (inaudible)
So now our word puzzle
should be using this preview as
neighbours map.
SP: Right.
And were using
our more efficient neighbours
look-up function. So hopefully
we are going to see some results.
Impressively its still
trying to find solutions between
house and shout, on the old code.
So let's see what we get out of this.
We didn't really
look at seeing a pre-compute
preview of neighbours,
so let's have a quick look at that.
OK, so (inaud) type checks.
Let's bind that to it, something like that.
We can do nMap ....
SP: Jellow and hells. (laughter)
OC: So bringing in
neighbours does seem to be working.
We seem to be getting some actual neighbours,
so let's see what happens
with the others, let's do ruby code then.
It doesn't seem to
be a huge amount more efficient
But maybe we'll
actually get a result from this now
We've still got a little bit to go.
SP: Does it take long
to re-compute the entire map ?
can you force that computation on c. ?
OC: We can try
forcing that and see what happens.
SP: So of course here
your going to be pre-computing the
neighbours across
the full dictionary, not necessarily
the dictionary
pruned down to only the the words (inaudible)
OC: Yes that's probably worth doing already.
Rather than ridding
the dictionary of everything.
We're using a
lazy map here which means that
we'll get a map back
that contains all of the words as keys,
but the values underneath
that map won't be fully evaluated.
So it's only when we
look up those keys in the map
that we will do that work.
So hopefully
having the full dictionary in there
doesn't make any difference.
But I think for clarity
that's slightly nicer if we
just say filter, length, equal to length
SP: Of course, this way your run length across....
is it hundreds of thousands of words ?
OC: Yes.
SP: So its a tradeoff.
OC. So we take the length.......
I think that's
because we have text values here.
We've already seen
this type of function before anyway.
So (inaudible) here.
Maybe we could do something about that.
The maybe neighbours
doesn't have to worry about that,
we've already done that once.
I think I'll just
leave that for now, see if that
has made a difference.
It seems a bit saggy doesn't it?
SP: Yes
SP:: So the acid test. (laughter)
There's still no
results between house and shout.
SP: So that's great, we've reached a point now
were we're able to
find chains quite efficiently,
Not just from cat to dog
but also from rude to code.
SP: Where do you
think you would go next with this ?
OC: One thing that's always (inaud) quite a bit is
in go we are using  foss boss (inaud)
which means that
because were always having to
put things on the end of the list.
we're always have to
walk through the start of the list
to get to the end.
And we're having to do that repeatedly.
There's a couple of
well known ways we can go about
optimising that at Haskell.
Difference lists are one possiblity.
Which means that
appending has much less of a cost
provided we don't
ever try to inspect the front early on
but we don't need to do that, we only need
to start inspecting
once we've built up this big computation
of all possible solutions, and then we can
start filtering things off the front.
So that could be
an interesting optimisation to see.
Maybe we'll be able to allocate
a bit less than the go function.
Beyond that I'd probably
want to look at the code profiling.
Try and work out (inaudible)
a little too frequently, and see
if we can do something there
Obvious strategies
and any graph search problem
would be memorisation.
Which works really nicely at Haskell.
That wouldn't be too hard to add in.
It's just a case of
working out exactly what needs to be optimised.
And a couple of other things.
Just in terms of the feel of this code,
that I'd want to clean up.
As I pointed out earlier, the neighbour map
always has to be
paired with the dictionary so forcing
the user to pass the
dictionary and the neighbour map
around felt a bit cumbersome.
It would be nice if
we could work out some sort of abstraction there.
A neighbour map
data type that has an operation like look - up
and remove ........
SP: Or the dictionary itself is more complex
and opaque structure
which can provide you with neighbours.
OC: Absolutely,
SP:  Because that's the only operation
we have on the (inaudible)
OC: Yes, it needs
efficient look up and efficient
removal of the things you've already seen.
Beyond that,
we don't have any other requirements.
I think were using a new (inaudible) set...
we did yes.
so the set does
have efficient look up and deletion.
But if we were able to combine that with
the pre-computed neighbour map
we would probably get a much nicer api.
SP: And having worked through this,
the overall approach of using
lists to represent the word chains
and  expanding those lists.
Is that the approach you would use again ?
OC: I think, now that we've got more familiar with
the problem,and its clear
that it has this tree structure
when you do a breadth-first search.
It would have been
nice to make that explicit
in the types themselves.
So use some
sort of tree structure to represent
the branching out, because I think
a couple of times we've confused ourselves
with lists of lists of text,
when we actually wanted
a list of texts, and it was  unclear
how we actually got them from
that nest of lists to a single list.
Was compact
the right version to be using
or have we
made a mistake somewhere else.
So we didn't really (inaudible) on the types there,
it would have  been nice
if we could have taken a bit more
advantage from the type system.
I think if I
were to do it again I would choose
a slightly better data structure
for word chains in the first place
SP: So there's a built in tree type,
isn't there?
OC: Yes, its not
one that I'm very familiar with.
It's in the same library
as data.set and data.map.
It doesn't have a hugh avi/api(inaud)
but it does avoid me (inaud) in terms of
just coming up with the data type.
And the other thing
that I might be interested in doing
there's a lot of hidden recursion here.
It's quite hard to follow this code,
it calls itself in different ways.
It's more of a (inaudible) Haskell
where you can
split that recursion out
and make it very explicit.
You have some
N functions that operate
on just one thing, and then you have
a recursion scheme you can apply to that.
And that might
come out with some slightly cleaner code,
but it's going to
take a lot more work to get that.
But I think maybe (inaudible)
could clear up a lot of this code.
SP: Right, that seems like a successful session.
OC: I think so - got there in the end.
SP: Yes, thanks.
OC: OK