NARRATOR: Welcome to Peer to Peer,
where you can hone your
skills by watching live coding videos.
Our guest today is Melinda Seckington.
She works as a Ruby developer
at FutureLearn, a social learning platform.
Melinda co-organizes BarCamp London,
and participates regularly in
hack days, frequently winning them.
I'm your host, Drew Neil.
And the challenge that I set for Melinda is called...
Building a Mechanical Turk system.
DREW NEIL: So Melinda would you like
to start by reading the challenge.
MELINDA SECKINGTON: Build a Mechanical Turk system.
It should poll people for answers to yes/no
questions that are easily answered by humans
but not by machines.
If a certain number of people
give the same answer to a question,
it's marked as resolved and
polling for that question ceases.
If people give different answers to
the same question, then polling will continue
until a consensus is reached and
that question can be marked as resolved.
When someone has answered a question, they
may view a summary of all answers to that question.
DN: There's a little bit
more to the question actually.
If you turn to the next page,
I've provided a sample question.
MS: Is this a cat picture?
DN: So I think most human beings
would have no trouble answering that.
Whereas it would be difficult to write
a program to give the right answer there.
With more than 50% certainty.
And there's another question as well.
MS: Is this a squirrel picture?
I think I can say no.
DN: Right.
So that's the kind of question I
thought we could be working with here.
I've provided about 6 animal pictures, so
we can come up with a series of yes/no answers.
Sorry, I mean questions where it's a yes/no answer.
Most of them are going to be nonsense,
but for each picture there
will be one correct answer.
MS: Yes.
DN: So that's what I thought we'd use as
a sample dataset for this challenge.
So, I haven't said which technology
you have to use to build this system.
What would be your preference here?
For me it would be Ruby and Rails
because I'm familiar with those already.
Plus we've already got a very simple login
and logout system so that people can register.
So, basically if we go to the login page.
And hit the register button.
[Silence]
Now we're logged in.
DN: So it looks like a brand new rails app.
MS: Yes.
DN: But it's not a brand new rails app.
It already has a register route and a login route.
MS: So if we go to login again...
You will be redirected to the main
page because you're already logged in.
DN: So it can detect that
you're logged in, it remembers you.
And, can you logout as well?
MS: Yes, if you hit logout.
Which you can't really see but you
can hit the login page and login again.
So it's very very basic.
DN: Rudimentary... we don't even have passwords.
No its really basic.
DN: Well that's fine, that's not going to be
an interesting part of this challenge I think.
[New Chapter]
MS: So, where to start.  It's a Mechanical
Turk system so we've got people... users.
And we want to show each
user the questions that we have.
So let's start with looking
at creating these questions.
Each question will have an image.
That's showing us the cat picture.
Text, I guess, like... is this a cat picture
So I guess let's start there.
[Silence]
Let's take the image.
DN: So the string is going to
be a URL for where it listed it.
MS: Yes.
DN: In the public directory probably.
MS: Let's do... description.
And string as well, because we don't want that to be too long.
DN: So the challenge doesn't ask you to create
an admin area where people can create questions,
We're going to pre-populate
the system with some questions?
MS: Yes.
So we want to...
[Silence]
Basically use this seed file
so that we can use db:seed.
So I'll load that in.
So I want to use the seeds file.
[Silence]
DN: So this is just a plain Ruby file. It will
load the environments and then create models.
MS: Yes.
DN: And then you can
execute this file with a rake task.
MS: Yes.
Let me just set up our questions.
So very simply we want to do Question.create.
[Silence]
So we have, what did we say
before... image and... description.
That would be the very
simple way of setting it up.
But we want to do something a little smarter I think.
Let's put the images somewhere.
DN: Yes, I gave them to you with your challenge,
but I don't think they're in your rails app yet.
MS: No they're not.
DN: When I first created these
images, I named them dog.jpg, cat.jpg
And then I realised that was a little
opinionated so I changed it to 'Animal 1', 'Animal 2'...
[Melinda thinks]
MS: Yes, let's just throw them in public.
Then maybe I'll come up with a nicer place later
[Silence]
How do you loop through numbers again... times.
I'll double check that again.
It would be Ruby times rather than...
[Silence]
DN: That's a great way of finding
documentation, is that something to do with Alfred.
MS: Yes so...
DN: So you've got it searching rails documentation.
MS: Yes, it's a workflow that's called Dev Doctor.
And it's not just for rails, it's for most
programming languages that you can think of.
DN: Oh that's good.
MS: Yes, it's really handy.
Yes, I was right.
I shouldn't question myself sometimes.
[Silence]
DN: Oh that's...
MS: Yes, sublime, likes to try to open...
DN: A binary file.
They could be called Animal-1.jpg, Animal-2...
I guess six times is going to be 0 to 5, isn't it?
MS: Yes.
[Silence]
I'm not sure we can make this
smarter, in the sense that...
Well, I guess what we can do here is...
[Silence]
Which animals do we actually have?
DN: That's a good question.
Hedgehog, Squirrel, Goat?
DN: Yes, that's a Goat!
MS: So...
[Silence]
Dog, Cat, Cow...
DN: You're definitely not a
machine, you make that look easy.
[Silence]
So... I want to do that.
Two times.
So now what we then get is, for every single animal...
Basically for every image we create six questions
asking whether or not it's
all the other animals as well.
DN: OK.
MS: So I think this should work.
DN: So we'll end up with 36.
MS: Yes, 36 questions.
DN: Where most of them are wrong answers.
MS: Yes.
So let's see...
We need to migrate first because
we haven't done that before.
And I hope that this doesn't blow up.
[Silence]
36, how about that!
And then pluck all the...No, I don't call them URLs image.
We should have 6 of each of them.
[Silence]
DN: Is this a hedgehog, is this a squirrel, goat?
MS: And I forgot to put a question mark at the end.
DN: Well you could even hard
code that. It is a question.
MS: I just redo it... so let's just delete them all again.
[Silence]
MS: I'll just add the question mark.
There we go, that's nicer.
DN: That does look nice.
It feels like being in a car with a toddler. [laughter]
So next up is, we want to display these to a user.
[Melinda thinks]
DN: Is that worth a commit do you think?
MS: Yes, it is, I keep forgetting that.
We've got our schema, seeds and then a question.
[Silence]
[New Chapter]
DN: OK, so we've got the question
model, what do you want to do next?
MS: The next thing is
displaying the questions to users.
So we want to, I guess, show the image and the question,
like... is this a hedgehog, is this a squirrel?
And then maybe not quite yet...
do the logic of allowing a user to answer yes or no.
but maybe creating fake buttons initially,
so we just display here's the image,
here's the question, and here are the buttons.
So, I guess we need to figure out
how does the user get to these?
DN: I suppose we could have...
when the user logs in the root page
could be a list of questions to begin with,
and each item in the list
would be a link to the question itself.
MS: Yes, that's probably the easiest way to do it.
OK, hmm...
So let's go to our route file and start with that.
So we...
basically we want the route
of the page to be linked to the...
to our questions.
DN: So it's a questions index really.
MS: Yes.
And we also want resources :questions.
Well, our questions to resources.
and then  I always like doing this...
To make sure that we are only
influencing the actions that we are using,
rather than getting all 6 of
them and leaving those in place.
DN: And in any case we don't want the
system to allow you to create questions... not yet.
MS: No, so only the index can show for now.
So let's make our questions controller.
[Silence]
As I said before, we have index...
and show...
DN: I notice you use a rails
generator when you're creating a model.
but not when creating a controller... is that normal?
Uhm... [Melinda thinks]
MS: I'm not sure I do that actually.
[Melinda thinks again]
Yes, I guess because I know
exactly what comes back when I...
use generate model.
And I always feel that with generate
controller I get more than I want.
DN: Yes, it generates the asset files,
stylesheets, JavaScripts and so on.
MS: Yes, normally it's like...
DN: More cruft than what you want.
MS: Yes, and again I'm guessing there's an easier way
to specify which things you exactly
want when you generate the controller.
But.. I kind of like having a
bit more control over it myself
and being able to see when I'm adding which files.
DN: Yes, sure.
MS: While with a model you
get the rspec file, the user file and...
...the migration,
and not much beyond that.
DN: So the model generator
gives you exactly what you want,
and you think the controller
generator gives you too much.
MS: Yes, pretty much. [Laughter]
DN: Yes, I can relate to that.
MS: So let's create the views for that as well.
So questions.
And in here we have...
I'll have to say index.
[Silence]
And show.
So...
Index is going to grab all
the questions that we have.
[Silence]
Here.
DN: That should be fine.
MS: I realise I never use the all
because normally with so much more data...
DN: We don't need to paginate anything.
[Silence]
MS: So let's just show the description first.
That should just show up here... No.
[Silence]
DN: Lovely.
MS: All the questions.
So let's make it a little nicer.
[Silence]
And let's link to...
Now what do we call that?
[Silence]
So question_path
So do we want to show the image on this page already?
DN: I think that would get a bit busy.
Maybe even you shouldn't show the text.
Maybe it should be like, question 1, question 2.
MS: Yes, we could even change it to that.
It makes it a bit more serious... what we're going to get.
[Silence]
DN: I guess they have IDs already
don't they which will probably be sequential.
MS: Yes.
[Silence]
Yes, they are sequential but
because we did the seed task twice,
they're not going to start on 1
DN: That doesn't matter does it?
MS: No.
But it might be nicer if
they were, so we can do instead...
I'll just change this to...
each_with_index
It's for the user that we're displaying what
question number it is, showing on the page itself.
[Silence]
Don't want to do it that way.
Let's just throw it into that one...
There we go.
DN: That looks good.
And maybe plus 1s that we don't have.
DN: Question zero.
MS: Yes.
DN: Question zero "what is your
name", my science teacher always did that.
MS: Yes mine didn't. [Laughter]
So, clicking on here won't do
anything because we don't have a show yet.
We have a show, but I think we'll just leave it that way.
DN: Right.
MS: So on this page... [Melinda thinks]
Someone who grabbed a question.
[Silence]
Let's just do that for now, does that work?
Yes, it would if I did that!
So let's show the description.
Is this a hedgehog.
I must look that up, I always forget.
[Silence]
image_tag
And then we have...
[Silence]
I'll say that first.
It's not called URL, it's called image.
DN: Ah... Close.
MS: So because we've put it in the public...
DN: Yes, is it assuming that
it's in the assets directory?
MS: Yes, I think it is.
So let's move it to the assets directory.
[Silence]
DN: OK.
MS: So this still won't work
because we need to specify...
[Silence]
DN: I thought that assumption was built in?
MS: I'm not sure it is.
DN: Would it help to actually look at the HTML source?
[Silence]
DN: It's missing .jpg.
MS: Yes, it is.
DN: In fact, did you move the images or
copy them. Are they still in the public directory?
MS: I think I might have copied them... yes.
DN: Well that's good because
that's where it's looking for them.
MS: So if we change this...
DN: Ah, there's no E.
That's it.
MS: We're not using that at
all but just adding .jpg behind it.
I guess I left that out during the seeds.
I didn't actually put that in.
DN: Regenerate them.
MS: Yes.
It's neater at least.
[Silence]
Let's delete our previous ones.
DN: Oh, I think you left the quote.
[Silence]
There we go.
DN: Do you think the image is a bit big?
MS: Yes.
I think we could do that with
size. Ah... just width and height.
I made use all the images are the same
width, but they do vary slightly in height.
MS: Right, so let's set the width.
[Silence]
300... yes that looks good.
DN: That looks good.
MS: Let's clean this up a bit.
[Silence]
DN: That's great, ship it!
MS: Let's put the question underneath the picture.
[Silence]
DN: I guess the form with the yes/no
answers would be straight after the text.
MS: Here at the top let's add
a link back to all the questions.
[Silence]
DN: OK.
MS: There we go.
[Silence]
DN: I'm sure some of them are [laughter].
Is that a good place to check in do you think?
MS: Yes.
So we don't actually need these,
because in the end we did just find it.
[Silence]
So allow users to see questions.
[New Chapter]
DN: So I guess next we have the yes/no to do.
Would that be a yes button and a no button,
or would it be a radio button with
yes and no and then a submit button?
[Melinda thinks]
MS: I think a radio button would be nicer.
How do we do that again? [laughter] Let's have a look.
radio_button
[Silence]
DN: Now there's a thought, what is it a form for?
When we submit this form
what actually happens in the system.
MS: Yes, so we haven't really looked at that yet.
But, I'm thinking we basically want a new
model that lies between the questions and the users.
We could call it user
questions but that seems wrong.
But, maybe just answers.
So an answers model that
belongs to a user and to a question.
Let's leave that form for now.
[Melinda thinks]
So rails join...
This doesn't actually show anything.
[Silence]
Its weird, I know what I'm looking for
but I don't know what words I'm looking for.
Is there a through keyword that you can use on, like...
to join the users to the
questions through the join table?
[Silence]
has_many :through
DN: So in our case, appointments is like an answer,
physicians and patients are
like users and questions, in a sense.
MS: Yes.
Yes, they are. [laughter]
I normally use the generate function to create this...
So we want an answer to have...
a boolean value for yes or no.
DN: Can we call it response perhaps.
MS: Yes, that's a good idea.
[Silence]
And then we want it to belong to both
the questions and to the (other one)...users.
DN: Do you want that comma?
MS: No you don't.
[Silence]
DN: I think if you do user, colon, reference...
Or it might be references, I don't quite remember.
[Silence]
MS: Yes, it is references.
So we had a response, we have...
the relationship to the user and the
question, and we don't need anything else, right?
DN: No, that looks good.
[Silence]
MS: Right so... your answer
belongs to a user and a question.
So we just want to have... answers.
[Silence]
Questions through answers,
but also has many answers.
DN: Right.
[Silence]
Same again for questions.
This has many answers
and this has many users...
[Silence]
DN: That looks good.
MS: So we now have that model.
DN: Is that worth a commit do you think?
Or is it not worth a commit?
MS: Ah... maybe.
Yes, I think it is, its fallen off, but...
[Silence]
[New Chapter]
MS: Right, so I guess that next
up is allowing users to click yes or no,
and then recording their response.
[Melinda thinks]
To do this nicely we need...
one is an answers controller.
DN: Right.
MS: Which... all it does is create...
[well records], the yes or no answer.
So we can...
So... basically we want our answers to be...
[Silence]
I'm trying to think what is
the best way of modeling this.
DN: If it was a nested resource, then the URL for...
Say you post to create an answer...
MS: It would contain the question.
And we also know who the
user is, because they're logged in.
So we can grab that from there.
[Silence]
So we only want new and create.
Maybe not even new,
Because we're not really displaying anything.
[Melinda thinks]
So let's create our... answers_controller.
[Silence]
What are we trying to do...
have our show... so here we need to add...
a form_for... an answer.
So here we need to create...
[Silence]
Answer.new
[Melinda thinks]
So I want to do something similar...
[Silence]
I'm not completely sure about that anymore.
So question_answers...
[Silence]
Alright, and then we wanted the...
radio_button_tag.
[Melinda looks for the radio button]
I'm not really sure...
[Silence]
That's actually under public license...
rails form_for radio buttons example.
[Silence]
DN: I suppose what we want is two radio buttons.
And I suppose one is true and one is false,
It's a boolean we save in the
answers, but the labels can say yes or no.
MS: Yes, so basically something like that.
So we want a radio button first.
Which... response, true.
And then a label for it.
[Silence]
False...
No.
So I think that should work... No it doesn't.
Oh... migrations.
[Silence]
DN: Right.
That looks nice.
MS: Yes.
But we can't do anything with it
yet, we've got to add the submit button.
[Silence]
DN: It's interesting the default submit button text.
It sort of makes sense in this case.
MS: Yes, but we can change it.
No we cant, not like that.
DN: I think the comma isn't needed.
MS: Yes.
Let's have a look, Oh yes it is.
DN: OK.
So is it hitting the right controller?
MS: Yes, it is.
DN: That looks good.
MS: We haven't actually put
anything in the controller yet.
So we have answer.
[Silence]
So we require an answer.
And that should have a...
response.
[Silence]
DN: Don't you just pass in answer_params?
MS: Yes... Oh because we...
And then we also want to pass...
[Silence]
I'm not sure that would be submitted.
DN: So the user is known by the system,
but it's not created in the format at the moment is it?
MS: No, the question will be.
DN: I suppose you could put the
user ID in as a hidden field in the form.
And then it could be treated like the other fields.
MS: Yes, we can.
[Silence]
So just hidden_field_tag... yes it is.
DN: There's a thought... do we have a current_user method?
MS: I'm not sure.
I don't think we do.
DN: We have a logged_in method
but not a current_user method.
MS: No, so let's create that.
[Silence]
and then session.
MS: That should work.
[Silence]
DN: answer, that's interesting.
So they all got submitted.
DN: User is empty, and response is true
which is good because you clicked yes.
MS: And the question ID is right.
But somehow...
DN: Maybe it's because... when you call radio_button_tag...
it doesn't put it inside of a form object does it?
Whereas if you used f.radio_button...
[Silence]
DN: Instead of radio_button_tag,
I think you can just say radio_button.
[Silence]
MS: Oh... actually, we weren't calling that anyway.
[Melinda thinks]
So current_user.
[Silence]
DN: Couldn't find user with ID.
DN: Are we actually logged in at the moment?
MS: I thought we were.
No we're not, that explains it.
[Silence]
DN: I wonder, should the hidden field be user ID?
MS: Yes.
That's most probably better.
[Silence]
I think there's something wrong here.
DN: What is it calling merge anyway?
Parameters is 73.
MS: Well that's because...
that's the only params that it has.
But, I'm going to find...
[Silence]
So our ID is 2.
So let's actually just try to...
[Silence]
look if we can get the current
user ID. Does that part even work?
So it finds the current user ID.
DN: So it is finding that OK?
MS: Yes.
DN: I wonder, what if we were
to hard code hidden_field to user 2.
[Silence]
DN: So it's not a problem
with the current_user method is it?
It's something about the
way we're calling hidden_field.
Should it be user_id rather than user?
MS: But we tried that... even that.
So there's something...
[Silence]
form_for and hidden_field
So it was a form_for that we're using.
[Silence]
DN: Do we need to say value?
MS: Yes.
[Silence]
So now if we hit 'yes'.
DN: Excellent, so finally
we are hitting our controller.
MS: Yes, and then in the controller, we don't need that,
because we've got question_id and user_id.
[Silence]
So why's that within create?
It's because we don't need that.
[Silence]
I think that worked.
Or well, it errored because we don't
have a template, rather than it not creating.
DN: Excellent.
MS: Sort of, except the question ID.
DN: But the response is nil and the user_id is nil.
DN: So something is not matching up there.
[Silence]
MS: So why would it only set the question ID?
DN: You know how before you
had params.require(:answer)?
And then you took our the require(:answer).
I didn't quite follow why you did that.
MS: That was because, looking at the params,
it didn't seem as if answer was
actually being passed along.
DN: But then you also changed
the form, and got rid of... what was it...
it was, some of the parameters were
inside a create object, weren't they?
If you got rid of 'as created' there...
MS: OK yes.
DN: Ah, that did work.
MS: Yes,
DN:  Ah, the question ID is nil.
MS: Yes.
DN: Oh that's funny.
So the question ID is coming from the
URL, so it's not scoped inside of the answer.
MS: So the other way of doing
it is adding another hidden field.
DN: Ah, well now you know how to do that.
MS: I'm sure there's a neater
way of doing this, but for now...
[Silence]
So let's delete the ones that we have so far.
So now I say yes and submit.
[Silence]
So now it's all set.
DN: Ah, excellent.
MS: Now... we still don't show anything.
So... at the end of this let's redirect... back to...
DN: Where did we end up...
well I guess we could just go back to the...
page for the question we just answered.
But this time instead of showing
a form [they both talk together].
all answers to that question so far.
MS: Yes, so that's...
That's question_path.
[Silence]
So we're back here.
DN: That's probably worth committing isn't it?
MS: Almost, I'd add another thing just here with...
If you haven't, or maybe not...
I was thinking... if you have already
answered the question, don't show the form.
DN: Maybe we could do that in the next commit.
[Silence]
MS: So what have we done
here... we're basically allowing
[Silence]
Allow users to answer questions.
[New Chapter]
DN: So we've now got the ability to answer a question.
MS Yes.
How about we now tackle
the part of the challenge where
if you answered a question, you can view a
summary of all the responses to that question.
MS: Yes, so basically we've already answered
this and we don't want to display it anymore.
So let's add an if statement here.
So here...
[Silence]
rather than saying .new let's do a find_or_create.
So where user is the current user.
and question...
[silence]
I think this should work.
DN: Right, so if the user hasn't answered
this question then it will generate a new one.
MS: Yes.
DN: In which all fields will be empty...
apart from user and question.
I guess the response field will be empty.
MS: Yes, and the response field
is the one we care about right now.
DN: Whereas if it can find one, the response
field will be true or false, rather than nil.
MS: Yes.
So now if we do answer.response.present.
[inaudible] nope.
DN: Ah, there's no find_or_create.
[Silence]
MS: Create by.
There we go.
DN: Ah excellent.
MS: Well no because we already answered this.
DN: I think we've got the
wrong branch of the 'if'.
So we're asking, "if present" and...
MS: Then we're showing a form for actually...
MS: So in that case... yes.
DN: So in there we should have some kind of a summary.
[Silence]
MS: Yeah...
Let's make this nicer and do here...
[Silence]
DN: Right.
MS: I have a feeling one or
two or these are... that one, yes.
DN: Because its a method call isn't it... a macro.
[Silence]
DN: Nice.
MS: Yes, what do you want to
show here, a summary of what's been...
DN: I was thinking it could be...
Let's say the system has 100 users and
80 of them have answered this question,
It could be something like,
79 people said yes and 1 person said no,
[Drew thinks]
Or it could be a percentage
rather than actual numbers...
MS: Yes, well we could play
around with that a bit I guess.
So let's create...
[Silence]
I am not happy with the names, but they can do for now.
We'll do this on the command line first.
So our questions...
Let's do our first one.
[Silence]
So I should have one answer...
two answers, two times true.
[Silence]
DN: Ah... that's nice.
MS: And then false.
[Silence]
The only problem with this is we
don't actually know what the question is.
MS: So we'll extract... that.
[Silence]
DN: Oh I see.
MS: It's not the most optimal
because it keeps on doing this.
Yes, we can actually...
DN: Ah yes, memoize it.
MS: Yes.
DN: Alright.
[Silence]
MS: Think I need to move that...
So now we have...
DN: I spotted another one on line 5 there.
MS: Yes...
yes_responses_count
[Silence]
So we have 2 and zero.
DN: Two nil. [laughter]
Let's just make it a little bit...
[Silence]
DN: It looks good.
MS: Simple, but...
DN: Is that worth a commit do you think?
MS: Yes, certainly, it's not a big commit but...
[Silence]
[New Chapter]
DN: So how about we go back to the
question and look at what we've still got to cover.
MS: So we've got the first bit,
allowing people to answer yes or no.
And we've got the last bit where we see
the summary of how people have answered.
We're missing the middle bit
where questions get resolved
after a certain amount of answers.
DN: Yes, the way I phrased that,
it was to give you the chance
to suggest how we might implement that.
So let's talk through some scenarios.
MS: I guess the most basic one
is just to have a threshold of
the number of people that we want to have answered.
So it could be as simple as...
If 10 people answered this question,
it doesn't matter what they
answered, the question is resolved.
But what you might get then is that
5 people said yes and 5 people said no.
And that's not really a satisfying answer.
DN: Not a consensus.
MS: Yes.
So one step further would be to look
at when has the majority answered the same answer.
DN: Yes.
MS: One way of doing that is...
Maybe still using a threshold so we at
least have a certain amount of people answering.
Maybe 20.
DN: OK.
MS: So let's say we need to have at least 20 answers.
Of which 90% need to be the same?
DN: Yes, I'm not well versed in
statistics but to me that sounds good.
MS: [laughter] good enough for this type of system yes.
Erm... yeah.
So how do we want to do this?
DN: So if we were to say a
threshold, as you say, it could be 20
Or, since we don't have much
data to play with, it could be 3.
MS: Yes.
DN: Where would you store the threshold?
So that would be, I think, in
a constant in the question class.
MS: So...
[Silence]
DN: And given a question, it would be
nice to say "how many questions do you have".
Or, more simply, "have you
reached the threshold of answers?"
[Silence]
MS: So...
count is...
[Silence]
DN: OK.
MS: Yes, really simple.
So now we've got...
I'm guessing, we want to do 'resolved?'.
And in that case threshold would have to be reached.
And maybe 'majority_answered?'
DN: 'majority_agreed?', that's nice.
[Silence]
MS: I can't spell!
Yes what's the calculation we want to do here?
DN: It's a majority of either
90% said yes, or 90% said no, isn't it?
MS: Yes.
DN: Both can be true, the case.
MS: Yes, so calculating both I guess.
So, we have total = answers.count
And then we've got yes_percentage.
As I said before, I'm not very good at naming things.
So that's...
Let's take a step in-between.
So we have yes_total.
[Silence]
DN: Right.
MS: Normally I would extract these
and put them in scopes, most probably.
But for now...
So yes_percentage is yes.
Total divided by total.
And the same for no.
DN: And for the percentage we need
to multiply by 100 as well don't we?
MS: Yes.
This is the point where I'm wondering
how do we deal with these type of numbers.
I think I might want to do that.
DN: Or is it 'to_f'?
MS: Yes.
I'm really blanking today. [Laughter]
[Silence]
So then if...
Greater than... 90.
[Silence]
DN: Another way of saying that
is yes_percentage is greater than 90
or yes_percentage is less than 10.
But, let's go with it.
MS: Yes, true.
DN: Shall we play around with
that on the console and see what works?
MS: Yes, our last question
had two answers so that should...
DN: Do you need to reload or does
that stuff get reloaded automatically?
MS: Yes.
[Silence]
MS: I knew it... it blew up.
DN: Does reload throw away your instance variables?
MS: No.
DN: OK.
[Silence]
MS: So the nos are not resolved.
DN: False.
Right, so we've got two answers.
MS: Yes.
DN: That's funny because I thought
both answers were yes, weren't they?
MS: Yes, but we need to have at least 20 answers.
DN: But you did 'threshold_reached?'
I thought you did 'majority_agreed?'.
MS: I did 'resolved' and then
I looked at 'majority_agreed?'
Oh right, we did do 'majority_agreed?'.
[Silence]
Let's just do a...
That's the wrong number.
DN: Were we working with the first question
previously, rather than the last question?
I think the first question is
the one that has responses.
MS: Oh, yes.
DN: Ah, there we go.
So the 'majority_agreed?' is not robust at the moment.
If it has no answers it blows up.
MS: Yes.
DN: But that's OK.
Well, we're running out of
time here, so unfortunately,
so we are not going to have
time to build a user interface for this.
But it's been interesting watching
you just play around with the console.
[New Chapter}
DN: So if you had more time, what's the
next thing you would do with this system?
MS: I guess the next thing would be to actually...
use what we've just done
here with resolving questions.
Putting in the interface...
and then beyond that...
doing something a bit smarter about
how we're displaying the questions to users.
Because right now we're just
showing all the questions in a list.
It would be a bit nicer if, the
user logs on to the system
and they get shown a random image.
DN: OK, so people don't see them in the same order,
in which case you have question 1 having
loads of answers and later ones having fewer.
MS: And maybe doing something smarter like
showing the questions that don't have many answers,
so you can boost the ones that need more answers.
DN: So it would be nice to have
a way to ask the question model
"Which of your records needs the next answer?"
And maybe recognizing that the current
user shouldn't answer the same question twice.
That's something you would have to think about.
MS: Exactly.
DN: And once you've got that you can
answer a question and ask for the next question.
And it will pick one randomly
for you, that would be nice.
MS: Yes, that would be cool.
DN: OK, well thanks very
much for coming on the show Melinda,
it's been really interesting watching you work.
MS: Thanks for inviting me.
DN: My pleasure.
Captions produced by Bonnie Roworth