Welcome to Peer to Peer
where you can watch how
experts solve tech problems.
Our guest today is Tom Stuart,
author of Understanding
Computation and veteran Rubyist.
I'm your host Drew Neil,
and the challenge
I've set for Tom is called ...
Counting Tree Nodes.
DN: So Tom would you like
to start by reading out the problem.
TS: Sure, it says:
Model a tree of max depth 5
Given a collection of such trees,
let me sort by these properties:
Total number of ancestors,
Total number of terminals,
These totals should be correct following
any operation that adds or removes a node.
OK.
DN: Is that clear?
TS: Well ... I'm not entirely sure
what you mean by
either of those things.
By terminals do you
mean leaves of the tree?
DN: Ok, so a leaf can be
anything that has no children.
By terminal I mean a
leaf at the maximum depth.
It's a leaf that cannot have any children.
In fact if you turn to the
next page there's an illustration.
There we have the root at the center
and then there's 4 concentric circles.
I've said max depth 5, you might
prefer to call it max depth 4
depending on whether you
call the root a level or not.
In that picture the terminals are the ones
farthest from the root, pictured in red.
The blue ones are ancestors.
Some of them happen to be leaves,
some of them do have children
but it's only a terminal if
it's on the outermost ring and
it's not possible for it have any more children.
TS: Well this answers
my other two questions.
One was what you meant by depth
because from the problem description
I didn't know if you were
including the root in that.
If I remember my
graph theory correctly,
one of the measures in
any tree is depth but I think
it's about how many
edges you have to traverse
whereas that's not
exactly what you want.
So you're talking about
how many fence posts there are
not how many spaces
between the fence posts.
DN: Yes.
OC: And I was going to
ask you about ancestors.
This here is not what I expected.
I thought by ancestors you would mean
nodes that had children
since an ancestor is
your parents' parents etc.
DN: So you're looking upward.
OC: But this is looking
at the root as being .....
I'd use the word descendants for that.
DN: Yes that's obviously a
better word. (laughter)
It doesn't matter ....
TS: Do I need to
know what this is for.
Is this the entire
scope of the problem?
DN: Yes, but if you feel it's too much
we can make it sortable by one of those fields.
You can pick whichever you like.
TS: One more question.
The count you've called ancestors
is how many nodes
there are in the tree
apart from the root.
DN: Yes.
TS: I'm hoping that that will always be
the number of nodes
in the tree minus one
because you're not considering the root.
DN: Exactly.
TS: Is the absolute value
of that number important
or is just its relative values?
For example if we did
count the root would that matter,
or is the only reason
to count this number
so you can sort the trees?
DN: Yes, it is so that
you can sort the trees.
TS: Presumably it's not
going to be a problem
to subtract one from
whatever that number is.
DN: I've used the word ancestors but
if you want to call them descendants,
forget that I ever called
them ancestors (laughter).
TS: It's tempting to
go with the terminology
that you've presented here
unless you feel uncomfortable with it.
If you want to change
the problem then do so.
DN: Yes, let's change the problem
and call them descendants.
TS: Shall we get started then?
DN: Let's do that.
OK, I'm going to make a ....
let's call it trees.
I would like to start by ...
clarifying what we want in here
by writing an acceptance test.
So I'm going to use cucumber for that.
Let me be strange about this ...
This might take a
while to install cucumber.
I should have done
it before we started.
Ordinary I would use cucumber
when I'm building a web application.
It's an obvious
benefit for me
to have all that
stuff written down.
More tenuous here I think
but I'm just
going to go with it
because it will give
me an opportunity
to write down the problem
before I start thinking about it.
So to crystallize that
conversation we just had ...
about what you mean.
So I'm going to run Cucumber.
And now it will
hopefully run zero scenarios.
I'm going to make ....
what shall we call it, a trees feature?
I suppose the actual feature that we're
talking about is the ability to sort them.
So I'll call that sorting feature.
So feature sorting trees ....
and I suppose I'm
going to be writing this
from the point of view of.....
ordinarily, if you're writing an
acceptance test for a web application
you would be thinking
about a particular kind of user,
From the perspective of
a client of an API
You haven't said there has
to be buttons to be clicked on.
So I'm going to say:
"as a user of the tree data structure".
I want to be able to sort collections of trees.
by various criteria.
so that ...
I don't really know why,
it's just part of
the problem statement.
I'm going to say:
So that my collections are in the right order.
In a real situation I
would interrogate you further
about why you want these
trees to be in the right order.
TS: So one of your scenarios was
sort by total
number of descendants.
Your other one was sort
by total number of terminals.
Given that I have a collection of trees
Let's say when I sort it by
total number of descendants,
then it should be ordered by...
DN: 'It' being the collection
rather than an individual tree?
TS: Does that make sense?
DN: Yes it does.
TS: That pronoun is referring to
the thing I was talking about before.
So this is going to be exactly the same,
but this will say sorted
by total number of terminals.
And this will be total
number of terminals.
Are you happy with that?
DN: Yes that's fine.
TS: think I will
change this to 'the collection'
just because... Are we sorting the
nodes of the tree or the collection?
DN: The collection
is what we are sorting.
TS: So that's slightly more
verbose but hopefully clearer,
which is what we want.
I'll run that feature.
It has complained that I
haven't defined these steps
and it has given me everything I need
so I will make a features step definitions.
Tree steps file.
DN: You're using Control P
there to create a file.
TS: Yes. By hitting control Y.
And it creates all
the parent directories.
It saves me
dropping to the terminal.
DN: Yes a good user interface.
Before I start
implementing these, I can see
that I've got a couple of when steps
that are essentially the same.
They differ only
in their final word.
And ditto these.
It's bothering me
that I don't know
what the correct
spelling of descendants is.
I'm going to look it up.
I'm sure that's
right but to be sure ....
Yes that's right.
I am much more confident now.
When I write this I want
there to be a block argument here
that says something
like 'order by' and then,
to keep this compact, I'm going to say
case order by and I'm expecting
there to be a descendants case,
and a terminals
case, so I don't end up
duplicating what I'm doing here.
This will just be anything...
Oh! well I should
have done that here.
So when I sort my collection
by total number of 'something',
and then I can
put my code in there.
There's going to be
something very similar here I think.
This is going to be 'Something'.
and then:
So that's the
skeleton of what we want.
In here I want to have
trees be equal to something.
So that's my first challenge.
I suppose here I will
write the code that I wish I had.
Although that's not
terribly straight forward.
In order for us to
verify that this code is working.
what I don't want to do is things like
make a random collection of trees,
and then ask the API to sort them.
and then go through
and say, "when I ask each
of those trees what
their total number of ancestors is"
then it's increasing because that would not
tell me that my code is working correctly.
It would just verify that
the code that I've written
did the same as the code that I've written.
I would like you and I to agree on
some representative collection of trees,
which to begin with is in an
arbitrary order that we determine.
And then for us to decide what
order that collection SHOULD be in
after it's been sorted..
DN: Yes, OK.
I would like to initialize
a few representative trees,
and then put them into the collection.
So I would like this to be something like trees equals
small tree, large tree ...
DN:  We could also have a shallow tree,
one that has no terminals or ...
TS: And then with the intention being that
down here, we would say:
"expect trees to be equal to
things that are in a different order".
DN: Yes.
TS: And that will hopefully
verify that things are working.
DN: Three seems like a good number.
TS: Are you sure, OK.
TS: Let's see how many we can think of.
So you want them to be of maximum depth,
and have, at most 5 nodes,
counting from the root node.
DN: Yes that's right.
So that's 4 edges in the path
from the root to the most distant leaf.
So they don't have to go
all the way out to the periphery.
DN: They don't.
Those would be unfinished fences, if you like.
TS: Fences! (laughter)
Let's just say the simplest
possible tree is just one node.
DN: Yes, which would be a root.
TS: I'm trying to speak
through my hesitation here!
I'm going to have to make a decision about ...
what's the class called
and how it's instantiated.
I'm concerned about baking
that into my step definition here
because although I am
prepared to make a decision now,
I don't know if I want
to live with that decision.
I'm going to write a helper
method outside the step definition
which I used to build trees.
So here I can call build tree and give it
something that's a little bit agnostic.
DN: Yes.
That doesn't talk about
the actual name of the class
or how it's instantiated.
Do you pass in an options
hash or positional arguments.
Or do you create an empty
one and mutate it or whatever?
I can try and keep this step definition
to just stuff that we're interested in.
My instinct here is to think of each node
of a tree as being a collection of its children
and a leaf is a node that has no children.
DN: Correct.
I don't know yet if we are going to need to
distinguish between parent nodes and leaves.
Your problem statement
didn't say anything about
storing values on the node.
In a binary tree you might
only store values at the leaves,
and the nodes are just a collection of children.
For now, since you didn't
mention it in the statement.
I'm going to assume that what
we want to represent is the structure
with no values stored within it.
And if we want to add to
it later I want it to be flexible.
If we finish this and then you say
I want you to add up all the numbers in the tree
we will find a way to store them in the tree.
DN:  I don't want to add
requirements at this stage.
TS: OK so what I was saying
was, I think of a node as being
a possible empty collection of children.
So for me, the obvious representation here
is to give it an array.
And say "I want you to build a tree",
and here are the children of the root node
which in that case is nothing.
So if I just want a root, node it will be like that.
What else could we do?
I can think of a 'wide tree'
that would be something like
it's only one deep but
has lots of direct descendants.
That would be a node in the center and
then 5 emanating from it.
DN: So that would have
many descendants but no terminals.
TS: Yes, exactly.
TS: Do you have any other
suggestions, as the owner?
DN: I guess we could do something that is deep.
TS: Would that be deep and narrow?
We could have one that's just got 5 children.
Like this ...
DN: Yes, right.
TS: I'm already liking this because you
can almost see the structure of the tree.
Each set of brackets is one node I think.
This is just one node,
this is one node with 5 children,
and this 12345.
So that's what you meant by a tree?
DN: Yes.
I'm going to write a comment next to each of these
to keep track of what we think
the metric is for each of them.
This one would have no descendants, and no terminals.
DN: Yes.
TS: This one would have 5 descendants.
(I'll write that down).
And no terminals.
This one has I think, 4 descendants.
Is that correct?
DN: Yes it is because we don't count the root.
TS: And one terminal?
DN: Exactly, yes.
TS: It's frustrating that we have two trees
that have no terminals, but that's fine,
we can cope with that.
Thinking ahead, because
the sort in Ruby isn't stable
There's a chance that if two
trees tie on the number of terminals
the sort is going to put
them in an arbitrary order.
But, we'll just have to cross
that bridge when we come to it.
That's absolutely fine.
What other kinds of tree could we have?
DN: We could have a deep wide tree that has ...
perhaps 2 descendants ...
in two entirely different branches,
that go as far as the terminal.
TS: Like this?
DN: That's right.
TS: We can have ....
So I think that's ... I don't know why ....
DN: Your missing the final ....
TS: I don't know why vim isn't ...
That threw me, I was expecting
to see a highlight on the first [bracket]
DN: But if you put your cursor
on the first opening bracket.
TS: Yes it highlights the closing one.
What are our metrics for this?
DN: We have 3 terminals and lots of descendants.
TS: Maybe that doesn't matter.
That's certainly got the most.
DN: It's going to be the winner.
TS: My expectation would be that there are 12,
because there were 4 in this one.
And we have basically tripled that one up.
Just a sanity check this!
Would we expect that these two things would ....
that sorting them by
descendants versus by terminals
is going to produce a different order
otherwise it isn't a useful test case.
If we sort them by the number of descendants
then we have none ... 4,5 many.
So that would be just one
deep tree, wide tree, deep wide tree.
DN: Yes.
Whereas if we sort them by terminals,
we would expect them to be in this order.
Like none, none, one and three.
Bearing that in mind....
I will not put them in in that order.
I'll put them in yet another
order so we can see the sort work.
So let's say ....
Deep tree, just one ....
this is an instance variable.
and the reason why they are
instance variables is so I can
refer to them in there
outside of this lexical scope.
Deep tree, just one node.
Deep wide tree, wide tree.
DN: Yes.
TS: I'm hoping that's enough to get us started.
I'll just check that, by running ....
Oh! Undefined method: build tree. OK, fine.
That's the failure I was expecting.
I will quickly make a features ...
I need to define that method somewhere.
I will make a file and put it in support.
I'll call it trees helper.
And so I don't forget I'm also going to make
that method available to Cucumber,
so I will remember to put a file in features.
The names of these files
are of no consequence,
it's just what I'm used to calling them.
So in here I want to require ....
just trying to think ....
I think I will need to require relative.
I'm trying to work out if this file is
going to run before or after the other one
because cucumber will load
all of the files in the directory.
Just to be safe I will require it.
I will do require relative trees helper
then if it hasn't already been loaded,
it will load it because I want to say world ....
and say make that available
in all of my step definitions.
This needs an argument, children.
It takes an array of children.
Now I have to make a decision
about how to instantiate these things.
For now I'll assume we just have a single class
and I'll call it node because
that's a word we've been using.
I'm assuming this will
ultimately return a new node,
but we need to know
what children it's going to have.
If that children array is empty ....
let me think in code ...
If the children is empty then it's fine to just do ....
We're going to give it an empty load of children.
And I'm prejudging the idea that we're going to
create these by providing an array of children,
rather than creating an empty one
and then mutating it to add them
but we will investigate whether
that's a good idea or not I suppose.
I'll just make it clearer that
that is going to be an empty array.
It may be that is an optional
argument and if we don't provide it
then it creates an empty node.
But this is what would make sense to me
and I'm thinking in terms
of myself being a client now.
If there are no children we make an empty one,
if there are children then ....
each of the children in my representation here
is of the same form as
the list of children i.e. an array.
I need to call build_tree on
each child to turn it into a node,
then I can pass that collection
of nodes to the constructor of node.
So I just need to call
this recursively on the children.
I know, because I've written Ruby before,
that I can do that by doing
children, map, method, build tree.
That's going to call
build_tree on each individual child.
That's the same as no new
children, map, child, build tree, child.
Just slightly more concise.
In fact I prefer that one.
DN:  Yes, it shows the argument better.
TS: Yes, you can see what's going on there.
Then I just have to
remember to close the brackets.
Now I can see that this line here is a special case.
In this one, we're mapping over an
empty array which gives you an empty array.
So I can get rid of that.
So now where are we....
Now it's complaining
that I don't have a Node class.
Let's make one.
I'll put it in a folder called lib.
I'm hesitating because this is the point at which
I would like to start dropping
down to write some unit tests.
Get this to a point where we're comfortable.
Still say uninitialized constant.
I would like to start
dropping down to unit tests now.
We haven't filled this stuff out yet,
but I think I'm happy to just bounce back and forth.
It would be nice to get this first step passing
because it's saying I don't
know what this Node thing is.
so I would be more comfortable to
drive that out with a unit test now.
TS: The main thing I'm
going to do now is install rspec.
At the time of recording the
most recent version of rspec,
is 3.0.0 release candidate 1. (RC1)
DN:  Bleeding edge!
TS. And hopefully the actual
version 3 will be out soon.
DN: Just out of interest, you've
been running Cucumber scenarios.
Are you suspending Vim or .....?
TS:  I will show you.
DN: So you have something in your vimrc?
TS: Yes, that does literally run.
I'm sure there's a cleverer way than that
but I'm just typing leader 'C' to run Cucumber,
and because I've got
cucumber set up to use bin stubs ....
DN: You don't have do bundle exec.
TS: Yes exactly.
TS: It stores all of these
bin stubs in .bundle/bin,
you can see there's a Cucumber binary there.
and I've got my path set up
so bundle bin is on the path, which
people have arguments
about this on the internet.
It does create the opportunity
for someone to get you to
clone a git repository that already has
a .bundle/bin folder with a binary called 'ls' in it
that emails your password to the person.
I prefer convenience over security,
which is why I'm a terrible programmer.
So that's all installed.
Rspec comes with a nice
thingy that will initialize it for me.
That's made a rspec file with some sensible defaults in,
and it's made a spec helper.
I will just check what's in here.
Yes, there's a lot of guff in here which
for the purpose of this, I'll just get rid of.
The only piece of configuration I want
is that rspec 3 has this wonderful feature called disable_monkey_patching
which will turn off all of the stuff
that patches the main object
and extends Object with the 'should' method.
So the only way I'm going to get
any kind of behavior out of rspec now,
is to specifically say I want to
call this method as part of rspec.
That's good.
I will run all of my specs.
Zero example, zero failures.
I better write some examples then.
I've already committed to
the class being called Node
so I will call this node_spec.
So because I turned monkey patching off,
ordinarily the first thing I would
do here is say "describe something"
but in rspec 3 when you turn monkey patching off
you have to refer to the
top level constant RSpec.describe.
Nodes of a tree.
Now I'm ready to start writing examples here.
If I run all of my tests.
DN: How do you run your rspec tests?
TS: I am using the vim-rspec plugin.
So if I grep ...
That's not very helpful.
Maybe what I want to find here is just spec.
There are a few different bindings here.
Leader 'T' runs the current file.
Leader 'S' runs the part of the
spec that is nearest to the person.
So that's really handy,
I can run focused tests by just pressing Leader 'S'.
And Leader 'L' is excellent because every
time I run the test it remembers how it called rspec.
Every time I press Leader 'L' it re-runs it.
This is from thoughtbot I think. It's very nice.
Where was I?
node_spec.
The first thing I want to do
here is verify that I can create one.
So let's say something like:
When the tree is empty.
That will do.
I want to start with something really simple here.
I'm trying to think what I want to do
here to drive out the creation of the class.
I don't really know what
behavior I want yet but let's say:
It has no children.
I'm already jumping slightly ahead but ...
This is going to help me to
think about what I want the API to be.
DN: Do you want to use the word children?
But I guess children means something different.
TS: That's a good point.
I've already introduced the word
children but yes, I mean direct descendants.
That's just my prejudice
about what trees look like
and what the things in them are called.
TS: I'm already having to
think about the API of the thing here.
I'm uncomfortable with that. Let's
say "it can be created without error".
That's really the bare minimum I would expect,
is the ability to create one of these things.
So I'm going to say expect this block.
Make me a new tree with no children.
Not to raise an error.
DN: Ok
TS: So if I run all my tests.
There's the failure I'm
looking for, uninitialized constant Node.
I created the file.
Or maybe I didn't because I
didn't put anything in it and save it.
There's a class.
If I run all my specs.
It's still saying uninitialized constant though
because I haven't made any attempt to load it.
DN: I wondered if that might
be happening by magic somehow.
TS: No it isn't happening by magic and I like that.
With rspec and Cucumber,
you have to explicitly add them in.
I'm a big fan of this.
One of the things that people
criticize both rspec and Cucumber for
was this lack of explicitness and
doing to much stuff automatically.
Both projects at the time have tended towards removing
that stuff and expecting
you to be more explicit.
In fact a lot of the automatic stuff
that people think of rspec
and cucumber as doing now
are actually being done by
rspec rails and cucumber rails,
because they wire cucumber
and rspec into a rails application
and then put stuff in the spec helper
and env files that boot up your application
and then you've got rails
constant auto loading as if  by magic.
but in this kind of setting we have to be explicit and it's nice
because it means that I can ....
I mean whether or not we end up
with more than one class here I don't know.
This might be the only spec file we write today.
In this spec file I can say "I want to load node".
By convention that lib folder that's
in the root rspec will put it on the load path.
so I don't have to fiddle around with the load path,
but I do have to explicitly
say I want to load this class.
'wrong number of arguments', OK
so it has found it and we've got the
wrong number of arguments in the constructor,
so now I can go back and say:
Now I hope to see a green test.
DN: Yeah, great.
TS: I've just realised that I've
powered on through this a long way
and completely forgotten to make any
commits and that's now starting to make me nervous
because I've just written a line
of actual code and I'm nervous about it.
I'm going to deal with
that by opening a new screen.
I'll still have Vim open but
I'm also going to have another terminal
where I'm going to make some commits.
inaudible
I'm not going to waste any time on this.
I'm going to do some slightly more
coarse-grained commits than I'm happy with.
So I'm now clean.
I should have been in that situation
before but I got over excited by the problem!
Let's go back and look at the test we were writing.
I believe that's all fine.
Everything is happy there.
What I'd like to do now is
start building this functionality out.
I can say, context when the tree is not empty.
This is actually when the node has no children.
I think that's more appropriate.
DN: Yes.
TS: And this is when the node has children.
Oh... what a disaster.
What I'd like to do here...
and I don't know if I will stick with this,
is to have a collection of test doubles.
In fact that's not here, this is here.
It is so I can give it an array
of something without having to
then think about what those are.
Anyway, see how far we can get.
We've still got a very basic
level of functionality here.
DN: Your missing a closing brace.
I'm expecting the evaluation
of that block not to raise an error.
Great, ok.
I've got my Node
class, and I can instantiate
which is great.
I can see here this
is some duplication.
So instead of having
two different things there
I will pull up this.
I'm defining
children in both cases
but in one
context it's empty
and in another
context it's not empty.
That gives me a
nice clean separation.
Those two things
are exactly the same.
Ordinarily I would
refactor this and pull
those out into a
shared example group.
If we duplicate a
lot of examples here,
I'll do that anyway.
Now I want to
think about what
my acceptance
tests are demanding.
I've run these unit
tests a couple of times
The acceptance tests
were complaining about
was, you don't
have a Node class.
Now I have got
the Node class,
it's time for me
to step back up
and run the
cucumber features again
to see if I have finished,
but I don't think I have.
These are failing now.
They are still complaining
that they can't find Node.
and that's because I
need to make sure it's required.
DN: In the environment.
TS: Yes.
So I'll say require
and again I think cucumber
is going to put lib
on the load path again.
I've gone slightly wrong there.
That's not supposed to be green.
These step definitions, tree steps
DN: They don't
actually do anything.
In order to show
what I wanted the
structure to be here,
this needs to be pending.
because I'm not
yet done with it.
That's what I want.
I should not have left these step
definitions that say nothing.
So now it's saying:
You haven't
implemented these steps.
sort by total
number of descendants
or by the total
number of terminals.
Now I can think in terms
of being a client of this API
What do I want
this to look like.
So I've got my
collection of trees,
which I've just
assumed is an array,
but I think
that's reasonable.
If someone gave
me this API and said
You've got a
collection of trees,
and I have
implemented an API, for the trees.
and now I want
you to sort them by
the number of descendants,
or the number of terminals
I would expect
there to be a method
on each tree that I can call
that would give
me a number back,
that would say how many....
trees equals trees sort ....
by something ....
it will either be number of ....
It's tempting to call it
'number of descendants'.
But I'm wondering if it
should be descendants_count.
Maybe that would be nicer.
It's a bit more idiomatic.
But then again, it's at
odds with the language
being used here, so I'm
not sure about that.
I might revisit that later.
I would like it so that ....
I can call descendants_count
or terminals_count
on each node in that
collection, it would give me
a number back and then
it's going to sort the collection
If I run one of my
Cucumber features now.
I would expect to
see actual failures,
which is what
I was hoping for.
This is complaining about
undefined method
descendants_count
terminals_count.
Again I've charged ahead here.
Let's be a bit more meticulous.
So this is:
DN: Your commits sometimes
have more text in the
commit message than
what is to be committed.
I find that to be the most
useful way of doing it.
So let's see,
what did I do here?
I want to split that.
I'm going to commit this change:
Which should have been
pending in the first place.
Now this is:
All clean again, I can relax.
All of the stuff in
my gutter goes away.
DN: Yes, I wanted to
draw attention to that.
I think that's fabulous.
TS: I think it's just
called 'git gutter'.
DN: Do you always
have that enabled?
TS: Yes.
DN: I noticed it and I wondered
if it had crept in at some point.
TS: It only creeps in if
there is something to show.
so if I make a change
the gutter will appear.
If I then make a change back so that git says
there's no change it disappears again.
DN:  I think the reason
we didn't see it for so long
is because
you didn't commit anything.
Everything was added, and new.
TS: The reason why I
didn't make those commits is
because I forgot to 'git
init' in the beginning.
Now I find I don't
remember to make commits.
It's the stuff in the
gutter that reminds me
it's starting to get a bit dirty.
DN: How much noise in
the gutter can you tolerate?
TS: Not very much.
Ordinarily I like to make
commits as frequently as possible.
Very small commits
I can get away with.
And as you say
quite often the message
is longer than the
content of the commit.
The problem here is
that we don't have a
terminals_count, or a
descendants_count method.
This makes me
realise that I'm trying
to do two
scenarios at the same time.
I would like to
focus on just one.
DN: Sure, yes.
TS: I don't want to
be simultaneously implementing
number of descendants
and number of terminals.
I'd rather just look at this one.
I'm going to temporarily:
There are better
ways of doing that.
With Cucumber you
can tag scenarios so you
don't have to run them but ....
this is the simplest thing to do.
I mustn't forget about that
but, as long as I
don't forget about it,
it's going to give me
the opportunity to run
through getting the
descendants count to work.
I'm going to switch
back to my node spec
and have a look at doing that.
So now I need to start
making some decisions around ....
how to even set up the test
because what I want
here is something like:
And then I want
something here that's like
the node is
something here and then
it has five descendants.
And then this would say ....
Which is what we
said in the step definition:
node descendant count
to be equal to 5.
So I know what the example is.
I'm not quite sure exactly
what I want to do here....
because I've got doubles here.
If I just make real instances
of node, I could already
build you a tree
that has five descendants
because we had a similar
one in the step definition.
DN: Yes, right.
So I know how
to make real trees
with 5 descendants.
If I want the children of this
node to be the test doubles,
then I need to work out ....
what it is that makes this
fake tree has five descendants.
This feels like it should
be a recursive method.
The number of
descendants of a tree
is the number of
descendants of all of its
subtrees plus
the node at the top.
If I've got three children
and each one of them
has three descendants in it,
then I've got 3 + 3 + 3 = 9
descendants, plus myself is 10.
That's a very obvious
structure for solving the problem.
I'm getting slightly
ahead of myself here.
It would be nice to say
"it has no descendants"
for the empty one.
because I can
avoid that problem.
I can just say:
You can see when
I press leader 'S' there
It's set up RSpec to
only run that line.
So now it's saying 'undefined method:
descendant_count for node'
and then I can easily
go in here and say:
So if I now do leader 'L'
to run my last focus test
It runs just that example.
I can make that
work quite easily here
I can't make it work
so easily down here.
because what does it
mean for the tree to have
five descendants.
This does go slightly counter to the
way I want to write tests
but I think in terms of
expediency it's going
to be quicker for me
to just make a real
tree here because
because I've already
written the tree helper
that knows how to do that.
And I've already
got some examples
from the Cucumber step.
I think that slightly
subverts the notion
of it being a unit
test, because
although I'm only
testing one method here,
I'll end up testing
it against multiple objects.
If I didn't have a time
limit, I would like to
spend some
time investigating
what would be the
consequences of me trying
to do all of this
with test doubles.
But my instinct tells me that
I might get a bit tied in knots.
So for this specific
example, I shall err on the
side of 'quickness' and have
a look at the tree steps here.
I already have a tree
here with 5 descendants
this wide tree.
So I can go here and
say something like this:
What do I want to do?
It's going to be
something like this:
Let's get rid of this.
That's going to give
me a node that really
does have five descendants.
DN: Yes.
And then this is going
to say check that it does.
If I already knew how my
descendant count was going to work
I'm in conflict about this ....
Let's just see what happens if I say:
I would like to get
my head around if this
is the right decision or not.
So, if I run this, firstly the
answer is going to be wrong.
It's going to say,
"expected five and I got none".
DN: Where is
children coming from there?
TS: Children is coming from here
It walks up until
it finds a place where
that has been defined.
So I'm still using this
as several test doubles.
I may decide to put ....
'let children'
inside here and then
it would provide...
DN: ...a locally scoped version?
TS: Yeah, exactly.
That's the wrong answer.
Expected five, got zero.
Now I can start thinking
about how I want this to work
well the most
obvious thing that I need is
to remember
what the children are.
And I guess this
could be something like:
Is that right? Oh well,
Yes .... No.... (laughter).
It's a little difficult
because this method needs to ....
We need to
subtract one from it,
only once,
right at the end.
So if we call it on the
root node of a tree,
it needs to walk
down through the tree
adding up how
many nodes there are.
And then we subtract one
from it right at the end.
DN: Yes.
It now occurs to
me that I'm not sure.
Oh, descendant count of
zero for the empty node
is correct because
there's just the root node.
Let's leave that as it was,
I don't think that's right.
So if it has got several children
in my head, the general
pattern that we want here
is to take all the children
and call descendant_count on them.
And when I know
how many descendants
all of the children have
I want to add one to that.
DN: Right.
The one whose
children you're asking about?
TS: The current node. Yes.
If I collect all the
descendant counts and add them up,
by using inject plus,
and then I have one
and that's kind of
the answer that I want.
Or at least that's the answer
I want in the recursive case.
I haven't been called
recursively as part of this procedure,
the root node, I need
to subtract one from it.
I need to think
more carefully about this.
Hopefully that will be
born out by the fact that
here we would want
all of these to return
that it has five descendants.
Right now it won't.
Because we've
got the wrong code.
Let's run that last test.
There's our first
problem, that because
all the children
are just test doubles
They've all just returned... .
At the moment I've
just got these three
dumb children.
So why don't I
set up a situation that looks like
the tree we had here.
Which was .... there
would be five of these
It would be
quicker to just say:
if I want five children .....
The easiest way to
do that is 5 x map.
Whatever is in this block
will get evaluated five times,
and put into an array.
I can use RSpec 3's
verifying doubles for this.
I can say 'instance double'.
I want to have a
double for an instance
of the node class.
And what this will do is,
if the node class is loaded
it will check whatever
stub methods I put on this
double actually
exist so it's checking that
I'm not stubbing out
methods that don't exist.
I want to stub
out descendant_count.
and I want that
to be .... new style
I can say the descendant count
of each of these,
needs to be one.
I can already see
that is not going to
give me the right answer.
Because it adds one, I get six.
DN: Just so I'm on the same page
as you here
you've created
five instance doubles,
each one is a node.
And it's reporting that
it has one descendant
but actually that
descendant is itself ....
ah yes, of course,
it's reporting to its parent.
TS: Yes, so this is
the problem, that ....
we've already said
that an empty node
should have no descendants.
That's returning zero.
But to even get this
started I'm having to say
that these nodes,
which I'm thinking
of being empty ones,
will have a
descendant count of one.
There's an impedance mismatch.
Effectively you've got
two different methods here
and we're trying to cram
them into the same place.
I'll get rid of this.
I need to fix this.
I already feel
confused by the test doubles.
given that they
weren't helping me
I'll get rid of them for now.
If I can use them later, I will.
This is going to
help me think through
how we want this to behave
because up here
we've got a real instance
of a node with no children
and it's giving
the right answer.
Now we've got a
real instance of node
and we want to
see what the answer is.
So now this is
saying we don't
have that build_tree helper.
So I need to require that.
I think it's up
in features support.
Trees helper.
And then I need
to include a module
in my RSpec file.
I don't have a great
way of having test helpers
that are available in both
RSpec and Cucumber features.
Usually because, when
I'm writing a unit test
I wouldn't want
these helpers that build
huge trees of real objects.
But .... that's
what we've got.
Why has that worked?
Expect descendant count to be five.
Ok, I've done the wrong thing.
expected five and got one,
and I think the
reason why we've got one
is because the subtrees
have all returned zero
DN: And then we've added one to it.
TS: Yes.
So I think that we
need to have one method
that we call from
the outside, which is
going to be descendant_count.
And a different method that is used ....
This code here is going
to be something else.
DN: I see.
And this thing here
can be 'something else'
minus one.
DN: OK.
Because when you
call this you want it
to count all the ....
what did we call them?
This is almost like .... 'node count'.
You want it to count all of
the nodes, including itself
and then disregard itself.
I think!
This may be stupid but
let's see what happens.
This I think, does
the correct thing.
So this needs to be one.
So what we are trying to
ask is how many nodes
in total are in the tree.
If I don't have any children
there's just the one, that's me.
and if I have some children
then I have all my
childrens' nodes and myself.
So I'm always adding
one, and at the end
you subtract one.
If I run my unit tests....
expected five, got zero.
That's not
what I was expecting.
Ah .... it's because I
forgot to change this.
So we have to call that
node_count method recursively
Now, it will correctly
count all of the nodes.
There are other ways
that we can arrange this,
but I think this is fine.
I think this is just as good.
It's slightly awkward that we have
these two ways of doing it.
But I think this is
sort of an inevitable
consequence of saying that
the root node is not ....
Actually ....
Maybe there is a
better way of doing this.
We can do a bit
of refactoring here
and make a commit
because I've definitely
done the work.
I've got
something that works now.
So I will just say:
I think there is a
smarter way of doing it
which is to always think about
the descendant count as being ....
How many nodes are
there apart from me.
For whatever reason, my intuitive idea of
what descendant count was doing
would be including the... It would
be like self AND descendant count
But that's not what you want
you want to know how
many children there are
and how many children
of children there are.
Not counting myself.
if I do this descendant count
Could I say,
'if I don't have any children
then there are
zero descendants".
If I do have some children
I then add up the
descendants each of them have
then I add how
many children I have.
So this would be:
And then I think that
does the same thing.
That's slightly nicer.
I hadn't thought
of that as being
a way of adding them
up but I think it works.
It's a problem
that you have to call
size on the
collection of children.
Whereas, previously
we didn't have to do that.
You got that for free,
because every child
was returning 'one',
If they included
themselves anyway ....
Now we have to
have an awareness
of how many
children we have.
I think that's why I avoided that.
DN; Well there's
only question to ask.
This is the best way of
representing what you wanted.
DN: Right.
TS: The examples
are passing the test.
I might stick one
more in here.
Given that we've got them.
I said I thought
this one had twelve.
So let's find out if it
does in fact, have twelve.
DN: It definitely has many.
TS: Yes.
So this one is going to be:
I was right, it
does have twelve!
Although I am
uncomfortable with the
use of the real
instances here,
I think I'm going to carry on
because for the purposes
of what we are doing here,
I don't think it
would be interesting
for me to fix that problem.
Now I've decided how this works
I could go back and instead
of having real instances here
I could just
have doubles, so that
here, I just need
three children that each
say they have four descendants.
So I don't need the
real instances here,
but I've already
'flip flopped' on that a bit
so I'm just going to
move on with my life.
I've only tested descendant
count three times there
but that's giving me confidence,
that it's not totally wrong.
All of these trees are
pretty much symmetric.
All of the children look
the same in each tree.
This one has got three children
which are all four deep.
I think I'm
confident enough that
that's not a problem,
so I'm going to carry on.
Let's run the
Cucumber features and see
where we are.
Undefined method
descendants count for node.
Why has that happened?
Because it's
descendant count.
I think descendant
count is the name
I want that
method to have.
When I was writing
the acceptance test
I did write
descendants count.
DN: That's an easy
refactoring to change.
TS: The reason there
was descendants there
was because I'd
written descendants here.
We've got the word
descendants all over the place.
But this feels more
idiomatically Ruby to me,
that's just my instinct.
Let's run them.
DN: The pending
one is the one we
don't care about
the moment isn't it?
TS: Yes, sure.
I'm going to add
this change and
just say:
I think we can power
through the rest of it now.
So now we say
the collection should
be ordered by the
total number of descendants.
That means we are going to
start putting some code in here
which says:
So if we've sorted
them by descendant count
we expect to
see just one node
which has no descendants.
A deep tree which has four.
A wide tree which has five.
and deep wide
tree which has twelve.
So let's run that.
I got that green before but I didn't deserve it.
In fact because
I didn't deserve it
I'll put pending in here.
So, I think we finished that.
I'll just go back here and ....
un-comment  that
and now we've got ....
sort the collection
by terminals is failing.
Ok, so I'm hoping we can
pick up the pace a bit now.
What situation are we in?
Undefined method
terminal count
I can start writing
specs around that.
For the moment
I don't have any.
So if we've only
got a single node.
It has no terminals.
It's complaining
about undefined method.
I've done with that.
If we just have
that return zero,
at least that
example will pass
and that's not
broken anything.
Now we have to do
something more difficult.
Which is:
How does this work ....
This is the flat tree.
That's going
to work as well.
DN: With no extra work.
TS: Yes that's great, and
we can just stop there!
This is going to
be more challenging.
It has three
terminals, is that right?
DN: Yes.
We're expecting the
node terminal count.
to be equal to three.
Let's run this one.
Expected three, got zero.
What do I want to do here?
I'm counting how
many leaves there are.
But I only want the leaves that
are at the maximum depth.
DN: That's right, yes.
TS: That gives me the idea
of having another method,
that can be
called leaf_count,
that takes a
depth argument.
We're going to have some
kind of maximum depth.
I think it would
be easier for me if
I thought of depth in the
way that I talked about it.
Let's go with
your method definition.
We just have
to make it work.
If we want to refactor
it then we can do so.
DN: I'm being
an awkward client.
TS: Yes this
is very realistic.
DN: Use my language!
TS: So in that case,
terminal count will just be
count all of the leaves
that are at depth MAX_DEPTH.
This just gives me an 'in' because
terminal count is one of those things
that we're not going
to be able to call recursively
we're not going to be able
to say on the child nodes:
"Tell me how many
terminal nodes are inside you".
Because the child
doesn't know where
it is in the tree.
It doesn't have
a link to its parent.
It just contains children.
The reason I'm
doing this is because
I can define
leaf count recursively.
If we don't have
any children then ....
If the depth
argument is 1
The root node
is at depth one
In your numbering system.
so the root is at depth one
and a child is at depth two
and another child is at
depth three, four and five.
DN: Yes.
If you are at depth one,
and you're a
leaf then you are
what we are looking for.
DN: Yes.
So you say count
how many leaves there are
and if you are already a leaf,
and we're looking for things
that are at depth one,
then return one.
Because that's
what you are yourself.
Otherwise, for
leaves at some other
depth return zero.
And in the recursive case,
I think we want to
do something similar.
We want to say:
This is going to
be more complicated.
As we recursively walk down,
we say now I
am looking for things
at one level lower.
So the root node is
looking for leaves at depth five.
But when it asks all
of its children it says
"do you guys have any leaf
descendants at depth four
because if you do that's
depth five with respect to me".
So we get all of
the child leaf counts
and add them up.
Let's try running that last test.
That passes.
If I run all the tests.
Got a failure:
"Double received unexpected
message: leaf_count"
This is the sort of
thing I was talking about.
The fact that there's
a failure there is fine.
Because it's what guides
me to stubbing methods out
of my test doubles and
then gives me feedback
on what the API of
those objects should be.
However in this
case those instances
are all objects of
the same class as me.
I think it
would be quicker
to make these
instances of node.
What was actually
the source of that?
This is line 38
Expect no new children.
I'm asking for
the terminal count.
And now I realise what
I should  have been doing.
This should have
just been node.
I already tried not
to use these test doubles
in places where I
was calling real methods.
They were for the purpose of
creating the [inaudible].
So all of those
tests are passing.
I feel moderately
confident that that is correct.
In which case, let's go
back to the Cucumber feature,
to see if we've done enough
work in the unit test
to make the
acceptance test pass.
We just haven't
implemented this yet.
Perhaps we should
have done that first.
What order do we
want these to be in?
DN: Is it sorting from small
to large at the moment?
TS: Yes.
DN: So it's not
much different.
It will be just
one node, wide tree.
Is that right?
TS: I think so yes.
DN: Deep tree
then deep wide tree.
TS: Yes.
TS: Oh dear...
This is very difficult to read.
My immediate
suspicion here is
that it is to
do with the sort
not being stable,
as I mentioned.
I can't read this
output and see
what the difference is.
My intuition is that
when you sort by terminal count
It's also fine for them
to be the other way round.
If we wanted them
to stay in the same order
in the array, we
can't use Ruby's sort_by.
Well we can, but
not out of the box.
We have to find
a way to preserve
the original
order of the list.
So that we can
associate all of the elements in
the list with
their original position
and then sort
by a compound key.
Firstly sort by how
many terminals they've got
and then by what
their original position in the
list was so
that is preserved.
DN: It's more likely
that I would be ordering
them by quantity, those
with the greatest number
and things that
have no terminals
is of no interest to me.
They are the
ones I want to ignore.
You could even throw away
the ones with zero terminals.
The use I would
have for this tree structure
it is not interesting to me.
TS: I will see if I can get
the existing test passing happily.
Then we can refine the
requirements if we want to.
It's been too long
since I committed.
So let's say:
I should have made
this change first incidentally,
I just lost track of
what we were doing.
Before I started
dropping down to RSpec,
I should have
allowed myself to see this fail,
and it would have
indicated that I needed to
go down and
write some unit tests.
I will say:
And then what
have I done here?
This is:
That's slightly frustrating.
The best I can do here
is to express our intent.
I can say:
That will verify
that this collection here
is exactly two long, and
has those two things in it
and we don't really
care about the order.
Because we do
care about the order
of the rest of it.
I can say:
This is a little
bit clumsy but it is
at least
expressing what we want.
DN: Yes.
You are saying
you don't care
what order they come in,
so we will use a
'matcher' to check they are
in the order we want.
Whereas we do
want the rest of it
to look exactly like that.
So, there we go.
DN: Very nice.
TS: We've got
everything passing.
I want to go back
and look at this.
We have definitely
done this bit ....
given a collection
of trees let me
sort by these properties.
This max-depth of
5 is implicit in the
definition of a terminal,
but we
haven't enforced it.
You haven't said, when
instantiating these trees,
enforce that it
isn't deeper than five.
But there is an implication.
And you've also
said the total should be
correct after adding
or removing nodes.
So there are
two things there.
What is most interesting
to me is the latter statement.
Although the enforcement of the
maximum depth is interesting.
Let's think
about the other one
and go back to that later.
DN: That is more
driving the API isn't it?
TS: I think so yes.
If only because, at
the moment we haven't
looked at what it
means to modify these trees.
At the moment it if
you look at our node class
you can't even get the children,
much less set them.
We haven't in
any way addressed
what it means to be able to
mutate these things.
That's an interesting
thing to think about.
I'm not sure how
to address that.
Let me make a
commit before I do anything.
So this is:
This is more
difficult to accommodate
in a cucumber
feature, but I think
there's probably
a way of doing it.
This is implicitly a requirement?
DN: Yes.
TS: What this
implies is that firstly
you should be able
to add or remove a node.
and secondly, when
you do so it shouldn't
change what's
going on here.
You should be able to
change one of these trees,
and then if I order
the collection again,
it should change.
DN: Exactly.
TS: So that
necessitates some kind of
acceptance test
that tells us
what it is we want.
And then some
kind of implementation
that allows us to
mutate these trees.
Or add and
remove nodes from them.
I'm trying to think
of the easiest way
to test that.
Maybe we need
a new feature which is
adding and
removing and updating it.
It's still part of
the sorting feature.
Given that I have
a collection of trees,
when I add a node
to one of them and
I sort the
collection again
then it should
still be ordered by
total number
of descendants.
DN: I had imagined
you would be doing
some kind of caching.
At the moment
you're not doing anything
with caching, all
you are doing
is counting
up live objects.
If you were to
create another feature
maybe we could call it
'manipulating trees' or something.
It could justifiably not be
part of the sorted trees story.
TS: Ok.
What's the best
way to do that....
I think what we are
thinking about here
is coming up with
an API for being
able to modify these trees.
DN: Yes.
TS: Let's say there is
a modifying feature.
Let's say:
I'm not sure what
I want to say here.
But something like that.
You start out with
one of these things,
and then you change
it and get a new one.
We don't need that anymore.
I think I can keep
putting this stuff
in tree steps.
If I run these cucumber
features it's going to say
you don't have any of this.
Let's say:
It doesn't matter really.
I guess we just
need to think about
what it is that goes in.
Now I've built 'some' tree.
I've got one
pending scenario.
I need to put
something in here.
that involves
adding a node to the tree.
And then I want to do
something that checks it.
To someone using
this from the outside,
what does adding a
node to a tree mean?
I think the
simplest thing is to add
another child at the root.
I guess it could be
"I've got a node that is already a tree".
I could say:
It could be a node with no
children or something like this:
and then I want
to somehow add that
as a child of the tree.
DN: I don't think
it would be necessary
to compose trees like that.
You would only ever be
adding one node at a time.
For example, when you
leave a comment on a blog,
they sometimes have
a 'nest it' type thing.
Imagine each node is
something that one user has added.
TS: Ok.
Well in that case ....
That's just making an empty node.
So I can add that,
and then I have to
do something to
my tree to add it.
So it could be that there's
some kind of add_child.
You haven't said anything
about the ordering of nodes.
Your diagram
suggests that you might not
care about the ordering.
You haven't drawn this as a
top to bottom,
left to right tree.
You just say
there are nodes
emanating out
from the center.
You can clarify
whether or not you care
but for the purpose of
this, we're just going to
add a child on to
the end of this node.
And then when
we get to this step
there is something
that is going to check
that this node has
been added to the tree.
We can go ahead and
start writing unit tests here
but my personal
preference would be
for making
these trees immutable.
Having this
return a new tree.
I don't think this example
is going to illustrate this,
but making these
structures immutable makes it
a lot easier to keep track of
what can possibly happen.
If I want to
memoize the result of those
recursive calls
then I could just
memoize them and
then next time I call them
you just get the memoized result.
And if you change
the tree, that just
means you have a new one.
And if you had some
kind of structural sharing,
so that when you
add an extra child,
you get a new tree
back but all of the
previous children are
literally the same objects.
But the parent node is new
and has a new child
and all of the cached stuff
would be shared from
the old parts of the tree
that haven't changed.
And then you
would have to re-build
the cache for the
new parts of the tree.
Driving all of that
stuff out with tests
is going to
be time consuming.
In my view,
it's going to make
for an easier
system to deal with
without these
things being mutable.
What I don't want, in
my capacity as a consumer
of this API, is to be
able to only do tree.children.
Like do that:
If there was just
an accessor on tree that
returned an
array of children and
I concatenated
that on to the end.
The root node of that tree
doesn't even know it's happened.
Now you have that
array in your hand
and you can do
whatever you like to it.
I don't really like the idea
of exposing it directly.
For the same reason
I don't like the idea
of this being
something that mutates
the underlying tree.
I would rather
just return a new one.
Assuming there's a way to
append the child there,
Which there isn't.
a failure in our features.
When I scroll off
the top you can see:
when I add a node to it
undefined method append_child.
So let's make
a commit there.
I'd like to make that work.
I think this is an
opportunity to do some ....
tidying up at the
implementation level.
We've expressed
what we want to happen
in the feature
here but let's go
down to the unit test.
Let's pick one of these.
This is quite a
nice one, where the
node has five descendants.
In this unit test
we have to decide,
and in the acceptance test,
how do we know if
it's done the right thing.
I don't really know how
we are going to do that.
DN: You could check
the number of descendants.
TS: At the moment
that's the only visibility
we have on to the tree.
Let's think about doing that.
Let's say:
So whatever that's
worth, we would say:
(Let's make a new one).
And this would be
the descendant count
to be equal to six.
I think that would
give us some confidence
that the right
thing has happened.
That's the best we
can do at the moment,
based on the API
that's available to us.
Let's try running that example.
undefined method add_child.
Now we're going to
need a method here
that adds a child.
There's a very easy
thing we can do here.
Which is to say,
And that's enough
to make the test pass.
That's moderately
convincing I think.
I don't think that
spec would have passed
if that didn't work.
So I'll make a
commit there and
I'll say something like:
Whoops .....
That's a nice simple
implementation I think.
How did you feel about that?
DN: I like it.
TS: Let's go back
to the step definitions
and finish off,
because we're still not done.
That's made that step work.
And now we have to say:
Because that one was two.
DN: Just before
you move on,
I notice you used
append_child there,
but it's add_child
in the implementation.
TS: Thank you.
Well that's stupid
why didn't that fail?
Oh it did fail, I
just didn't read it.
Yes you're right,
append_child is a better name
DN: For the immutable nature of it?
TS: Because it tells you
where it's going to go.
DN: Right: 'Add child below me'.
TS: Yes, and the fact
that it goes on the end.
After the existing children.
At the moment you can't tell.
So yes, let's call it add_child
because at the
moment there's no way
of knowing where it's gone.
If at some point
we decide we're going to
be able to expose
the collection of children
and now we care
about where it comes
when you have it,
that would be the
point at which to make it.
But right now you
can't make that distinction.
Let's just commit that fix.
That looks annoying.
And this is:
That's fine.
We are ignoring
the fact that presumably
the whole point
of all of these trees is
that you can at some
point get to the nodes.
At the moment there's
no API for getting to them.
I would like to
bring that out a bit
by saying something like:
I think that to
not do that is to
slightly dodge the issue.
DN: Sure
TS: We don't have a
way of doing this yet.
DN: So at the moment
children is a private attribute.
TS: Well it's
an instance variable.
There is no children.
Not even a private
method called children.
so that's going to say
"I don't know
what you're talking about".
In the specification,
you didn't say explicitly,
but I think implicit
in all of this stuff is:
Where you say model a tree.
It is implied that
you want access
to the contents of the tree?
DN: Sure.
TS: So this gives us
a way in and verify
that the children of
the tree are inclusive.
I want to check this.
If it was an empty array,
then that should fail.
We expected that
to include that node.
If I just had an
array that had additional
node in there then I think
that my... Yeah!
That's to verify that my
rspec expectation is right.
Because I always
spell include or includes ....
or does it
have a question mark.
Every time I type include in Ruby,
I get it wrong.
So that has given
me confidence that my test
is testing the right thing.
Now, that
introduces a new requirement
which is how do
we get at the children
of the tree?
I guess that means we
need a test here that says ....
This would be a good place for it.
Or something like that.
It exposes that it's
possible to 'get at' the children:
I would say:
I can round trip
that collection of children
through the node.
There's some duplication here
but I'll leave  it.
All over here
we've got places where
we're making
node.new children.
There's a temptation
to have one of these
let things that says:
Here we could do it.
That says:
That means that
all of these places
where I've got
node.new children,
I can replace
that with just node.
And I think
that those tests will.... ,
Wow!
completely explode.
That's not what I wanted.
Oh, it's because
this is nonsense.
It should be:
I was reading the one above.
This is not
supposed to be a block.
This is an argument to expect.
That's the one failure I wanted.
That is not what I wanted.
What did I do here?
Oh this was:
here I wanted to add ....
(I've raced ahead
and done two things).
I just want to add that:
That is still not added
but all the rest of it which is:
That has
cleaned up my spec a bit.
And now I've
just got this new
example which is failing.
I'm not going
to spend time writing
examples around
this, but I don't want
to expose just
that children array.
I think that would be bad.
Because then you
would be able to modify it.
The simplest
thing I can do to
make the test pass is to say:
In fact I don't
even need to do that.
I can just say:
I think that will
make all of my tests pass,
and hopefully
when I run all my
cucumber features,
it will make them all pass.
So I will commit that and say:
But, I'm not really happy about it.
DN: Even though it's a reader,
you can take that
object and modify it.
TS: Exactly.  It doesn't
let you re-assign the
children collection, but
once you have an array
you can
remove everything from it
and re-populate it.
We could freeze the array.
We can make
an accessor here that says:
Can we freeze it here?
I think if we do
that, it will still work.
DN: Yes, right.
TS: Our cucumber
features will still work.
So that's one
way of dealing with it.
I think a more
interesting way would be ....
to expose an enumerator.
I think that would
feel more natural to me.
To say "if you want
to iterate over my children".
"Then you may do so".
If I just pop open irb:
"if I have an array".
There are a variety of
ways to make an enumerator out of that
you can call to_enum, or
you can just call each
and that also returns enumerator.
I think here I would
like to define an iterator.
So if we can
iterate over each child,
and I can provide a block.
Then I will call each
on the children for you.
And that's nice because ....
if I have some class,
If I call:
If I pass on the block argument like that.
And make a new one of these.
Then it will work.
If I don't pass in
a block, each will
behave as if I
haven't passed in a block,
which gives you
an iterator back.
This gives you the
same as doing 10.times.each:
Or I've just been
using 10.times and then
not passing it
a block, and then
calling something like
map on the end of it.
The reason that works
is because these methods
in the standard
library return an enumerator.
The opportunity to
return an enumerator here
is a nicer interface.
It's more constrained,
and gives you what you want.
And, you don't even
know that it's an array.
The enumerator
itself doesn't let you
reach inside it and say
"what kind of thing
are you iterating over"?
So that feels quite nice.
The problem is that that's
going to break all of our examples,
or just this one
that asks for the children.
DN: So we still don't
have a children method.
TS: No. We just have
a way of iterating
over all of the children.
So we need to
change our spec slightly.
So I can't call
children any more,
I can only call each_child.
Which gives me
an enumerator back.
If I want to
check all the things that
are yielded by that enumerator.
I could write some code that says:
I could pass this
a block and then say:
append_child if I
had already initialized one.
But fortunately
enumerators include the
enumerable module which already
has a method called that.
It's called entries.
So I can say "if I get
an enumeration of all
the children, and
turn that into an array
by accumulating all of them.
That should be the
same as the array of children".
What's that complaining about?
Node line 9.
Oh it's because I forgot
to refer to it
as an instance variable.
So that's all fine.
If I now run
my cucumber features.
I've got a
failure because that's
calling children as well.
This is all
about designing the API.
I've got an
opportunity to shape the API,
and those changes
to the API need to
propagate out of
the cucumber feature
because in the
world where the customer
is the person using
the API, we need to
make sure that all the
things they want to do
have been designed out.
And I think that
exposing an iterator,
although it's not as nice
as being able to call children.
In fact, we could
add a children method
that does each_child.entries
if we wanted to,
but this is nice.
It's low level
but it exposes the ....
This is like the essence
of the interface, is that
you can iterate
over all of the children.
I will commit that:
DN: If you did call each_child.entries
and the array that you get back
if you then changed
that, it wouldn't affect it.
TS: Right. Because that's your array
DN: It's a copy.
TS: The tree doesn't
even know that you
have called entries
on that enumerator.
You've just got one.
In fact, that reminds me.
In terms of
designing the API of
this thing or
doing some re-factoring.
You can see there
are a few places where
we want to
know if this is empty.
Here's the clearest point.
What we are asking here is
whether we are a leaf.
"Am I a leaf?"
That's what it really means.
If we're a leaf
do this otherwise
do this other thing.
We can have a method here.
Which is "are you a leaf"?
Because I've got access to it
I can just say children.empty?
But I'm nervous
about all of these places
where we're referring
to the instance variable.
I would much rather
have the instance variable
in as few places as possible.
Instead of all
these places where
I'm accessing the children
For example, in
this leaf method,
instead of saying
children.empty?, I could say:
So build me an
array, and then
tell me whether it's empty.
But there's an even
better way of doing that.
Enumerable has
a method called 'none?'.
So if I call each_child
to get the enumerator ....
I can say:
That is saying
"are there no children?".
In fact it will tell me if there
are any children that are nil or false,
but in this case,
none takes a block
and you can say
"are there no children that
satisfy this condition?"
If you don't provide the block, it says:
"are there no children that are truthy?",
which in our case is the
same as there being none.
If I run all of the unit
tests, that still works.
And all the
cucumber features still work.
That gives me
an opportunity to say:
And there are
several other places
where I could do this.
I'm only using
children here  to map
over something, which
each_child will do quite nicely.
And same here.
All I am doing with
this instance variable
using it to remember the
value that was passed
into the constructor,
and then I am
exposing a way of iterating over it.
So the only state
that is stored in here,
allows you to
expose it in iteration,
and some of the work is
done by doing that iteration.
So if I run all of my tests.
They're fine.
And the cucumber features are fine.
I can change this to:
The only frustrating thing is
because we did this children.size ....
When you create
an enumerator, it is
possible to tell it
how to find the size
of the underlying collection.
Some enumerators can.
It has always
got a size method,
but sometimes it returns nil if the
enumerator has been
created without providing
what the size of the
underlying enumeration is.
If I say each and
then ask that for its size.
In the case where
the underlying collection
that you've provided,
does report the size,
you can get the size back out.
I feel slightly nervous about that.
Oh! But, I've just remembered!
I think enumerable
has a method called count.
Which does
something like 'all' or 'none'.
You can give it a block
and it will tell you for
how many
items in the enumeration,
that block is true.
But I'm not sure
if this is going to work.
It does, good.
In all these cases
I have avoided building
an array of all the children.
Now that we
are only accessing that
children collection....
(we have got to do this).
Apart from that we
are only accessing that
children collection
through the iterator,
which means
that children can be
anything that's enumerable,
anything that
responds to each.
It doesn't have to be an array.
It could be some
sort of 'lazy collection',
which you haven't specified.
But designing it
this way means
we are gradually
reducing the surface area
of what we expect from children.
All we require
from children is that
we can call each
on it, to get an
enumerator back,
and the rest of the
functionality sits
on top of that single
assumption about what
we can do with  the children.
I'm not changing
the tests at all here.
I'm just getting a
chance to re-factor:
And then,
(this one is a bit tricky).
There are two ways of doing this.
I'll show you the stupid way.
Well, you don't need me
to show you stupid way.
It's just:
Run all the tests.
Run all the cucumbers.
That's fine.
DN: Yes.
TS: I think a better way is to build
an enumeration of the new children
by adapting the old enumeration.
I can say here:
An enumerator
works by providing an
object called a yielder to this
block that you
pass in the constructor.
and every time you call yielder.yield
It will yield that value.
Let's look at it on irb:
If I say:
First you can step through them
one at a time.
You can say give me the
next value, and the next .....
It's using fibers to suspend
execution of that block
after every yield
until I say I'm ready.
If I enumerate
off the end it says ....
I think I can re-wind.
Yes.
It's enumerable
so I can also say:
I can do:
It works like a
normal enumerable 'thing'
but you've
built it programmatically.
I can take
advantage of that by saying:
So yield all of the existing children
to the yielder,
and then afterwards,
Yield a new one.
I need to do
some variable re-names.
It's fine but
I think it's confusing.
So add a new child.
And then I'll say,
make a new enumerator.
It will not create an array.
This piece of code
will just spin over the
old children and yield them.
And then will
yield the new child.
Rather than
building a new array here.
I can pass in
my new enumeration
of the children.
And that works.
I think that's
an efficient way
of mutating these trees.
To think of the
children as being
enumerations of children.
If we had some
kind of 'insert before'
You could do a
thing here that says
"if child equals
the one I'm supposed
to be inserting before,
then yield the new one.
And after that
yield the existing one."
If it's 'insert after' you can
yield the old child
and then immediately
yield the new one.
Adding it on to the
end is the easiest
because we
know where it goes.
But enumerating
over the old collection
and inserting the new
one at the right time
allows us to ....
If we wanted to insert a copy of this
after every existing child.
We can say
"yield the old child
and then yield the new one",
each time around the loop.
We can do any modification
to the tree
that we want here.
But we're not
actually modifying anything.
This has the nice
structural sharing property
where this new
new node that we are getting
is re-using the
collection of children
that the old node had.
It isn't copying that
array and adding to it.
It's holding on to
it through each_child.
The new node has a
child enumerator that calls
each_child on the old node,
and when it's
finished enumerating all
of its children, it
yields the new one.
That feels close to optimal to me.
It's not super efficient because
when you are doing
things non-destructively,
you're expecting
the garbage collector
to do the work of cleaning
up all the old stuff for you.
But after the
garbage collector has run,
we're not going to be
using lots more memory.
If you want to
compose a lot of trees together,
which this API
allows you to do.
Every time you compose
a tree into a new one,
you are not taking a copy of it.
You are holding on
to a reference to it.
Which you would do
anyway if it was mutable
And every time you
make a change it's creating
just enough new stuff
and holding on to as
much of the old stuff as is
necessary to make use of it.
I feel good that we have
been able to do that there.
So I shall say:
How are we doing?
DN: I think that's a
good place to wrap up.
Thanks Tom, it's been very
interesting watching you work.
TS: Thanks for having me,
it has been really good fun.