Chapter 8: Adding a build system.
So... I think we should go back to the challenge.
Well we have this, but not the interface.
We don't have play and stop and
there's no way to modify the tempo,
unless we change [the code],
and that's not very dynamic!
DN: Right, change the code.
SP: Yes, and reload. No! That's not very funny.
So... I am lazy so I'm going to use a
component that renders all those buttons for you.
Because I just don't want to do this over and over.
I suppose it's good to be lazy as a programmer,
if you work to make sure you don't have to work again.
So I made a component and used it with npm.
I need to initialize this thing as an npm project, first.
So I'm going to npm init this thingy.
Because that way I'll have a package JSON.
Otherwise it stores the thing
in `node_packages` folder,
but it doesn't save the
dependencies to packages.json.
If I give you this repository and
I don't check in the node modules,
you're going to have a hard time
figuring out what dependencies I'm using.
So this is important.
So I will just... OK fine, then clapping.
No text no repo, clap.
[Silence]
You have to do it that way or it doesn't like it.
Yes, it's perfect.
In theory I should just press return, but I
like writing yes, it gives me confidence. [Laughter]
I'm not going to mess with
something I shouldn't be messing with.
So now I should be able to npm install things.
They are going to be saved
as dependencies in packages.json.
Otherwise if you say `npm install --save`,
it doesn't really save if there's no package.json.
And I'm not going to create this
thing from scratch because I can't remember.
[Silence]
I think it's 'transport' - I hope it is.
I don't know why they call it 'transport',
but in musical software it's always called that.
It's the buttons with play and stop, the bpm thingy.
I didn't want to be too
original so I just called it transport.
DN: Yes, OK. I haven't heard
that before but it makes sense.
SP: If you look up transport you will
find a lot of references to all the inaud,
especially MIDI creation software inaud transport.
I think it's so you can transport
yourself around the song. I'm not sure.
So this comes from this organization
that has more modules and things.
This is the one I'm using.
This is what it should look like, if you use example.
But the one that we are going to
use doesn't really have any themeing;
we can add whatever we want.
SP: This uses web components
to render, this is a web component.
Because web components are not really clear yet.
You need to install the component along with a
web component polyfill to make sure this can work.
DN: Right.
Maybe I should also document
this thing, because it's not obvious.
There is a nice polyfill that you
can install, which is called webcomponents-lite,
and it installs the minimum that
I need for this, which is: registerElement.
and I think a couple more things, but I
just need to be able to do registerElement,
because that's not enabled in Firefox yet.
It's available in Chrome, so if you
try things only in Chrome you don't notice.
But if you try in Firefox without the
DOM things enabled, you'll find errors.
So this is going to polyfill the thing.
So I've got all these things and to load them I need
to use require, and this is not standard JavaScript.
I could try to load these things from node modules,
but it doesn't really work with this component,
because it uses other modules you should require.
So what I should use is webpack or browserify,
or something that takes my main.js
that I've been using so far, and converts that
into something that takes all the requirements
and things and makes that just one bundle.
DN: Right.
SP: So this is when things get interesting.
I just used webpack last week and
that was the first time I've installed it.
It's pretty easy to use. I'm going to reuse it again.
It's kind of like browserify, but it's got watch
and things like that which are very convenient.
With browserify you need to install watchify
or something but webpack does everything for you.
They call it 'Batteries included'. I like to
play with different things and assess them.
People say that webpack also
generates smaller packages,
but I haven't really used it in a project enough
to compare. I like to experiment with things.
And because this is the first time
I've used webpack, I don't remember the syntax.
So I'm going to go to look at 'getting started'.
So you install it (this is not good
practice, they say you should install...)
So they recommend installing webpack minus g.
That's not a good idea, because I don't want everyone
who uses my computer to be able to use webpack.
So I'm going to do it a different way.
So they suggest that you use
webpack and then the entry.js,
which in my case is main.js,
and then it generates bundle.js
So what I'm going to do is
to call that from npm script.
Then it will call it from the
binary inside `node_modules`,
but it doesn't need to be installed
globally. So I will just run it from the package.
So here's package.json.
And then I can add a new script which
is called build, and this one will use webpack.
So we will tell it to take main.js
and output that to bundle.js for now.
And you run this with `npm run build`.
It adds this bin to the current
environment for that moment.
And then you don't need to have
it globally because this is in the path.
So you don't need to install
it globally and then it's way cleaner.
Because otherwise if I tell you to go and run
webpack, you need to know that you need to install it.
That's OK with webpack, but some other packages
have a different name from the package.
The binary they install is different.
I think Grunt is an example?
For Grunt you need to install grunt-cli. But how do I
know that I need to install grunt-cli?
DN: Right, so there's a lot of assumed knowledge there.
SP: So if you just keep it like that
and your project uses webpack: I don't care!
Because your project just deals with
whatever the name of the executable is
if you use package.json script.
So hopefully if this works it
should just run the thingy.
Yes, so it does build the thing.
But I don't think it's a good idea to just
output everything here, so it kind of grows.
So I'm going to make a directory for building things.
So I can build things here and
then tell it to output the thing to build.
I'll remove this one.
And then run the script again.
Not everything's is in the
same place so that's better.
I also think it's not very neat to have
everything here with the build and everything else,
so I'm going to move
everything to a source directory.
Otherwise it's too messy.
I think I need to move all the claps.
And package, I think, is not in the git thingy yet.
I need to move it to source. I have created that, OK.
A new package has to be here anyway.
I also need to ignore `node_modules` and build,
because I don't want those to be added to git.
Vim is complaining about everything not existing any more.
So I will create the .gitignore.
This is the issue when you start adding build
systems you have to move everything around,
unless you start from the beginning.
But I think it's a good idea to
prototype and not care about build systems,
because you get confused about webpack and
watch etc. And you won't get anything done.
So we'll ignore `node_modules`
and also the build directory.
Since we're on a mac, DS_Store
at some point will show up!
DN: Yes, sure.
SP: So now if I run git status it will just try
to add this, and not node_modules or anything.
DN: I guess you will have to re-write the
npm script as well, so that it looks inside source?
SP: Yes. This need to look into these.
and also because I haven't updated that...
And this is kind of gross but it's
just going to load from the build.
I can fix that later.
Just to make sure it works because if we have
a server later and it's starting on the build,
it can't access this thing so we want to
maybe copy this file there and just load bundle.
But step by step so it doesn't get too confusing here.
So if I run the build now and then open source index.
[Silence]
Did anything happen (laughter).
What is going on here?
So this is... Is it called inaud? I'm confused now.
So it takes inaud
[Silence]
So it's in build, it  has to go
up one level and then build.
And why didn't it...?
So because we are not using a local server it
cannot even detect that we are not using that.
If we were using a server it would
have said "I can't find that thing".
[They listen] Now it's working, OK good
OK, so we are building
everything again so I could maybe...
DN: Is that worth a commit?
SP: Almost. I want to make sure that I have a clean task.
DN: OK.
SP: And also make sure that this directory exists.
So there are two scripts that
people use...I think it's prebuild?
It will detect that it goes
before build and it will run those.
If I run build, it will run prebuild before.
(I don't know if this needs a hyphen).
OK, so it's called (prebuild) before.
So I can mkdirp - the build thingy.
That will make sure the directory exists.
And with this I want to delete the build
directory, so I don't leave any traces.
DN: Right. Is rimraf an alias?
SP: No it's two modules that I'm going to install.
SP: Because that way you can have
this whole build task inside package.json
without having to install a task runner like grunt
or gulp. I learned it recently and it's very useful.
If you running this in windows or something,
you don't need to worry about
using different types of delete and things.
DN: Nice, OK.
SP: So I will install both.
I think rimraf is made by
Isaac Schlueter, the guy from npm.
I'm not sure about mkdirp, but they are used
by people in npm so you can trust it I think.
Now... Yeah I changed this thing,
so I've got new dependencies here.
So if I run clean...
The build has gone, so I don't have rubbish down here.
I think now it's worth a commit.
This is a bit of maintenance
but I think it's important.
It's good to have a clean slate before you move on.
[Silence]