Chapter 6: Playing part 2 sequence.
So we've got this thing which
is, (sorry control-M)  looping.
But, we might want to have the second player playing.
Because right now it's incomplete!
So I'm going to mute this thing again.
And so looking at the challenge, it says
that it starts playing both at the same time.
After 4 times of repeating the stanza,
the second player shifts one note?
DN: Yes.
And then after four times of doing that
thing, the second player shifts another beat.
So I want to increase the stanza
number after every 4th repeat.
And I'm going to use the stanza
number every time I want to shift.
So I'm going to algorithmically
generate the score for the second player.
Instead of giving this player a different
score I will look at the score and shift that.
It's the second score but it's
determined based on the existing score.
Because maybe later, if we have time we
might want to change the score. inaud
That's why I'm not generating that from the
beginning, but basing it on the existing score.
I guess I can have something like stanzaLoopTime...
No, I don't like this variable here.
DN: I suppose it's almost like,
how many repetitions in a stanza.
SP: Yeah, stanzaReps. Like power lifters! [Laughter]
OK, so we also want to loop
4 times to hard code everything.
I don't know if I want to call it stanza loop.
numStanzaloops maybe, that sounds better.
DN: OK.
SP: I will say I want to loop this
thing 4 times, and every time it's 4,
I will just increase the reps and
then decide what way to play it.
Also, we can get rid of this play
sequence because we are reducing the thing.
Go away.  It's good to leave it clear inaud.
DN: Yes sure.
SP: So this is when we should repeat
the thing, so this is we need to increase.
We also could get rid of these console thingies.
What else... For example here,
but we will keep it for now.
We could use it to print the
number of reps that we've done.
I'll go to the top so I can see.
So stanzaReps.
We also want to know which
is the current stanza number.
We want to keep the number
of reps of the current one; maximum of 4.
But we also need to know which is the
current one so we can increase that after 4 beats.
DN: Sure.
SP: And also make sense inaud this,
So this is the current one.
This is the amount of time we repeat with the stanza.
And this is the maximum we repeat the stanza.
I think it's a good idea to have
variables ordered in a logical way.
So when we finish the sequence, we look but we also...
We increment the number
of repetitions of this stanza.
But if the stanza reps is the number
of loops, we should increase the current stanza...
Hopefully. [laughter]
So I will print current stanza here.
[Silence]
And maybe the reps as well so we can check it.
SP: So this is the current stanza and reps.
I don't usually use the word stanza.
DN: It's not flowing off your fingers.
SP: No, it's not.
In theory it should stop.
Something broke. I don't know.
inaud
[They listen to the clapping]
I'm not sending anything to
zero. So that's why it's going forever.
So it should increase that but it also should...
It's hard to think when this
thing is clapping in your face.
It should increase that but also go back to zero.
We need to inaud that because we're doing a new one.
OK let's try again.
[They listen again]
I think that makes more sense.
The first one doesn't load because
we are not inaud yet, but I think it's correct.
DN: It looked wrong at first there because... inaud
SP: Yes, we should show the thing on the
screen all the time, it would make more sense.
So I think I will do that once
we get the player playing.
[They listen] OK, this looks good.
Now I need the second player to play.
I need to commit this.
I keep checking this, I am only changing main.js.
This should be 'keep track of stanza and reps'.
And with that I can determine
what the second player should play.
So the ‘should play' is for the first player.
And we need to determine
if the second player has to play.
So I'm going to rename this
to shouldPlay1 and shouldPlay1,
and then I'll find out if the second one needs to play.
It's not very scalable when you have lots
of things to play but for this case it should be OK.
So this is going to be using
the number of the current stanza,
because every time we play
another 4 loops we want to shift.
And I'm going to calculate
the step separately, so it's clear.
So the current step is the current step,
plus the current stanza because that shifts 1.
But we don't want to go too
far because the sequence only has 12.
So if I'm in the last step and I'm
playing the second player, I'm going to be out.
so we have to look back and start from zero and
we can use the modulo operator for that.
Inaud,
Does that make sense?
DN: Yes that does make sense.
SP: So, for those at home that don't know...
(This we're not going to execute).
So if you have the modulo thingy. Suppose you
have 12, which is the number of steps we have.
So we model the values with 12,1 =1, 2=2 etc
And 12 should be zero, because it goes back to zero.
That way we never go out of the array.
Knowing how the modulo works is super
handy when you have a number of values
and you want to skip to the next.
If you do something videos++
modulo the length. And it works super quickly.
I like those kind of things, but it's not the best
practice because then you have to explain them.
Or you could say something like index++
No that is even worse it's
better to say ++ index % length.
It may be hard to understand, but sometimes
when I'm typing in a rush, I might use this thing.
It's not the best practice. But if you're doing
short things you might just want to use that.
Just to make sure... I will log it.
Ahhhh go back.
[Silence]
We can't really say because
it's showing the other one.
So let's show both at the same time.
DN: Ah... Right,OK.
SP: So right now they are the
same because we're still not looping.
But in the next block we
should see how they've shifted.
It seems to be working fine.
So now we know that that
one should be playing a different thing.
DN: We're in the third stanza, zero two.
SP: Yes, so there are two shifts. OK, that looks good.
So that's why sometimes logging is good.
You could debug this thing but the problem with
debugging is that you need to go step by step.
Whereas, if you can see the progression
like this, it's easier to see what's going on.
You don't need to say next next next,
because that would be really boring.
And also, this is not the same it's really slow-ish.
So yep, OK.
[Sole thinks]
We have the currentStep2,
we can determine the shouldPlay2.
So shouldPlay2 = sequence[currentStep2]
[Silence]
So if(shouldPlay2) and just
play the buffer. And clap sample.
And they are happening at the same time.
It's just that they are looking at
different points in the sequence.
But the the steps are still in step time.
Maybe if this was a proper score it
would all happen in quarters, I don't know.
Like different lengths and things like
that. This is a very simplified version.
So in theory this should play the things I want.
[They listen]
OK, let's try this.
I will look at this and see if there are more things.
So you have two  playing.
You can really see the difference now.
[They listen]
DN: Ah there we go. [The clapping speeds up]
It's really hard to tell who's playing isn't it?
SP: Yes, We still have the dynamics compressor
so things are not going to be super loud.
That's the issue with using the same sample
for both, so I think I will change the sample.
[They listen].
Yes, it's hard to say. I'm going to
change the sample and add another one.
So we can see the difference
because right now it's too hard to say.
DN: Yeah.
SP: I would say it's working, but who knows.
OK, so I will commit this and change to loading
to 2 samples instead of using one for both.
Otherwise I don't know what's going on.
DN: What we have here is a performance.
SP: A performance!
DN: Well, yes it is clapping music.
SP: But a very precise performance, all the
players sound exactly the same. And always in time.
DN: It's 'clapping music' by a robot.
SP: Yes, but it sounds like a machine as well, do do do do.
Also, in this case there is
no silence in the second rep.
And the reason is because the dynamics
compressor makes sure we are never saturating.
So if we didn't have it we would
notice louder things... But right now we can't.
Let's try a different sample to start with.
[Silence]
So 'make second player play'.