Chapter 13: Panning each player left or right.
SP: I did commit this thing.
And instead of reverting this thing, I'm going to
reuse this structure I created for the gains.
And instead of changing the volume,
I'm going to make sure that each panning node is on a
different side so each player is on a different side.
The playBuffer() function had the gainIndex and the gainValue.
I don't need the gainValue because
the panning is going to be set.
So I'm going to remove that.
So one of the notes will be on
the left or the right, or whatever it is.
We don't need this.
Instead of gain it should be panNode.
This I don't need.
The structure is pretty much the same.
I could maybe replace all.
DN: Is there still a gainNodes somewhere?
SP: Yes, some gains somewhere
but we know where they are.
This is going to play in the pan zero.
We don't care about the
values now because they are inaud.
This is a terrible function call
because it's clapSamples1,
plus some time and one number,
but you don't know what it is.
It's not the best practice but
you could elaborate on that later.
I don't like this, "magic
numbers" thing it's pretty terrible.
OK so we need to create
panNodes instead of gainNodes.
I think it's Panner actually.
Let me make sure.
There is also a StereoPannerNode, which is
the one we want because it's easier to set up.
So this StereoPannerNode just
goes left and right with the pan thingy.
Whereas the other one is 3D, and you
need to set up direction and the listener
and also specify the listener. So
this one is easier - just left and right.
So I want to create the StereoPanner... And nodes.
This is a habit with me.
DN: g... p...
SP: So I connect this thing here.
I also need to specify it's pan.
This is terrible.
So p pan value.
DN: Is this going to be something  between -1 and +1?
SP: Yes, -1 is full left, and plus one [full right]...
So how do I do inaud function of this.
I'm going to be super lazy
because we are running out of time.
I'm going to say v: allow here
if j is zero minus one plus one.
Because we are just going to write from zero to one.
Maybe we don't want it to be so specialized,
because this is extreme left and
extreme right, but we will see.
Sometimes you don't want
to do it so saturated because,
if you play it in places that have
proper speakers, some people won't listen to it
because they are in the wrong place.
But I think for us this should be OK.
So hopefully this should still work.
[They listen]
Yes, stereo.
DN: Can you tell?
SP: I can.
DN: Yes I can hear it now. From where
I'm sitting I'm just getting a wall of sound.
SP: Like the inaud from before but...
I'm trying to click on this to
stop it but it's hard to capture.
Anyway in theory you can see
where the property is, if you could stop it.
Now you can see the pan here.