Chapter 7: Using a different
clap sample for each player.
SP: I have another sample somewhere, like here.
You can see the difference.
This one which doesn't want to play again.
DN: Yeah, they sound completely different!
SP: They are different.  Maybe not the
best, but you want them to sound different.
So we just paste it in here, so we have two.
We want to load two and we want to
make sure both have loaded before we continue.
So here we enter the horrors
of synchronicity in JavaScript.
They created this thing called promises, so
you can enter sync without having zero callbacks.
If we didn't use promises we have to load the first
sample and then the second, and it's not very elegant.
So we are going to turn this into
a generic thing for loading the samples.
Giving them the URL and
then instead of just loading the thing,
we will make it give us a promise,
and then we will use the Promise.all() method.
That waits for everything to be loaded. So
it's a bit less hard-coded and a bit more generic.
So I'm going to change this
comment to "Loading samples generally".
So it will return a promise.
I will do this step by step.
So I can give a URL, and take
out the hard codedness of that.
So instead of opening clap zero
wave, I'm going to load the URL
And instead of just returning
this... I'll do it step by step.
And also we don't want this thing here either.
So if we load this sample, I want
it to have some call back or something,
so it can tell you this thing is done.
But I want to convert this into a
promise because it should be faster.
So I'm going to return a promise.
You tell the person there's a promise.
At some point something might happen.
The promise happens or it is
rejected, which is when something fails.
When you have a promise you can use
the then() method to say when you fulfill this,
promise me this thing then do it.
It's like the connect() method
but instead of for (web audio) nodes.
It's for things that might happen in the future.
You can connect as many
things as you want to the promise.
You can connect a number of events.
Inaud, or you could load more things.
For example you might want to load something
sequentially, instead of all at the same time.
But in this case we just do promise all.
I don't know how it schedules
things and I don't really care.
I just care about the things being done.
If you care about the order of execution
you might want to use a different library.
In this case I don't, so I will just make this thing.
The way you use promises is you wrap the
code that you want to execute with a function
that has two things, 'OK' and 'fail'.
I think this is not the correct method names,
but I like this thing because it's pretty obvious.
This is the 'OK' callback or the 'fail' callback.
So if you return this thing...
In this case, instead of triggering the
whole process of everything I'm going to...
(I'm not familiar with this keyboard)
When I'm loading I'm going
to call the OK with a response.
(I will need to decode the thing, but anyway...)
I will use this thing or use fail instead
of this. So I do need to use the decode thingy.
It can be just 'load sample', because I just
want to get a sample out of here at the end.
However you create it, or decode it,
I just want you to load and give me a sample.
So I'm going to make it inaud and then here.
There is a promised version of the inaud
ordinator but it doesn't work in Chrome yet.
So I'm still using the callback.
So it's pretty much the same.
This is a good case so I'm going to respond.
I'm going to fulfill the
promise, with decoded buffer.
And if there is an error, I'm
going to fail with the error.
That's why I like the OK and
fail because it's fairly obvious.
Not like an error callback...
It's too long...  Get on with it!
So I think with the promise version you
can just return OK with the result of this.
But that's not in chrome, unless I add
another poly filler and I don't want to do that.
I want to keep it simple and
this should be simple enough.
So if I call this function I'm just going to get
a promise, and it doesn't actually do anything.
I'm going to show you. I'm
going to try to load 'CLAP_07.WAV'
[Silence]
So if I do this...
The promise is pending. So nothing's happening.
But if I say Promise.all()
With an array of promises. In this case just one.
Or maybe not. Let's not go that far. If I say sample
promise then hopefully it will give me a sample.
[Silence]
Ta Ta !
I could do this thing, or I could
use promise all with... Err not that far.
This is not Ruby... So I need
to have parenthesis. [laughter].
We have some spaces.
So here I should have samples.
So it will make all the promises happen somehow.
I don't care how, I just want it to be done,
and then give me the samples in another array.
I should have another buffer which is the inaud before.
So I could do the two, or I could maybe just...
I could generate this but I don't
think it's worth starting that. [Laughter]
Sample2... I'm just going to be very lazy.
DN: Seems fine.
SP: If I had another one I could list
the samples to load in an array;
and map it so you have a map
of promises, and then you make them.
So inaud. (laughter).
So you could do all Promises.
Suppose its sample1 and sample2...
And you could map that to sample URL.
So you want to return promise and generate URL.
So this should give you a list of
promises that you then send to a promise.
DN: Right.
SP: I'm just going to put that promise here.
[Silence]
We need to complete this thing. [Laughter]
DN: I think you need to call the first one 1.
SP: Yes. So in theory that should
give me two samples, hopefully.
Yes, we have two samples, so now we can do this thing.
I could store these samples
in my global clap samples.
Instead of just clap sample as I was doing before, (inaud)
Instead of having clap
samples, I will make it an array.
So if I try to play when I have
everything loaded inaud a break or something.
We could start it here, but we want
to start when everything has been loaded.
So we can start here.
Now everything's done I'm going
to add other comments so it makes sense.
Everything's  loaded.
So in theory that should do it.
We need to change the function that plays samples
so it uses different samples for each player.
(We can delete this).
So this function now is loading the sample
and decoding it. It doesn't have any other logic.
it just gives you a response for
the sample and that's the promise.
So it's really re-factored nicely.
So this is loaded and then we just
need to make sure this one plays different things.
But we know where they are. One is zero.
This is not very good practice but as long
as you know what your doing... [laughter]
So instead of just playing the clap
sample; play one and play the other one.
It maybe should be less hard code. Especially when
you have many things happening at the same time.
You want to use arrays instead of variables. But I
think for the time being, and simplicity, it's better.
Because otherwise the
syntax has too many brackets.
See just here; it's an ugly array.
So I'm going to try this, see if it works.
[They listen]
See? It's slightly different.
DN: Yeah.
Too perfect, but they are playing.
They can get you tapping your foot.
DN: Yeah. That's completely transformed
it, just by adding that other sample.
It sounds much less mechanical. Or less
monotonous I should say, but still mechanical.
SP: Less robotical.
At least you can differentiate. Otherwise
it was like "I don't know what's going on".
OK, so we've got this thing.
Now we can make another commit.
And now I need to add more files.
[Silence]