Chapter 5: Playing part 1 sequence on a loop.
SP: Right now there is no way to loop.
DN: Right.
We just play 1 player.
And there is also no way to adjust the tempo.
And also there is no way to stop it. Once it starts
playing I can't stop it and I can't continue.
So we need to change this and
do a different way of scheduling.
We need to do a proper way of scheduling,
because I could go on following your challenge,
With this sequence I have in my array, I could build
something which generates this narrow variation.
And also load another sample so the other
player is playing the same thing at the same time.
But the issue with that (and same thing here), is that
I'm scheduling the whole thing from the beginning.
Then once it's playing there's no way to stop it.
And then I won't be doing the things that
you ask me for which is playing it, stopping it,
and changing the tempo etc.
Right now this will be pretty boring.
One of the best things with web
audio is that you can interact with it.
It's very playful, and generates things dynamically.
And what we're doing is not very dynamic.
As I said, web audio is running a
different clock so you could try and do a timeout.
But that's not a good idea because timeouts are
very erratic and they depend on a lot of things.
It is recommended to have a timeout that
periodically checks if it needs to schedule things.
But that's not a good idea because timeouts are
very erratic and they depend on a lot of things.
It is recommended to have a timeout that
periodically checks if it needs to schedule things.
So a way to explain that would be... We
are going to keep track of which step we are in.
And we know how long each step takes, so timeout is
going to be checking if it needs to schedule things.
Every time we've finished with
a function we give it a new timeout.
So it's not a timer, it's a timeout.
So we are going to keep track of which
position we are in in the steps in the sequence.
So every time the timeout is going to
run it's going to say "Which step are we in?",
and see if it needs to trigger
things or schedule things to be triggered.
The reason it's a timeout
and not just a timer is because
a timer is going to be trying to
call all the time as fast as possible.
But with timeout, if for
example you drift a little bit,
the next time you called you will try
to make up for whatever you missed.
DN: If I understand correctly, the way
we've done it so far is to define one bar of music,
and we've defined it all up front. And then we just
set it running and it plays and we can't stop it.
But with this it's almost like we're saying...
SP: We're going to be reading the score.
DN: We're going to be reading
the score like a musician does.
And at each point in time
we're scheduling the next beat.
SP: Exactly. And like a conductor saying
"slow down" because we changed the tempo,
we're still reading the score but take longer.
SP: And if someone says pause, just pause for
a moment, instead of "Oh, I can't pause now".
DN: OK.
SP: So I will just describe a step or
something and stop at 0. Which is where I am.
So I want to introduce a couple of functions,
one for starting and one for stopping,
and another for trying the timeout.
SP: We won't call this playSequence,
but I'll delete that thing later.
And I can delete this thing also.
I like to have some spaces here as well.
And for some reason I
have these little curly things.
SP: So I've got start and I've got stop.
I like to write this skeleton so
I know I need to fill things later.
It's what I always do. And at
the end of this I will call this again.
DN: I see.
SP: I will use this so I can
cancel this on stop... Is it clearTimeout?
Because obviously cancel was
not a good name. [Laughter]
So I build this thing.
So that's more or less what we want to do.
That's why I think it's a
good idea to have the skeleton;
so you can say I want to
start and stop. And that's the crux.
Obviously we want to have more things in schedule().
SP: Not just like start or stop timeout.
I also need to create the timeout as well.
[Silence]
It's nothing right now. It's good
to be clear about your intentions.
So when I start this thing I'll
save the time at which this started?
Let me think.
That way I know when I pause
the thing, I can calculate the steps.
This is a bit weird, and it
takes a long time to understand,
but you will understand why I schedule this thing.
DN: OK.
SP: So you have the sequence, but you
can't pause or play,  or change the tempo,
You're just scheduling everything in
advance and that's not the way it should be.
And it's not really playful. So
what we should use is 2 clocks.
There's this brilliant tutorial called 'A tale of
the two clocks'. And if you look will find that.
So essentially what were going to have is
this timeout function; this scheduling function.
It's going to be like the player looking at
the score saying "What do I need to do now"?
It's fast enough but not exactly
like what a player would do. Inaud.
So the way we do this thing is with this
timeout that I'm going to be setting all the time.
It's kind of complex to build
this thing from the ground up,
and I always forget something,
so I've prepared a skeleton.
It's a simplified version of the tutorial.
Because the tutorial also deals with having
swings, so you can smooth out the tempo at every step.
But I think that's too complex for this,
and also "Clapping Music" doesn't have swing changes!
DN: No.
SP: So I feel it's best to have
a simplified version here.
So this skeleton has a start function,
a stop function so we can clear the timeout,
and a schedule function, which
determines how long each beat is.
Like 60 seconds slash the bpm,
gives us the number of seconds per beat.
And we want each step to be a quarter of a note.
Like a black note, so that's the length of the step.
And we want the schedule
function running every time we can.
Every time it runs it will look at the
current time in context, minus the start time.
Which is what we said when we started.
So if you have the sequence it can
try to make things relative to the steps.
And not to whatever time the whole thing started.
DN: Yes, right.
SP: So the step time starts at zero, so if you start at
zero and this thing is related to the serial thingy,
it's easy to say "Am I still in this step,
or do I need to jump to the next one"?
Or, "Should I just stop
because it's not time to play it yet?"
So that's what we are doing here.
So with the step time and the start
time, you can say if something has to happen,
it has to happen at step time, using the sequence.
But when you scale something you scale in the context playtime, which is the web audio clock. So you have this sequence which is totally atemporal, so to speak, so we are going to be looping over the sequence all the time.
But when you schedule things you do it with the context because we will be playing and stopping things several times during the lifetime of the website, so that the clock of the context keeps growing, but the sequences are still zero one.  Supposing its one step, one second, zero one two three four. At some point the context might be like – thousands of seconds, so that's why you need to remove or...
how do you say, when you add something you sum it, but when you remove something you...?
DN: Get the difference? Or subtract?
SP: You subtract! That's the word.
So that's why you want to subtract this start time, so it becomes relative again.
So just go to the next step and if it's more than the number of steps we are looping so you go back to zero again. And then you have step length and you want to scale it again.
DN: And it calls itself.
it has to happen at step time, using the sequence.