[Chapter 2: Playing a clap sample]
SP: So this is just an empty
directory: there's nothing here.
I'll start by creating an HTML file,
so we can start doing things.
And I'll just use Vim. [Laughter]
And I can configure that the way I like.
I don't like decorum when I make things.
So the reason I comment something like inaud is because inaud the labels. Everyone says what kind of course is that why inaud.
and [Silence as Sole types]
So this is just inaud.
[Silence]
I think I learned this trick from you, how to solve inaud.
DN: Is that utf-8?
No, this is me typing quickly. I think you can use both.
inaud the parser knows.
Right now I don't need to have anything
but I suppose I should put something for it.
Close everything. Inaud.
So if I open this thing – there's nothing here,
just this thing, nothings happening either.
To start with it's just the plain clap.
You can see how I start assembling the whole inaud.
So back to this thing.
I need something that loads, or does
the thing, so I'm going to load a script which...
This is not the best place to
put it but I will start with this.
And obviously we need to write the file.
I like to be at least, a little correct. inaud here
So the code at least waits for loading.