Welcome to Peer to Peer
where you can hone your skills
by watching live coding videos.
Our guest today is Soledad Penades,
who is a developer evangelist at Mozilla.
She works on the web platform
and developer tools for Firefox.
And she loves to experiment
with Web Audio and Web GL.
I'm your host, Drew Neil, and the challenge
that I set for Sole is called "Clapping Music".
Chapter 1: The challenge.
DN: OK Sole, do you want
to start by reading the challenge?
SP: Yeah! I'll try to, I'll do my best!
Ok, so the challenge is: Create a system that
performs Steve Reich's composition "Clapping Music".
"Clapping Music" has two parts that
are based on the same rhythmic cell.
Part 1 plays this rhythmic cell
consistently throughout the piece.
(x means play a sound, _ means rest).
So it's like tatata tata ta tata
Part 2 begins by playing this cell
then cycles through 11 variations,
each of which is shifted by one beat.
The system should have some user
interface to play and stop the music,
as well as providing a way of modifying the tempo.
DN: On this page we've got
a representation of the score.
SP:  Exactly. [Laughter as Sole considers
how difficult it is to represent the sounds by voice]
SP: OK, so its tatata tata ta tata, so
on the first line both players are playing in sync
And on the next repeat the first
player is playing the same thing
and the second player would shift one step?
Or it's like he's one step behind or ahead.
DN: Yeah... [thoughtfully].
SP: Actually it's one step ahead, so we
want to add one step to the thingy.
SP: It keeps shifting and then at the end
they are playing the same thing again.
DN: Yes, that's right. It's a very simple
idea but it's surprisingly engaging.
The music that comes out of it is interesting:
the noises it makes are quite exciting to listen to.
SP: Yes, and all those videos on YouTube
are really interesting. [Laughter]
I think it can serve to show a number of
techniques because this is very in sync.
And if things drift it's very noticeable. So with
normal audio tags it's going to drift at some point,
because you repeat the same thing all the time.
So for example, you think things are not working.
I would say you can generate lots of elements,
so it would get memory leaks at some point.
Or the garbage collector being like: "WOW
this is a lot of things for me to worry about!"
So if you do it with web audio it should
be in sync. If you do badly it could be messy.
DN: Yes, so you mentioned web audio; that's the
technology you'd use to solve this challenge?
SP: Yes. I don't think you can do it
correctly without web audio in this case.
DN: And that means it would run inside the browser.
SP: Yes, it will work in any Browser.
I will go through details later but it should
in theory, work in any modern browser.
Even in mobiles and tablets, so it's really cool
because you can have this running everywhere.
Friends can play with it everywhere [Laughter].
DN: Nice.