Chapter 3: Adding a limiter.
This is OK, but sometimes you want
to make sure things don't get too noisy
because maybe this sample is super
super saturated. You don't want to deafening.
So it's a good idea to insertn
a limiter, in the meantime.
So instead of connecting the sample
to the destination, you connect it to the limiter.
So you don't maximize all the sounds.
DN: So you don't blow up your speakers.
SP: Exactly!
So I will create this thing up
here... Very much a inaud name.
And I will create another node
which I think is called 'compressor'...
DynamicsCompressor.
So instead of connecting to the
destination, I will connect to the limiter.
And then I  will connect the limiter to
the destination.  So we create this whole chain.
And this is always connected,
so we don't need to do this all the time.
So I will connect this into the limiter.
and it should still play. [We hear a clap]
DN: OK.
Its not the format inaud. This is the base here.
DN: So we're seeing the graph?
SP: Yes, but we don't see the buffer store
because it's just died and it's been deleted.
DN: I see.
SP: You see now everything has gone
because we're not using it anymore.
DN: The garbage collector is
doing his thing [laughter].
So you saw that very briefly.
DN: A flash of a second.
SP: Well we have more things running.
We will see more things showing up.
and it's interesting to see that things don't stay.
So that's inaud.
So when you want to describe things, or when things inaud too long.
Inaud.
Hmm... Maybe I should check that everything's correct.
So when you want to describe things, or when things inaud too long.
DN: I see.
SP: So it's good to keep an eye on these.  If something inaud correctly. We want to make sure things are really disposed of.
DN: Yes.
SP: So we've got this thing but it's just like a clap and we want to play the sequence.
So when you want to describe things, or when things inaud too long.