Chapter 10: Adding a tempo control.
Now I need to add the
listener for the for the bpm event.
And this one is slightly different because
I need to read the data from the event.
It's not just like an action I need
to read the data from the event.
It's using custom events, I don't know who designed
this thing but you can't just put properties.
You have to use details. I guess
it's so you don't create properties.
With the object inaud future
properties in the spec or the events in general.
So you can only access them through the detail.
In this case the value that
you get is value [Laughter].
So if you have a bpm event
this is a new value you will get.
I will log it and you can see.
The new values are inaud.
[They listen]
SP: I can change that.
There's lot of changes so OK. Inaud
You just need to change the new bpm.
The score is being changed all the time.
The events are calculated based on the current
bpm every time the schedule function is run.
It will take the value that we send it,
and we can change that on the fly.
The only issue with this is
that this might be sent as a string?
Because it's coerced. I always
make sure to multiply by one.
DN: Ah right.
SP: Especially if you try to add things because it
might end up concatenating strings with numbers.
So in case of that, I just multiply the thingy.
And we have a global variable somewhere here.
So we can just say the bpm is this new value.
And hopefully that should change.
[They listen]
[The music starts slowly and gets faster]
SP: So now it's going really fast.
DN: How fast will it go.
SP: I think it's limited to 300.
Because, I do some happy hardcore
things. I think It's from 300 to 1.
DN: Yes.
This is really slow, it's one beat per minute.
I guess we can also add this thing.
I never remember what I changed.
In a more complex project I would use source tree so
I can see the whole thing but for this it's fine to use....
[Silence]
I think this meets the challenge...
Because you can play and stop the music
and have a way of modifying the tempo.