Chapter 9: Add play and pause buttons.
SP: Now we have this thing we can
start adding the web components;
this is why we wanted to add the build system,
not just for the sake of having a build system.
DN: Right.
SP: So here... I want to load the web components.
This will make sure that the
polyfill and everything is loaded.
But this is maybe better outside here.
So [webpack] just puts the code in there.
[Sole thinks]
I also want to load my component.
And I need to register it as well,
because there are two parts to using
web components with custom elements.
You need to load the prototype, and then register;
which is making it available to the parser.
So here you can use 'openmusic-transport' or you
can use 'mega-component', or whatever you want.
I've made that in a way that you
can register it any way that you want,
for example you may want to
put different versions of the component.
And the parser can only cope with one name.
So if you try to register something
that already exists it won't let you.
I don't know if that's the best
solution but it works for me.
DN: So is that going to be the name
of the tag you're going to use in the DOM.
SP: This lets the browser know that
there is a new tag that it can use.
So if it finds openmusic-transport in the
index.html we will be able to include the thing.
Hopefully... I hope this works.
[Sole types]
OK the completion is good.
And then here is my parser saying,
I don't know what you're doing.
This is the problem with using web
components, nothing knows what you are using.
But I guess you just have to cope with it.
And the problem is I need to watch.
I need to rebuild this thing now.
So I need to run build etc.
So were going to use the webpack
watch version thingy. Watch mode.
[inaud]
[Silence]
It's pretty much the same but with extra arguments.
So with browserify, it's so modular that
it doesn't even have the watch function itself.
You need to install watchify,
which then calls browserify.
That's the cool thing with webpack,
I still haven't explored all the
advantages but so far this is neat enough.
I guess i if you don't want special things because,
with browserify you also have browserify
transforms; I don't know if webpack supports those.
These are the things I have learned so far.
So if I run watch now it should
compile the thing and then keep watching.
So if I change something here
and save... There is no difference.
[Silence]
Yes, created something now because it's different.
I think if there is no change
it doesn't rewrite things.
So that's cool when you're saving out of habit.
So if I go to... I've got my
component here.[clapping plays].
Ah OK it doesn't have anything
and it's not connected to anything.
I can press these and nothing happens.
DN: That's interesting already.
Pressing play disables the stop button.
SP: Yes that's functionality from my
component because I really hate writing UI.
So if I write it once and it works
I want to use it as much as I can.
So detecting this is not super hard but if you
can stop having to do that all the time it's better.
So it emits events, and you
can listen to those events.
If you just press play it will
give you a play event, or stop.
Or, if you change the bpm, so you can access that thing.
I need to listen to it and do things
accordingly. So I'm going to connect both things.
The issue with this component so far is
that there's no way for me to tell it to start playing.
Or to display the playing state.
So my hack is to find the button and click. Like, trigger the click event. But this is not the best way, I want to find some way of specifying whats the current status declaratively. Like, in the mark up, say: this should be already playing. Instead of me clicking the button.
DN: Something like an autoplay attribute?
SP: No no no, right now if you look at the markup it just has the transport, I would like to be able to say something like: status="playing". And if I specify this, the play button should be disabled and the stop button enabled.  But right now you can't do this.
So I'm going to do a kind of hack where I will add a listener to play and stop, and then I will immediately click play so it starts playing. Instead of me starting the play() function and changing the status of the button.  I'm going to attach listeners, and then click, click! Programmatically click play as if I was the user.
That's how it works so far. It's a hack, but in the theory in future I should be able to specify it differently.  So I'm going to use that trick.
I need to find the element.
The cool thing about using web components as custom elements is that they are just DOM elements.
So you can just use getElementById, or querySelector, or, you don't need to use whatever.
For example, if you use React, it's wrapped in whatever React is using.
So you can't access the DOM elements that easily because it wraps them up in a precious way.
But with web components or polymer, you just use the elements.
In this case I'm going to use querySelector.
Close this thing...