Chapter 11: Humanize the performance.
SP: We have a thing which
I think fulfills the challenge.
DN: Yeah.
Part one is playing this thingy,
part two is playing the variations.
And we have a user interface to
play and stop the music, and modify the tempo.
That all works so the
challenge should be fulfilled.
DN: Yes sure.
SP: The issue with this is, it sounds super robotic!
Normally when you play an instrument
and you are a human, you make some errors.
So I think we should make, every
note triggered slightly out of time.
So we'll add some randomness.
I would start with doing that so it sounds a
bit more natural. Because right now it's too perfect.
DN: Yes, I've seen sequencing programs where they
call it a 'humanize' function, it adds some jitter.
SP: Yes, well we can just change the start time
slightly. Not by a whole beat, but more subtly.
I will make it a little less
perfect until it sounds a bit better.
So for the last time, this
is too perfect [They listen].
DN: Yes.
SP: We can make it a bit more ‘amusing'.
We know when things are starting which is...
So this is the contextPlayTime. Instead of
using that we might get some randomness here.
Like, a little ‘indecisiveness' of the players.
So I will say getSomeRandom()
I'm going to make this function that
will return positive and negative values.
It could be that when you are playing,
sometimes you anticipate a bit.
Players are not perfect, they're not totally
in sync so it's OK to have some randomness here.
[Silence]
So we just make the function here.
So what do we return?
We can start with some randomness and
then adjust depending on what we see.
0.5 second is a lot, but so we can see the difference.
[Silence]
You can call the random() function but
this returns [a value] between 0.0 and 1.0.
So if I multiply that with 0.5 it's going to be just 0.0 to 0.5.
So that means it's always going to be a bit later.
I want some to be a bit earlier.
So if I have `0.5 - Math.random()` this
is going to be in -0.5 to 0.5 ... I think.
[Sole thinks]
Or, one minus this might be from zero to...
So this can be negative or positive...
I don't know now. [laughter]
DN: Wouldn't that mean the
maximum value would be zero?
SP: Yes. So I want this thing.
So if it's zero it's 0.5? Or maybe...
OK, I'm just going to leave it like that. Whatever.
DN: Let's see what happens.
SP: So this needs a semi colon.
Now it should be a bit more erratic.
Oh no, why not.
What am I returning?
[Silence]
So if it's negative? WHAT?
This doesn't make any sense. Why?
I'm going to debug this thingy.
What is when, which is fine.
[Silence]
I guess it's because I've set the
debugger which introduces some delay,
so I'm not getting a negative time here.
DN: Interesting yes.
SP: So I'm going to remove the breakpoint thingy.
It's really messy. Because they are really bad players!
[they listen]
DN: I think the variation there is longer than a beat isn't it?
SP: Yeah exactly.
SP: I hate this! I always want to have a page with all of the one-liners I can check and make sure that they're ok.
This is going to go from 1 to 0, but that's not what I want.
So if I multiply this...
This is me going off on a long-winded...
What am I doing? Argh!
One...
This is easier:
1-0=1
1-1=0
I think if it's: