Chapter 4: Playing part 1 sequence once
SP: OK, so we want to play this thing, at least once.
Let's just make the first player play its thing.
DN: Sure.
So I'm going to copy this
here and add it as a comment.
Obviously we don't know how to play the thing.
But I'm going to simulate this as
an array. Make it as zeros and ones.
DN: Yes, sure.
SP: So it's one, one, one, and
the score is zero, so it's nothing.
Then one, one, one zero, one, one, zero, one,
zero, one, one, zero.  So that's the same, but in binary.
DN: Yes, binary solo.
SP: Yes. Sometimes what I do when
you have things that come from strings,
because people are comfortable
drawing things, kind of like ASCII art.
You could parse it and say
if it's an x replace it with a one  etc.
But, in this case its short
enough for us to leave it like that.
Yes, that should be short enough.
So, we can assume that
every element of the array is a step.
So I will arbitrarily give it a stepLength,
say 0.2 seconds. Because web audio uses seconds.
So what I will do to play the sequence initially,
is calculate the timing for all this
and schedule the play, so we can listen.
so we can reuse the same buffer
I don't need to load it every time, just load it
once and reuse it with different buffer sources.
So instead of playing the buffer,
what I'll do is play the sequence.
So I'll change this.
With the decodedBuffer... I'll change things later.
I want to inaud up on things that already exist.
[Silence]
It's not behaving so...
Normally my font is very small
so I can see everything in one go.
But here I can't so I need two panes both in the center.
When it's a long file like this I like to see the top.
Also I've found you can use this
:vsp to have two different files.
So you can look at say, the class
in one side and in the other.
I was like, this is the best discovery I've made!
Because I thought that the
vertical split was only for the same file.
I didn't know you could view
different files, so this was a good discovery.
So I've got this sequence, and I
know how long I want to play each step for.
So we'll just go through that and
arrange for other things to be played.
[Silence]
So initially, time is zero.
DN: Right.
So if I go through the
sequence and I know the stepLength.
I need to be adding the stepLength to time,
because I want to say "do all these things at this time"
DN: Yes.
SP: So it should play the sequence at that position.
So if it's one it would be truthy and if it's
zero it won't be truthy, so I won't do this thing.
DN: Oh yes OK.
SP: If it should play, I would say playBuffer.
But I don't know when, so I need to add a new parameter.
So I say when. And instead of just
`start()`, I'll say `start(when)`.And I'll say at `t`.
But actually `t` is not zero.
T has to be the AudioContext.currentTime.
Because, the way it works is
when you create another context...
I don't know if it's when you create
another context or when the page is created.
But essentially the clock starts running, so
when you say to web audio I want to do this thing,
you don't tell it in the scripts time,
but in the clock for the audio context.
So when you want to scale things, you want to do
that relative to the audio context 'timer' or 'clock'
or whatever you want to call it.
So if you start with the current time, you say
"run it from there" and we keep adding things,
and it's like it's all in the same
scale, we are using seconds here.
Because everything is using seconds
that should all be correct. So it has to play,
I was checking this, this is going
to play all the time, it has to.
So this is going to create 12 buffer sources and
it's going to connect them and start them.
They're going to be scheduled to start
playing then at some point they will just die.
DN: Yes right.
SP: And that's the way you
should do things in web audio.
You don't need to worry about
deleting things, or stopping or re-using them
because it's better to just schedule everything.
And let web audio take care of
things because it goes in a different thread.
And you can't be sure that the things
that your doing in this thread are the same.
DN: I see.
SP: In the same time scale or,
you know... I call it the parallel universe.
Just send things and hope for the best.
So in theory, this should
now play. [We hear the claps]
So see, they have disappeared,
because they are being destroyed.
I will try it again. [We hear the claps again]
DN: Yes, how interesting.
SP: Yes, but this is just happening once.
So this is good. It played the sequence.
So I'm going to make another commit.
This is where I get obsessive about this.
[Silence]