NARRATOR: Welcome to Peer to Peer
where you can hone your skills
by watching live coding videos.
Our guest today is Sam Phippen
Who's a swashbuckling hacker from London, UK.
He fixes every size of data problem and inaud plausible solutions.
He helps fight the forces of justice
as a member of RSpec core team.
And he's sad that he can't hug every cat.
Our host is Camille Baldock.
And the challenge that she's set for Sam is called
Building a Spy library.
CAMILLE BALLDOCK; So Sam, do you
want to start by reading the challenge?
SAM PHIPPEN: Sure.
Write a simple library to enable testing with spies.
Here's a simple Ruby app
which interacts with a RESTful API.
The app has a parseing test suite, but the tests
are an incomplete specification of its behaviour.
Add a set of isolated tests that
spy on collaborations between objects
to complete the test suite.
Chapter 01
CB: Right! So do you want to have a
quick look at what this Ruby app is and does.
And we can have a play with that
before we actually dive into the challenge.
SP: Sure... so...
It looks like we've got a gem file and
a jem file.block lib and test directory.
So I guess the first thing we should do
is check that all the tests are passing.
The project has a test helper,
so we'll run that... it should run
We have tests and they're passing so...
I'm going to start by looking at what the tests do.
Seems like a reasonable place to begin.
So we've got a sort of standard mini test inaud and we're requiring a file called Counter Client,
which is presumably the RESTful
client the challenge mentions.
And we can see here that
we've got our counter client test class,
Which inherits from Vtest test
and it has a set up phase, but
it doesn't look like it has any actual tests in it.
Instead it's just used to do the set up, and then
this child class integrated counter client test
is the one that's actually running the tests.
And that does it's own minor piece of set up
providing I guess, the integrated collaborator.
CB: Inaud using HDP for the client right?
SP: Yes so whatever this LHTTP thing is
erm... that's presumably making the real
HTTP requests giving our integrated test.
And then we have our test
for the degenerate case erm...
... so that uninitialized key has a count
of zero and then 1 and a random number.
These test seem like they are pretty good,
covering for the behaviour of the actual object.
CB: Yes, let's have a look at what the
object does, we can only see a couple of methods
SP: Sure so...
... counter client object can
be initialized with an HTTP,
it has a get method which delegates onto the HTTP
and an increment method which does the same.
So that gives us the API that we're dealing with here.
And it's worth noting that there's a small
fix we can make here before we move on.
At the top of the file here we're
acquiring LHTTP but it looks like it's actually...
CB: We're not actually using it anywhere here.
SP: Sure, but it's being dependency injected so
I guess sometime in the past this file needed that.
CB: Alright and it's going to inaud to get that out.
SP: We should be able to play
that away and still pass all the tests.
[Sam thinks]
And the reason we're failing is that
it's not being required in the test,
which is where it should be
being required, so let's also fix that.
And I've put the require at the
top there but it can go either way.
Great, so we've past all of our tests.
Back to green... that's nice.
So we've made a more change without having
to think too hard about anything in particular.
So, the challenge adequately
describes the problem with these tests.
There's no actual evidence here of any real collaborations between the inaud HTTP and the counter client.
If you look in these tests, no actual
interactions occur with LHTTP and the test itself.
It's assumed therefore that the client is
delegating that, and we know that's the case,
but it would be nice to have
evidence in test as well as evidence in code.
CB: Right so when we look at that test, we have
no confidence that there is a HTTP thing going on,
and someone might have just put a hash and memory....
SP: Right, exactly, so I think it would
be a good idea to add some isolated tests
which use the the fact that the
counter client is already dependency injection
to specify the contract effectively between
the object, which will be an isolated test.
CB: So here we don't care about that it's
using HTTP, all we care about is that our HTTP thing
that we've dependency
injected in our counter client,
is going to be called in lots
of different ways and do the work.
Not just something else, right?
SP: Yes, effectively the counter client and
doing HTTP are at different levels of construction.
The specific languages here are different.
The counter client has methods that
are talking in terms of our domain rate, inaud
And the HTTP client has inaud that is talking in terms of HTTP inaud get post URLs
and then here we also we have conversion
from the string to the integer response body
because we have integer counts but
we obviously can't specify the HTTP body.
So I think it would be a good
idea to add a set of isolated tests,
which will take us into our spying library.
CB: OK, so let's go back to our tests and can
you show me where you would like to get started
in terms of what is it we would
like to look at on this HTTP object.
SP: Sure, so we'll start by adding a test to get that.
So we're going to have a new test case
which will be isolated counter client test.
Which is itself going to inherit
from the counter client test base.
The same way our previous one did.
It's going to have a set up block, and
here it's going to be mostly the same.
except we are going to need to provide
an isolated dependency, not the HTTP client,
so that we can observe interactions.
So this is going to be our spy object.
CB: OK, so I'm going to let you go on for a few seconds
then I'm going to ask you lots of
obnoxious questions about spies.
SP: So we need a name for our spying library.
I was thinking Bond... so we'll
say that each HTTP is a new Bond.
CB: We're getting very British Government with
this and I can only whole heartedly approve.
SP: So we'll pretend for the moment
there exists a module called Bond,
which provides us this
method and then we'll run the test.
CB: So what do you imagine this method
doing, what is our Bond history going to do?
The Bond object is going to be
a minimum viable implementation.
Or something that looks like
how spies are implemented in RSpec.
CB: So why don't we talk about how that
works, as in the minimum viable stuff in there.
SP: In RSpec, spy objects respond to all method calls,
that is, whenever you invoke any method on
a spy it will actually succeed and then return self.
which means you can do inaud, because when you get the object back
it's the same object which can respond to any method
so you can do eg. spy. inaud and that would work because it's just returning spy on each inaud
The job of spies, and why they are useful in testing,
is they record all the method
calls that are made upon them,
which means that at the end of our test
we can assert on the calls that have been made
to allow us to observe the interactions.
And so here, what we will do when we write our tests,
is the counter client will send the
various methods to our spy object.
We'll record them and then we'll assert on them after the inaud
CB: So we're doing the exact same tests we're doing on inaud
but on top of that we're going to
have a spy listening in the middle.
And making sure the right things
happen with a collaborator in the middle?
[New Chapter]
SP: So we need to write this library now.
And I think we'll do that as a new gem
and so we'll move out of our project,
and do bundle gem bond.
This will have bundler initialise and create the
new gem for us with all of the necessary set up.
It's done that.
CB: There's got to be a gem
called bond out there in the world.
SP: I'm sure we're stomping on someone else gem in inaud space but...
CB: It's experimental.
SP: This will be fine for what we're doing.
So this is what our project looks like
after bundler has generated for us.
There's a bit more in here.
One thing that's worth noting is we
now have a spec directory not a test directory
and that's got bundler set up to
automatically include RSpec into projects for me.
CB: So are we going to write our tests for inaud
RSpec and then revert back
to mini-test for our client.
SP: Yes, so the idea would be that,
our spy library, we can test it in whatever,
it doesn't really matter.
And then it's actually just going to be a
module that we can include into any set of tests,
And it should work.
The nice thing about using inaud Ruby is they all communicate failures the same way.
Which is they raise
exceptions when expectations fail.
So all we need to do to make Bond
compatible with both RSpec and mini-test,
is have it raise the appropriate
exceptions at the appropriate times.
and inaud our tests fail.
CB: OK, a question before we go on... inaud Bond so our license inaud or what?
SP: Yes, we have an MIT license, we have
a gem file which has a gem speck in it,
and then the Bond gem speck declares development dependencies on bundler and inaud.
It has 2 Ds here, we'll just fix those.
[Sam thinks]
We'll just fix all of this we
cant have any 'to dos' left or...
CB: Why what would happen?
SP: My understanding is that bundler
won't let you compile into a complete gem
if you have 'to dos' left in your summary or description or inaud page.
So it's to force you to put
something meaningful in there.
This one is fine because there's this response to
thing in here so we can actually just blow this away.
That's from private gems.
CB: Alright so if you have your own internal Ruby inaud, OK.
SP: One thing that's worth noting is...
we haven't got a dependency on RSpec declared here.
CB: Do you want to add a test
development dependency on there?
SP: I'm actually going to put it in the gem file,
because we're going to pull RSpec from GitHub Master.
This is a thing I tend to do in
my projects because I work on RSpec
and I want to be able to find
bugs when I'm actually using it.
CB: So you just work breeding RSpec or something?
SP: Yes, but I am uniquely qualified. [Laughter]
No, if that goes wrong we'll find bugs in it.
CB: Yes, no question about that.
SP: One of the nice things about doing
this is not only do we have all of our own testing,
which on RSpec is pretty strong, but it
means it's getting some real world usage on master.
We have a pretty strict no red merges policy.
So it's very rare that
master RSpec is non functional.
CB: But you have a bunch of tests
that you run on a bunch of Rubys?
SP: Yes, but we'll see. [Laughter]
CB: Who knows what today has in store for us.
SP: The other thing we will do quickly is GitHub the
project and add the gem file and the gem spec.
And we've got RSpec and spec
helper, and we'll see what those do.
That is the default test that bundler has
generated which I am going to delete.
And with green with some
examples... so that's a good initial...
CB: I love this failing test initially bundler,
it,s a great way to test your set up.
SP: Yes, I typically blow it away as soon as I
see it hasn't run, but it's useful to have a test there.
[New Chapter]
So we sort of specified the API a
little bit, back in our mini-test.
So we have the Bond module
which we can include into test classes,
And that provides us with our DSL,
which is basically just a method
which will return us an object and it takes a name.
The reason we tried that name is so
we can put it in the inspect strings.
Obviously if you have multiple
spies flying through your system
you don't necessary know which one
is which so it can be useful to tag them.
CB: OK so you use a name to
uniquely identify your things.
SP: Yes, this is a thing that I do with
all my RSpec doubles and all of my RSpec spies.
I give them a name which is
the first parameter they all take.
So that we don't have to think
hard about where it came from later.
CB: So this is when you do your let in RSpec and specify inaud double.
SP: Exactly.  So given that we've
specified a public API that seems OK,
I'm going to start by writing a high
level failing test which shows that off.
I'm not opposed to that API changing at some point
if the tests are indicating that's a good thing to do.
But it seems like a sensible place to start.
So let's open the Bond spec backup
and the first thing we're going to describe
is the .bond class method.
And the reason it's a dot and not a hash
is that the Bond method will be
available on the Bond module itself.
Not an instance method... no that's wrong,
it should be a hash, I'm talking no sense.
CB: Ok so we're going for an instance method Bond.
SP: Because when you do like this: that
makes all the methods from that module available
Right, so when we have a test method like
test these, right, that is an instance method call.
Not a parse method call, I was wrong,
but I had to work it out by saying it,
so that's fine.
The other thing I want to check
before we get too deep into this
is the contents of the spec helper, of the project.
I'm checking that because it's useful to know
how your test configurations actually happen.
I can immediately see something
here that I would like to change,
which is to do with how the requires, and also
there's no RSpec configuration block here at all.
This is a thing bundler has clearly generated
for us, but it's not exactly what we want.
So I'm going to have RSpec overwrite the
bundler configuration with its own defaults,
CB: So this is your inaud RSpec yes?
SP: Yes, so BER is just an alias
that expands to bundle exec RSpec.
[Big sigh] it's inaud a lot, so now if I just close the spec helper and re-open it.
That should have changed but it hasn't.
Am I doing something wrong?
CB: Can you do something to force it or remove it?
Maybe.  That's interesting,
I usually don't have this problem.
Let's just delete the whole spec directory, that
will make sure we just have exactly what we want.
Great, and now we have the default
generated RSpec configuration.
This is a file filled with comments, I'm going to
blow most of them away, that's what I usually do.
There's a lot of stuff that's usuful in here.
CB: I actually like it, it gives you the options
available without having to configure it.
[Sam dictates what he writes]
SP: This is a setting I turn on inaud my spec helpers.
It basically stops RSpec from going away,
and patching methods onto
all objects and classes, whatever.
So it disables the inaud syntax, but it also disables bare describe.
This is a lesser known thing it does, but if we reopen our one spec inaud file, which I deleted,
Require spec helper, and then type inaud describe, like we had before with bundler.
This won't work because we're in main,
we're not in the main object, right.
CB: OK.
SP: So disable monkey patching has
removed describe from module and object.
We're at inaud spider fault.
CB: So why would you recommend inaud these tests.
SP: It's mostly so if you end up writing
an object which has a method called describe,
RSpec doesn't stomp on you, which people actually do.
It' not like describe is such an uncommon word.
And nor should it specifically belong to RSpec.
CB: So is it specifically describe,
or are there other things going on here?
It's a bunch of RSpec DSL methods so
it also removes the example and specify.
And basically those are all aliases of each
other that delegate on to doing the same thing.
CB: They all describe inaud
SP: Yes, but the point is that's it's
better not to have to think about that.
The only trade off is it means you have
to write RSpec.describe at the top of your file.
But once your in here you can write
describe as normal, and the reason for that
is that we're inside inaud we have trust.
We've got out MT test set up and
we need to write first test which will sort of
help us begin to push the feature, which means
we need the method to have it do something.
I think we will start by having
it return a Bond spy object.
We're basically just going to make the class
then assert on getting an
object of the correct type back.
This isn't the best test for where we want
to end up, but it's good enough to begin
bootstrapping it and it will
probably go away at some point as well.
I generally try not to have object type checks
by the time I've done rating my tests but...
CB: But how do you test for inaud if it responds to all of the methods?
Quaks, like, all the Ducks.
SP: Fortunately, there is a protocol in Ruby we can use,
regardless of how pathological
the interface to our object is.
We might end up using that internally as
we're writing... it's the triple equals protocol.
What RSpec does internally is it will
triple equals. the class against the object.
If we say, expect this to be a kind of
that, it will use triple equals to do that.
We don't need to worry about designing
an object that doesn't work against RSpec,
because RSpec really is designed
for all kinds of screwy objects like this
What we are going to end up doing
will end up being similar but more powerful
than, for example to how active
record defines attributes methods.
where, like, they're missing and then
they get defined when you ask for them,
And it's kind of magical, but this should be fine.
So I'm going to say it returns a Bond spy.
Which I need to type correctly!
Bond spy and then we'll
say expect Bond - this is arbitrary,
[Sam thinks]
... to be a kind of Bond spy.
The other thing we need to make
this work is to include Bond into our tests.
And so, we've actually taken a reasonably large
step here, but given that we defined the API earlier,
I sort of want to get that down
into paper before I run the test.
We could have done inaud Bond, watch it fail, call the method, watch it fail,
Watch the class beyond
defined and then define that,
but I think it's useful at this
point to have all that written down.
In the strictest sense, we've skipped
some steps but again I think that's fine.
CB: In the strictest sense, but your also
trying to show me where you're going,
so it's useful to have the API right there.
SP: Sure, alright let's run it and see what happens.
So we failed with undefined method Bond for RSpec inaud Bond, which is great.
So to fix that we can just go to
the bond module, define the method,
and that should get us to the next failure.
Doing that, we still have undefined method Bond,
so let's work out what's
going on to the documentation.
CB: OK
SP: This is pretty standard.
It's probably worth me pointing out here
that I'm totally fine with Googling stuff like this
all the time, even though I should know it.
I think having the stuff offloaded into the
collective brain of the Internet is a good thing.
None of this is what we want, although we could...
CB: Module spy!
SP: No say, [Laughter]
CB: Distance.
SP: I think what we should do here, instead
of screwing around with RSpec too much,
we can have a subject object
which can be included into it.
[Silence]
So here I'm going to do object.new.tap.
And then we're going to extend Bond.
[Silence]
Let's just format this so it makes sense.
Basically, we are going to make a new object,
and then the tap gives us the ability
to mutate that object and then return it.
Sending extend there should work...
I can't remember if extend is private...
So if we do Bond holder.bond arbitrary.
Undefined method bond inaud object... [Sam thinks]
CB: OK, we are extending the
module, are we extending the right thing
and are we requiring the right things?
SP: That's a good question... what's going on here...
CB: I don't know how you are including all your files...
SP: Let's just see if that magically
makes it work... it totally does.
My guess would be, Bond version, the versoion inaud was being loaded,
but not the whole module,
because this file defines the module.
CB: inaud no methods and try to inaud methods over it and not including them.
Ah Ruby....
SP: Yes, even RSpec inaud sometimes.
CB: I do like that it's really explicit though
and you don't have magical things happening,
It's a good thing that it fails.
SP: So if we do this now, does it work?
Yes totally, great, awesome.
It's nice to know Ruby works
how I think it works. [Laughter]
CB: Is there a mysterious thing to tack on the end inaud.
So our test failure was, got
one argument, expected zero,
So we can fix that with inaud name in here.
And we run all the tests and now
we have uninitialized constant, Bond spy.
And now we're cooking.
And so because Bond is the top level of our library,
I'm going to have it pull in
most of the constants we define here.
So we'll require a Bond spy here in just a second.
The reason I'm not going to require
that in the test is... I like to think of...
... at least these really high level
tests of library, as if they're a direct client,
and you're never going to see Bond
spy in your own usage of the library,
It's going to be a detail which is hidden from you.
Your just going to rely on the testing API
that we provide, so you don't need to know about it.
So we'll require it here at
the top level of the library.
If I was planning on
maintaining this library forever,
I would also mark the
Bond spy constant as API private,
so that people knew not
to interface with it directly.
Given this is a toy, we'll add that
require there and we'll make lib bond spy.rp
which will be module bond class spy, that
should be enough to get us to the next test failure.
And right, we've got expected
nil to be a kind of Bond spy.
To satisfy this we can just do bond spy.new and I'm going to thread the inaud through here,
and cheat slightly, and parse that in as well.
So now when we run this
my test should pass... and it does.
So now we've written this new bond spy
class it's probably useful to start writing tests
that describe the
behaviour of this class in detail
before we  pop back up and begin talking about
the library, because I cheated very slightly here.
We could also think about writing
a top level test on the bond library itself.
CB: Alright, what did you have in mind?
SP: So the next test would be 'it responds to all method calls'.
But because this is just like a DSL
that wraps the object construction,
I'm tempted to make these
tests appear on the spy class itself.
They could go in either place and I want
to make sure there's no test duplication as well.
Although the nice thing about
having them on the top level is that it
provides very explicit usage documentation because we're interfacing with the inaud API.
So maybe let's start there.
CB: We can always move them around later on.
SP: That's true.
The next test we're going to write will cover
the entire behaviour work flow of the library.
of the library, now that I think we've got it all connected together,
It's useful to think about how
the library is actually going to work.
So I think an adequate description here
is 'responds to all method calls and records them'.
And we'll write the simplest
possible way to verify that.
So my spy is a bond... these names are arbitrary... inaud method name.
and we need another method for
our library which is creating expectations
for the methods that were actually received.
And that method can't live on the spy
object itself, it needs to live on the library.
And the reason is because the spy object
responds to all method calls and records them.
So bond did you receive? Something like this...
And this could be a symbol, or a string ...
CB: So is this another test because we have the inaud something,
and then we have the action knows how to
tell me whether the things I want have happened.
SP: Yes, the other test we could write is...
it fails the test when it didn't receive a method call.
CB: And this is the usual inaud reception thing which is the default test.
SP: We expect this to raise error,
we don't really care about the inaud class right now.
So this is all the behaviour we probably need.
It's just a case of which one
we want to go after first.
I think it's going to be easier to write small
amounts of code to get the raise error to parse.
Before having to implement
the 'it records everything'.
So for the moment, I'm going to make
this an exit so it doesn't run all our tests.
And so if we run everything now,
we have our return to bond spy.
CB: We've got one that's skipped.
[Sam reads the message on screen].
CB: We're trying to be generic and RSpec is helping us not be inaud.
SP: So, that warning is useful and it's telling
us we need to specify an error class or a message.
And I think what I'll do for the moment,
so we don't get a constant missing failure,
is have an expected to receive,
and then it's this method name.
This is useful because we can just close this other pane for a moment,
we can see that we've now got a tiny bit of
duplication in our test, that I'd like to get rid of.
So we'll lift that into a let.
[Silence]
That can be this erm.....
And then...
Now that expectation and the bond that you receive
have the same string being assigned to them.
It's like 'called out' is
the thing were comparing on.
One thing I like to do,
when writing these kinds of tests,
is call out anything that is going
to be a comparison, into a let,
because where you parse it in your being
extremely explicit that it's the exact same thing.
For example, imagine that we were testing
something that used numbers, and said, that is a 5
Well, there it's much more obvious
that the method names are the same.
But if I have a 5 here and another 5 here,
it's not so explicit that that's what's going on.
So yes, that will be the first test that we
get working, and then we'll look at the other ones.
So if I run this now it's going to fail.
[Sam reads the message on screen]
Which is super useful.
So, that needs to go on bond itself.
It takes a spy or a bond, I think spy is the
wrong name, so this is a spy and this is a method name.
And all we need to do to make this test pass,
is raise expected to receive...
So that is incredibly obvious but
it has caused the test to pass.
So, in the true sense of the word
we've done, like a little bit of tdd inaud,
we've written our test and then we've
done a really stupid thing to make it pass.
CB: OK, how about we inaud some actual logic now. [Laughter]
[New Chapter]
SP: OK so we've got our easy test passing
with something really simple, the degenerate case.
Now let's re-enable the test that is expecting a
method call to go through implementing that.
So I'll just delete and then run the tests.
And we get our failure that we were
expecting, undefined this method name for bond spy.
CB: Something interesting happens when
your inaud, can you scroll out to er...
SP: Sure, so the test run started here and
what I have set up is, every time I run my tests,
it runs a bunch of git commands to work
out if anything has changed, what's changed,
and then it will run the tests and
depending on whether they pass or fail,
it will move us onto a branch and then
check everything in with status red or green.
CB: Great, so if we check on GitHub now
it's going to be red, red green, red, or...
SP: Yes, like our last test was red
because it failed, and then green red green.
CB: inaud
SP: Sure, we had two greens in a row,
we were stuck in red for a while, that happens.
One thing I tend to observe is,
when I've had an integration test,
you get many more red commits
as your pulling all the pieces together
but then once your beginning to
flow you get a red/green switching.
It's worth noting now that we have this
failing test as we begin to implement this class,
it will be red for quite a while, because
we will be making individual unit tests.
CB: So your just going from
failure to failure to failure.
SP: Yes, but the important thing to
note there is that it's incrementally moving
towards getting things working and we'll have more
green tests at the end of each run, hopefully.
I'm actually going to change this
test very slightly before we carry on.
And it's the same change that we
made before to our failure case test.
Where we called method name into a let.
This test has that same sort of duplication but
it's harder to spot because this is a method call
and this is a piece of data,
but they are indicating the same thing,
so I'm going to change this
to public send on the method name.
And this one to method name as well.
That's just the same as calling the method,
but it eliminates that piece of data duplication.
which I think is useful.
CB: inaud
SP: Well it's the difference between
making sure the method is public
and it being any method on that object.
Tests generally shouldn't reach inside objects
and using public send is one way to achieve that.
CB: So in our case we want it to respond
o public methods and private methods on the spy?
SP: Well our spy doesn't present private methods.
CB: It just responds to everything publicly?
SP: Yes, but no object should
know that that difference exists.
Even if you send a method,
your not caring about it's visibility
There are weird cases around that and we're not
going to think too much about any of them today.
Like what happens if you try and
access the private methods of the spy object.
Mostly because this library is
for interface contract verification
and obviously you don't do
contract verification on private methods.
I think this is fine.
CB: Yes, absolutely, I think it's
just one of those funny things.
SP: So let's just run again
to make sure we're still failing.
An undefined method name for bond spy.
So let's switch to our spy object, it's empty.
And now we're going to start
writing tests for this specific class.
To do that I'm just going to open a vim inaud with the spec file in.
And make sure the directory exists for it.
And now this test is ready to go,
so we'll pull in the spec helper.
Will describe spy and we'll
put this inside the bond module.
That's just so we can reference things without having to put bond inaud in front of everything.
Because we're describing our spy,
we'll immediately make the subject of our test
the spy, and we'll do spy.new, and again
I think this name is arbitrary for the moment.
So we'll just parse in a symbol there.
One thing I tend to do is when I'm inaud values like this,
I use a name like arbitrary, or doesn't matter,
to indicate to anyone that might be reading it
that it's not important to
read too much into that detail.
The moment comparisons begin
to happen, I'll pull that out into a let.
CB: How do you go about
using describe class, in general?
SP: Sure, it's true that putting that
constant in there twice is a bit of a duplication,
but I usually don't care about
that because I think that you get a lot
from explicitly referencing the class.
CB: inaud the favorite part of your files. [Laughter].
SP: Anyway, we need to write
a test now, and usually at this point,
when your writing unit tests, you would
write a test on a specific method name.
But, we have a strange object here in
that we're not testing any specific method name.
We test that it's going to respond to everything,
so that's going to be the name of our describe.
It's very important to consider
how we're going to make this happen,
so I'm going to start with something obvious
and see how we can easily contravene that.
So let's say for the moment that
our method name is method name
and I think we're fine to make this a symbol here.
So firstly, we're going to do
some Ruby level API checking.
Respond to should always return
true for any method on this object.
It should also inaud, but we'll worry about that later.
And this might be a good place to
describe the response to method like this
to indicate that's what were doing.
And there are a couple of things
that are important to note here.
Respond to is actually a
two argument method in Ruby.
Most people implement it with one
argument which is the method name,
but it also takes a inaud true/false, which indicates whether or not the method is private.
but were going to ignore that, but
I just wanted to make sure that's correct.
So because our object responds
to all methods, it's going to return true.
So expect subject.respond
(I can't type) this should be spy.
Respond to method, aim to be true.
And, that should fail in an exciting way.
We need to acquire the constant.
[Silence]
Undefined method, method name for bond spy.
That's our integration test
failing so it's true or false.
At this point we can just make this parse.
Private is a reserved word, I think it would be better if we call inaud method private.
We can just stick the word true
in here and that should work.
[Silence]
Can't have question marks or variable names
CB: I was going to ask about
that, those are pretty cool.
SP: I'm just bad at Ruby.
Right so the method is private,
it's optional, it defaults to false I think.
Let's check that.
Again, never be afraid to Google.
[Sam reads from screen]
CB: Can't include all also mean include private?
Sure, but actually it doesn't matter,
because we're just implementing
this method in the most obvious way.
We will be removing this
definition in a bit, but for the moment
this is just enough to get us going.
So that test now passes and
our integration test is still failing.
So now we've set it up to respond we
need to describe what happens when it returns.
And I'm going to say that it
returns self because that's our...
CB: Yes, it's going to be useful to do inaud.bar type.
SP: Yes, so we can dot chain.
[Silence]
[Sam dictates what he writes on screen]
It's probably worth noting here, that the reason I'm using B here instead of inaud
is that B does exact object comparison
so we know it's definitely the same object.
CB: It's an object ID whereas....
SP: Yes not just one that compares.
CB: So behind the scenes B is comparing
objects, what's the actual implementation here.
SP: It delegates onto something in Ruby.
I can't remember exactly,
but that's the desired media.
So if we run that it's going to fail
with undefined method name for bond spy.
And here's where I'm going to be
adversarial in the way I do my implementation.
So I'm actually just going to write the method.
CB: Oh of course, inaud to make it pass.
SP: Totally, and now I can blow away
my respond to definition and run this.
And those test should pass, and they
do, only our integration test has failed.
What we're seeing is, because this
method name is static we're never going to
be able to force the implementation of
the spy via test to respond to everything.
So we need a more powerful construct here.
My understanding is that in Ruby
basically any string is a valid method.
Valid method name if you
use send [they both talk at once].
There's that fun gist like when you
define imogee as your method names.
So I'm going to treat this
like the tests are external.
Entirely external to the object.
So we can use secure random.hex
to parse the method image.
Because the object has no way of knowing
in advance what that method name is going to be.
So you can't fake it out.
CB: So you're randomizing a method name.
Silly question but can you have a method as such inaud that?
SP: I believe so, as long as you use
define method I think any string is valid.
If we get errors we can just
stick a letter on the front of it.
But this seems like a reasonable place
to start, so we'll just stick that in there.
And we'll require the secure random.
At this point I expect both of these tests to fail.
And they do, with false and
undefined method 916 etc 4 bond spy.
So now both of our tests are putting pressure
on us to come up with a better representation.
It seems to me the best thing to
do here is to use method messing,
in order to define the behaviour
which will work for any method.
inaud
We have a method missing but here we are.
CB: I can't believe I'm going to let someone do inaud
SP: So the inaud method missing is it takes the method name
and then the ARGS that were
passed to the method in a block.
And we specified that we were going to
return self, so we'll stick self in there for a moment.
And then the other thing we need to do is make the inaud check work.
To do that we could override
respond to and return true.
But that's not strictly correct.
Ruby provides us with a hook to tell it about
method missing implementations that we support.
That's the method respond to missing,
which is invoked as part of respond to checks,
and as part of method missing dispatch to
know whether or not we actually respond to that.
So I think the signature is method name
and visibility but we should check that.
In fact we happen to be right there,
thanks Google, include all true or false.
We're actually not going to use that
property and the property is not optional
so we don't need to pass a default.
Great, so if we run our tests now, hopefully we'll have
that one failure, which is our integration test.
And the rest are working.
[New Chapter]
So we've now got that first piece
of behaviour working on our spy object.
It's responding to everything, it's returning self.
Let's just pop back to our integration
test and check where we're at.
We still haven't done this
bond did you receive method.
So if we run that we can see...
expect to receive method name.
CB: Is that because we're including
something that has all the methods?
SP: So we're getting this failure because
we implemented one did you receive
to automatically raise
whenever the method is sent.
Now we need to go back into that method
and begin to change it to make that work.
And in order to do that we're going to
have to do a couple of things to the spy class,
But let's not get ahead of ourselves.
So here, we really need to ask
the question, "if the spy receives the method"
then do nothing, otherwise raise, that can be inaud less.
And then we need to think
about how (they both talk at once).
CB: How do you feel about that interface?
SP: Well, we're going to
change the interface a little bit.
CB: So how do you see the method on the spy, how do you...
SP: Let's just start poking towards it, right.
We're going to make this method
private, that is an implementation detail,
nothing else really cares about it.
[Sam dictates what he writes on screen]
Now we have a problem and that is,
we've defined the public interface of the
spy to respond to everything all the time, forever,
so we can't add method to our spy to allow us to
interface with the calls that are being made to it.
We need something else.
So I'm going to change the construction
of spies to include another object.
Which we are going to call proxy.
And we'll then ask the proxy object
for each spy what's happened to it
during the execution of the test.
CB: So you still have your spy
that responds to all the things,
and there's also the proxy thing that
will have methods along the the lines of
have you received the method, and that
thing is going to be keeping terms on the spy
to check that the right things have happened
without messing around with the methods on the spy.
SP: Exactly.
CB: Is that how RSpec works behind the scenes?
SP: Kind of, but it's a little
bit more complicated than that.
But this is a good approximation.
Basically in RSpec, whenever you stub a
mock on an object or you create a double or a spy,
a companion object is created for
that object which tracks a bunch of details
about methods that have been
replaced and called and arguments and stuff.
We're going to implement some of that, but because
this library has a lower complexity boundary,
and also because it doesn't tough user objects,
we're going to get away with doing a lot less.
So when we construct our spies we're
going to need one of these proxy objects.
And we need to be able to get it back afterwords.
So in the bond module I'm going
to have registered proxies hash.
This is going to be really simple for the moment.
[Silence]
CB: Why are you hesitating on this one?
SP: I'm trying to remember if this
wants to be single 'at' or a double 'at'.
inaud proxies with the memorization.
Which probably means that there's a design problem.
I'm going to do something
really gross and I'm going to fix it.
[Sam dictates what he writes]
CB: Ok, so your making an
object to keep your proxies open.
SP: Yes, we're going to make an object and use the single inaud module.
Which is gross but it seems
like a reasonable place to start.
Actually, the other thing we could do...
is just have a... this... and then we can
reference bond concom proxies and do things to it
just until we're working,
and then we can reflect on it.
CB: When you have an idea like this or something
you definitely want to get rid of in the future,
Do you lead yourself or comment
yourself or something like that?
SP: The real problem here is that
this is a module and not an object.
Maybe we should fix that at some
point, but the nice thing about modules
is that they can just be included into the tests.
Actually, no I think this should be a class variable.
I think I like this more.
[Silence]
CB: Let's see where it takes us and
we can consider the pros and cons in a bit.
SP: I'm pretty sure that a single app would work there.
Mostly because it's going to happen
during the execution of a single test.
CB: So you would re-register
your proxies on every single run?
SP: Yes, this could just be an instance
method, it doesn't need to be a class method,
and that should work fine.
One thing RSpec does is keep track of proxies
globally, but we don't need to worry about that here.
So this should work just fine.
And then we need to create and
register a proxy object for each spy.
So to do that we'll parse... [Sam types]
We're actually going to do...
this is going to be slightly nuts.
So we're going to parse a lambda
into the spy, which will call itself.
So this is the spy, and then we do
register proxies [Sam dictates what he writes]
This line of code has gone
terrible so let's just pull that out.
And in fact we can give this a
method name, this is a proxy factory.
So basically...
And actually, this isn't a factory, it's a callback
CB: Oh good point.
So basically...
[Silence]
We need proxy to be returned from the left.
So, this looks slightly crazy so it's
worth explaining what this is going to do.
[Sam thinks]
When we call the proxy callback in the
spy it will parse the spy in so that we can basically
look the proxy up by the spy object
itself later in the execution of the test.
I'm just trying to think about whether
we need to immediately cover this with
unit test coverage before we move on.
I think we're fine at the moment because
we have that overriding integration test.
And also this feels to me like something
we're going to pull out once were done.
At the moment I'm doing something that
Sandy Mets calls looking for the honest green.
where I'm using the integration
test to guide what I'm doing,
and writing unit tests where there's
something that's obviously an object,
and then I'm going to wait to pull other
things out until everything is functional.
CB: How do you do inaud lambda call here?
SP: One of the principles I have is to
prefer lambdas over procs when racing.
Stuff like this, and the reason is because
lambdas get their own stack frame and procs don't.
That means they can validate the inaud of their arguments because the arguments go onto the stack.
And you can also call the
keyword safely from a lambda.
Otherwise they're very similar, I just think
it's generally better to use lambdas where
you can because they tend to make more
sense from a thing that you can call into view.
Having procs can sometimes
lead to very strange behaviour.
CB: OK.
Now we're parseing the proxy call back into our
spy, if we run all the tests we've got some failures.
Wrong number of arguments, those are
our three failures so we can fix that
by parsing the proxy call back in and if we run again...
... we still have failures. Now our unit tests
are failing so we need to go back and fix that.
CB: Because we don't have a default proxy callback.
SP: Let's just run our tests again.
So we have no changes, so we need to
go back to our unit tests and fix them up.
Ah... spy, we just need to re-load that.
So each change in construction of
the spy is parsing a proxy callback.
We're going to need a top level let for that.
And what is a useful default value for this
For the moment I'll let that be nil and run the tests.
So now we're back to having
the single integration test failure
and I'm going to add the behavior to
the spy to record stuff into the proxy.
And we'll do that with tests.
[New Chapter]
SP: So the test for this
records the method call on proxy.
And in order to do that, this is going
to be a command method to the proxy
So we're probably going to mock the interaction.
So, if I send the method then we need
some expectation that the proxy has been called.
We're going to get the proxy from the proxy callback.
But, it doesn't need to be very
complicated, so we'll say expect proxy.
And here we need the method name, like
the recording of what the method calls is going to be.
And we're going to make the proxy and RSpec spy.
[They both talk at once]
Yes like a nest, spying libraries inside each other.
And we'll just call this record message received.
And we won't worry too much
about arguments for the moment.
We'll just focus on recording method calls.
So expect proxy to be received,
record message received.
We don't have a reference for the proxy at the moment,
so this is going to be a lambda which will take
the argument and return the proxy for the moment.
The proxy will be a new let
which can be an RSpec double.
We'll call it proxy and it responds
to record message received
and we don't care about return
values so I'll explicitly make that nil.
One thing to note here, I was talking
about extracting duplication into lets.
I don't consider this to be a form
of duplication, these are actually different
because this one is saying set
up that you understand this message,
and this one is saying assert
that the message was received.
So even though they are the
same symbol and do the same thing,
these are being compared so
I'm not going to pull it out at all.
So if we run that now we should have
two failures, one unit and one integration.
We do and that's because record
message received wasn't sent to that object.
So to fix that we just need to go back here.
And we can... [Sam dictates what he writes]
And one thing I've done here is put
a double underscore under the method name.
This is a sort of conventional Ruby thing
for libraries that are super weird.
So because we respond to all messages,
we can't add more method calls to our object.
But it doesn't make sense to have the entire body of
behaviour around recording method calls in.
Method missing so it's fine to
push that out into another method.
In this case we're prefixing it with a
double underscore so that we don't conflict.
It's very unlikely that anyone is ever going
to want to call the method double underscore
record message sent to proxy on
our spy, so that's probably fine.
CB: So if we were in a production
environment we would probably have a thing
where we say if it receives inaud message sent to proxy then we do something different.
SP: Yes, the other thing that might end up
happening is this method might be one line long,
and then we might just put it in there anyway.
But usually I want to give things a useful name.
I'm pulling this out, not for the
abstraction, but for the name.
And this will just be
@proxy.record message received name.
And then to make the proxy we should
just be able to do [Sam dictates what he writes].
CB: inaud
SP: It does but I don't want to do that yet.
CB: OK, alright.
SP: We're going to slow down a bit
and make this step a bit smaller.
In this case we can just have a
lambda which returns the proxy.
And that should work [they both talk
at once] we record message received name
We've got three failures because wrong number of arguments, zero for a one inaud call back.
Record message received.
Proxy inaud received, record message received which is that name, which is the same as that.
Let's just print proxy and make
sure it's what we were expecting.
CB: What's getting the wrong
number of arguments here.
So it's wrong number of arguments
zero for 1, 18 proxy callback.
Ah! I see the problem, it's because
this lambda is being parsed into a context
where this let proxy isn't available.
CB: Right so we will want to make the proxy available.
SP: Or, we can just do this.
And I think that if we make
this a proc, that should be fine.
It's kind of nuts that we have to do
that but I think that's what we want.
Failing that...
[Sam and Camille ponder]
I'm not sure that I was right
there either... block proxy callback.
[Sam thinks again]
Ah! wait, no we've misread the test failure output.
These are all our integration tests.
And it's because we're
expecting self in the integration test,
because we moved ahead of ourselves, so that's fine.
For the moment we'll get our lambda back, that's fine.
It's important to make sure your reading the correct inaud.
So those are all our integration tests.
None of those need a test right.
CB: So now our RSpec has failed.
SP: So our actual unit test has passed
because it has received that message.
The other thing that we need to add here is the name,
which is something that we missed in our test.
Just to make sure that we actually do need
that, I'm just going to delete the name.
It's still failing, that's fine.
It's the first failure output.
And that's because the method name has been symbolized when we inaud.
So in this let method name we should inaud.
That should pass, and it does, we only
have those three integration tests failing.
So we now have our basic method recording
back, but the other thing we need to do
Is say, it sends itself to the proxy callback,
which we are currently not monitoring but we need.
To facilitate that we're going to change
the proxy callback from being a straight lambda,
To being another double.
And that's so we can spy on the inaud of the proxy callback,
to check that the self is parsed in correctly.
CB: I need an aspirin. [Laughter]
This is going to return proxy from the call
method so all our existing tests should still pass.
And then we'll do the same thing.
CB: So inaud public send and then...
SP: Yes just doing that would be sufficient.
We only need to go through the instructor but it's
good to keep exercising the whole thing here.
And then inaud method name,[Sam dictates what he writes]
And so that should fail, and it does.
I'm not even going to read the failure output,
I'm just going to do the thing I expect and see.
What! it does.
And because this is a single line it's
probably worth putting that back up there.
I think that's good enough.
The other thing I would do if we
weren't writing such a crazy object,
is add an inaud reader for proxy so I can change it later,
but in this case it's probably not
worth polluting the public interface.
[New Chapter]
So now we've done that, if we run
all our tests we've got some failures
but that's because we haven't got proxy.
So let's follow those failures
and implement that next.
[Sam dictates what he writes]
We'll also make a test file and run
everything to see where we're at.
We're still going to get that name error,
and that's because we haven't required it.
[Silence]
And we'll put that same require
in the test file for proxy as well.
Now we only have a single failure,
which is undefined method record
message received for bond proxy.
which gives us a good way to start raising our tests.
We'll describe proxy, we'll put this in module bond.
[Silence]
[Sam dictates what he writes]
Proxy is the wrong name, it matches the
class name but here proxy is the role it's taking.
At the moment we don't know if we
need any constructor arguments
so I'm just going to do proxy.new.
It's worth noting that RSpec will do this for you.
It implicitly will call subject,
it's just name class new.
But I'm doing this so that we get this proxy name.
Just to remind ourselves
where we are, let's run our tests.
So let's describe that.
[Sam dictates what he writes]
Here we need the hash -
it's going to be an instance method.
And now there's a question
about what this method does.
And internally the proxy is just
going to store all the calls as an array.
And so on it's own, this
method has no observable effect,
It's just effectively shoveling into an array.
We could just mock the array
and observe the shovel method,
but that's total overkill, so instead
we're going to have a method like
"was the call received".
CB: And we don't care about how
the proxy stores it's stuff.
SP: So I'm not going to
describe the individual methods.
But instead describe the
work flow with this object.
And because of that I'm going
to delete this describe block.
And I'm just going to say
observing the method call.
I think I used the word
recording so let's be consistent.
And again I'm going to
start with a degenerate case,
which will just be the method
wasn't received so we'll just return false.
CB: Do you usually start with the degenerate case?
Yes because it's usually easier to implement.
It offloads a certain amount of
mental work for me and also,
I like to view doing this kind
of TDD as very adversarial.
The test that I'm writing now should set me
up to write a maximally contradicting test next.
So to do that I find it much easier to start
with a really simple case than a complicated one.
So in this case inaud, respond to this false, did you receive this false,
is obvious and sets us up to maximally
force implementation with the next test.
And the inaud here is it tells us it hasn't received a call when it hasn't,
which is a terrible test name, but
I'm going to take that out anyway.
[Sam dictates what he writes]
And this is more like [Sam dictates what he writes]
I'm still not in love with this test name.
[Sam dictates what he writes]
Maybe we should describe the get a method.
Sometimes when I'm struggling I describe the get
a method and make manipulations to the object.
And be OK with that.
So this is message received...
CB: So do you want inaud whether specific message received, that's your interface.
SP: Yes.
CB: When that message wasn't received then?
SP: Yes, well it's more like when
no message has been received.
[Silence]
Have I got myself confused, yes, great.
And this is going to be
expect proxy.message received.
And here we're going to parse a
method name in, that will be a let,
because I know in future tests I'm going
to have to keep referring to this method name.
So we'll allow let now to be false.
So if we run that... it fails.
We'll make a let.
Here this can be an RSpec double because
we're not going to be sending real methods.
[they both talk at once]
The reason I like to use a double is that
I know that the only way a double compares true
with another object is if it's the exact same object.
The thing about symbols is that now they're
dynamically garbage collectible in Ruby 2.2
you don't necessarily have that
guarantee that's it's the exact same object.
It could have the exact same
symbol content but it's not necessarily...
CB: So do you need to treat them in testing
like you used to treat strings and older Rubys?
SP: Yes, and the other thing about
this is that it's a really strong callout.
But this double is the thing that
is going to be compared against.
That guarantee is really useful, because you know
that doubles only ever compare true to themselves.
So now we have that set up we should
run undefined method, method received.
[Silence]
And then wrong number of arguments.
And then expected false call nil.
And then parsing.
Great, and so the next one is it
returns true when a message has been received.
CB: Surely that message has
been received  right? SP: Sure.
A specific message? CB: Yes.
SP: And again here, this is an example
of that maximum change required idea.
I could have implemented 'it returns false' when
a specific message hasn't been received.
But that wouldn't require me to
change my implementation at all.
CB: Would you return to a specific message
received and then go to it actually returns false
when the specific message has been
received but your testing for another one?
SP: Yes, exactly.
So we're going to record that the message
was received and then [Sam dictates what he writes]
And we can copy this line
and change the false to true
And if we run that it should fail.
CB: And it does.
Undefined method record message
received, so that's forcing us to implement that.
I'm just going to go a little more
quickly here so we get the next failure.
inaud false to do that we'll have a
received messages which can be an array.
We'll do an attr.reader...
...and then receive messages shovel method name.
That's still failing so we'll do
[Sam dictates what he types]
CB: So we still have our integration test failing?
SP: Right, and actually, before we move on,
we should add a test for the negative case as well.
[Silence]
CB: inaud false on line 1 I think. SP: Yes.
SP: inaud pretty great.
Great! so that actually parsed
without us seeing it fail,
which is a thing that happens sometimes.
I think it's useful to see tests in both
states even though I can logically derive that
this implementation is correct, so I'm
going to do something obvious to break it,
and in this case I'm going
to put 'not' on the front there.
I just want to see all of the tests fail.
CB: So typically we should have
done something like receive message.empty
and then move on to include, or something like that?
SP: Yes, it really doesn't matter as long
as you see your tests in both states,
if your confident about what it's doing.
I'm happy with now and even though
I didn't make my tests do it in the exact order,
I can logically derive that this is what
we need to do, so it's probably fine.
Also, the implementation is really simple.
[New Chapter]
So back to our integration test which is
[Sam dictates what he writes] I'll just run that.
Expected to receive method name... and this
is because bond did you receive is raising still.
because spy receive method
is still open to implementation.
We actually missed a bit up here
earlier, we need to parse this method name in.
And then we just do registered
proxies fetch spy.message received...
...method name.
CB: OK, so what do our registered
proxies look like at the moment?
SP: It starts life as an empty hash.
CB: So at what point are we doing things that add to it?
SP: Our proxy callback takes the spy and makes a
proxy, inserts it into the registered proxies' hash,
which has persisted across whatever
instance this module gets attached to.
CB: Do you want to use the spy as a key, like the name or...
SP: We can use a couple of things as a key here...
...it' fine to use the spy as a key because the method
missing implementation that we have on the spy
isn't going to beat all the methods on the object.
And you can store just objects in a
hash and they will be looked up correctly.
So this should work... let's find out
It does... that's pretty great.
CB: So we've got inaud it checks our methods,
how about we have a play around with it in our inaud.
SP: Yes, so this library can observe the
methods were called and the subject will be
compatible enough to keep working, so it
makes sense now to integrate it in for one last try.
We'll make sure all our tests are passing...
and they are, so we'll head back into our Client
And modify the junk file to include bond...
And the way we do that is [Sam dictates what he writes]
It should work...  so let's just bundle install that.
And hopefully it's there... bond at 0.1.0 from
source at./bond as you can see, which is great.
So let's go back into our tests and remind
ourselves of where we were when we started.
So we're going to make a bond with
an HTTP tag, include it and then super.
So to make that work we'll
require bond and run these tests.
CB: Do you need to include it?
SP: It's already included in
the test at the bottom there.
So let's check to see if that
works by doing the correct thing...
inaud Ruby test helper...
Great so all our tests pass but more
importantly, this test class worked.
So now we can write tests against the spy.
So we will say, [Sam dictates what he types]
This is testing that that
delegation actually happens.
So to do that, we'll pull this test out and say...
counter client.get key...
...and then in a similar way to what
we were saying before, we'll ask bond...
[Sam dictates what he writes]
... the method name which is a get.
'And if we've done everything
correctly, this should work.
It does.
Just to check that it's all
working, let's also see it fail.
And it does, you can see here expected
to receive get, in the bond did you receive call,
and it didn't, so our test failed.
Great, so we've got something useful.
It's probably worth  also breaking
the implementation on the test.
So if we head back in to the counter
client, and just comment this line of code out
and head back to our test helper and run it...
... you can see here, all our integration
tests failed but also our inaud failed inaud.
Which means that despite our best
efforts, the spy library actually works!
And tests something useful, which is very
surprising, unsurprising, one of those two.
CB: A combination thereof.
[New Chapter]
CB: Alright, so we've got
our minimal viable spying library.
Where would you take next this in terms of, like is it a feature or something else?
SP: I think that the best thing to do
right now, given everything we've got...
...is do a little re-factoring of the library, because I
think if I was going to make this production ready,
specifically... this bond inaud is getting fairly large.
This proxy callback is clearly a
'thing' which could be given a class.
All of this stuff like spy_received_method
To me this feels like there are separate
concerns here, and also at the moment
the spy proxy is only using the method
name to record past failure states.
And I would probably change the way we
record methods calls to include all of that data,
and then push that decision down into the
proxy object, which is actually how RSpec does it.
The other thing... that I think
a good re-factoring would be...
is that... we're just shoveling the method
name in here, but when we add those details,
that's going to end up being it's own object.
Because it will have the method
name, and the ARGS and a block...
... and those things together
are clearly a concept in the system.
It's like add individual method call, and so
I would probably end up giving that it's own name.
This registered proxies thing as
well, we're not using all of the hash interface,
only a small amount of it, and that
probably means that's a main object as well.
You see, I can attack any of these.
The other one that's really common, but we won't do
now is... at the moment there's real no test cleanup,
so you loose your references to all
the objects at the end of the test.
One thing RSpec does is prevent
you from retaining any of the
mock stubs, spies or doubles across tests.
It actually knows which test they were
instantiated in and makes them invalid.
The other thing, that's kind of funky here,
is the spy returns self from all the things
but that breaks a number of
well understood Ruby protocols.
2I, 2F, 2S and so on will probably get
their own specialized implementations as well.
Just to not break other objects inaud
In fact, RSpec totally special cases, inaud on its spy objects
where this method missing  implementation
first checks if it's any of those calls,
and otherwise it does just return itself.
CB: So it's just like the usual public
method on any plain old Ruby object?
SP: Yes, one of the things that RSpec
does is ensure that its double and spies
are very compatible with
the rest of the Ruby system.
So == behaves as you would expect and so on.
This implementation is fine as far
as small is possible library perspective.
But I think a re-factor is where I would go next.
CB: OK, I think that's all the time we have for today,
but thank you so much for doing this
and the good explanations along the way.
And it was great seeing you work...
typing really furiously there.
SP: Thanks, it's been a lot of fun.