Welcome to Peer to Peer.
Where you can hone your
skills by watching live coding videos.
Our guest today is Jamie White.
Who's a Ruby a JavaScript
developer at With Associates.
And a co-organizer of the London Ember inaud
I'm your host Drew Neil
And the challenge that I set for Jamie is called
DN: OK Jamie, would you like to
start by reading out the challenge?
JW: This is how the sequencing should look.
And a sequence is
connected by guests and hosts.
DN: Effectively yes.
JW: So let's have a look
at the data to begin with.
I've already got this stuff.
I'm looking at past episodes to begin with.
I'm interested in the ones that
do form parser sequences already.
We have episode one where the host was you
and the guest was Tom.
That sequence moves on to two .
where Tom the guest becomes Tom the host
Camille becomes the guest.
And then this one leads on to here
where Camille goes from guest
to should have been host.
DW: Unfortunately Camille was ill today
so I'm standing in as host.
DW: In fact, this data is slightly stale
We could have changed it so that we have a branch
Where I interview Tom and also you.
But we're going to pretend that Camille is acting as host today
and stick with the sample data that we came up with.
We can always adapt it later.
Thinking of the nouns in this description
The data structure is composed of collaborations
The description is quite explicit about that
Now, at the moment an episode
isn't strictly a collaboration
A collaboration should have an episode
but not necessarily be an episode.
And it is not explicit in this data
inaud sequels.
But we know that we can
determine those from the host and guest inaudible..
I am going to use ember for this
A bit like reaching for rails,
I won't use all of it to begin with
but it gives you plenty of
directions to go in once you set up
Let me see what version of Ember I am running.
Cool .... leading edge inaud
Let's call this:
inaud all the dependencies we need.
DN: OK.
JW: It will take a while,
there's quite a few of them.
Because I'm using a local copy of inaud
inaud
I got it off GitHub
With inaud, what you tend to do
when working on packages that you're adapting.
Is to .... you do MPM work and it will similar cup
your copy of the repository to the node modules.
or directory
I cant use it straight away,
I need to first enter the ember mpm link cli
And that says also use it inside this project.
Now, if you follow the
trail in this local project.
You'll find this sim-link here going to local modules. inaud
inaud links to my very own copy of it.
It's a nicety of mpm.
Let's just make a quick change
and make sure we're
doing what we think we're doing.
OK, it seems to work.
I am inclined to ....
Get the data in first, and get it in the browser,
and think about it that way.
Pick up the data and put
it down again as much as possible
until some way to handle it emerges.
Before we get going, I'm going to ....
store another dependency.
So Ember is about to undergo ....
some significant improvements and this
inaud
And so you just opt in to the future.
I just want to do a quick check.
inaud at once and anyway it's wrong.
parser once and ....
There is another one.
DN: Did you just
switch to repository for Ember.js?
JW: Yes.
So I want these three features.
If you're running on Canary
inaud
The new things that are coming down the pipe
are hidden behind the feature flags.
That allows the inaud to release things incrementally.
That allows people to try them out.
without breaking the inaud
So I want those three things,
and the other thing I want is ....
I don't want this stable build of ember,
I want the Canary build components.
DN: OK, so this is leading edge, all the way.
JW: Yes
And the reason I think it's
going to be worth while is that
Ember will be changing shortly after you record this,
and I think it's worth
seeing what it's about to become.
DN: OK.
JW: So I think I want
that version of handlebars.
And that version of Ember.
Yes that's taken.
I'll just have a look at ....
all these differences.
So ember in the future ....
opt in to the future inaud features
and including inaud bars, which is the ....
next generation inaud up
I'll just make sure
all that actually works.
inaud this side of bower
inaud locked file.
It keeps the dependency
resolutions in the same file
in which they were specified in the first place.
There's not a lot of
difference to notice at the moment.
But things are better under
the hood for various reasons.
I'm not going to begin to test just yet,
because I don't know
quite what the target is yet.
I know I| want a data structure.
But if it's something I want to display,
then I want to let the view lead me
to what would be most useful.
Let's say for the beginning ....
display a list of episodes.
Thinking back to Toms Peer to Peer
and how often he commits,
and I realise that I'm
already several changes
into that inaud commit
my bits of inaud stuff.
DN: You've created a git repository,
was that done for
you by the ember inaud?
JW: Yes, ember as a new creates a inaud.
So that's my stuff to get
up on the latest ember.
And partly to demonstrate how easy
it is to use the leading edge of ember.
inaud rails, and inaud  command line inaud
It should feel inaud
Check in that check as well.
I'll just see what that is exactly.
So that at the moment is fine.
It's compiling, it's just that there's nothing to inaud
It just says there is no data.
So I'm going to commit that
Let's pull in those files.
I've got men next door.
I'm going to pretend they're
coming from an api of some sort.
So we'll put them in.
So we now should be
able to fetch down from
lol host\api\
lol host is because a inaud
I'll concentrate on episodes for now,
because it looks the most like ....
I don't have inaud yet the
roots of where data gets loaded in,
so I will:
I don't want to change the template
but  I do want the rest of it.
In my template,
I wasn't referring to model directly,
I'm referring to the episodes.
I'm going to stick with that.
So what I want to return from here
Is .... set up some ember uses.
I want to return a
promise to load in that data.
That should I think, be enough.
Let's just see if it compiles.
Yes, it seems to.
I'm going to go a step back to something
that looks a bit more like the guides.
Ajax ....
DN: Oh wow, that was quick.
JW: Yes (laughter).
DN: The episode inaud already
JW: Yes, its already made space. inaud
inaud here, I wasn't accounting for that,
It's actually way better.
We need to bring in the model,
for this template to render its ....
promise that you get to
load it somewhere in the future
and the rest will be taken care of.
Let's emit a little more data about this.
See what else we have to work with here.
This is to 'feel out' the data
and see what it suggests as
a good way to move forward.
Interestingly ....
inaud, leave off the closing dl tag.
And then what you'll find here ....
is that the new template compiler
It worked out that I
made a semantic mistake
in not closing my dl.
I guess I could just ....
DN: It should work for all but the last one.
JW: Great.
DN: I don't have a
poster frame yet for todays episode.
JS: We'll be doing a lot of that.
This data, in a sense tells us everything
we need to know about inaud the sequence.
What I would like to do is be able to ....
If I'm going to create this collaborator data structure.
I feel like I want to inaud test.
Now that I've got that rendering of the data
this is a good place to start.
Let's just commit that.
So I've added a route,
which brings in the same data.
I've added some of that data
to my template to make sure .....
I fully understand it.
And I'll generate some inaud tests which
I'll leave alone inaud too much about at the moment.
Maybe the simplest thing
for now is just to have a function
that does the job of
taking these two data sources
and produces all the right things as the output.
If I generate ....
So that's going to generate
a function in it's own module.
So I need a bunch of episodes to feed this thing.
and I might leave the
partners to one side for now.
It would be good
eventually, if that data is available
that the objects are re-used.
So that if I've got for example, one record for Tom
loaded into memory.
It's always that same
record, wherever I reference it.
And let's just see if we can
inaud the sequencing.
That's what we would expect inaud
I'm just going to refer to this again.
Episode 1 begins the sequence,
therefore it has no prequel.
but it has one sequel.
Oh no it has two sequels according to this data.
Jamie reads from screen.
Are there any left after 2 sequels?
DN: Not yet, but I think we could easily
adapt our data
to accommodate that later.
JW: OK. So let's take a
sum of what's in this data here.
so the episodes we're passing in are:
Let's get the prequel
side of things working first.
The challenge being ....
Let's just base this on the inaud id  to begin with.
I want to know when
I build collaborators as this:
Basically, I want a data structure
that's exactly as described in here.
So I want something that looks like:
I'll just take away this OK.
What I'm expecting to get
at the end of the road is episode .....
Its going to look a bit like .....
Like that:
Let's just deal with the sequels.
This is an interesting aspect,
If they point at each other ....
Let's find out.
It could get cyclic
DN: Yes, that's possible.
So this collaboration is
going to point to the next one.
inaud sequel back to this one, a prequel.
So I can't really expand out that necessarily,
So they will have to refer
to each one by an id I think.
DN: Right.
So you don't want this
one containing it's sequels?
JW: Not necessarily.
So this is an episode and
it would have this one sequel.
But then this would have ....
a prequel, which is ....
this one again which contains sequels.
Maybe what I want is
to simply append the id
of the prequel and ids
of sequels into these episodes.
Otherwise it will become this cyclic thing.
Say instead that I do get a inaud back ....
I get the same two episodes inaud a bit more data.
I guess we should run
some tests against this.
Let's ditch that server
for now and get test server.
I've got inaud just now.
That's interesting, I'm being told I've got js inaud now.
It's telling me that
the results are just true.
because I've not written a line of this method yet.
and this is inaud that's expected.
So let's start by ....
rather than inserting true in this let's go:
Let's return the episodes back.
inaud density function.
Let's see what the diff looks like.
I can see in the prequel inaud.
DN: So we're close.
JW: Yes.
JW: If we take this list of episodes.
We want to reduce it to some result.
The result is another list.
Each time we hit an episode ....
We can figure out what it's ....
We've got a temporal advantage
which is that our list of episodes are in
order of time, and therefore
a prequel isn't going to appear
the moment after one of it's sequels.
DN: Yes, that's true.
DW: Although if they
did come in a different order.
this would break down.
But let's just go for this to start with.
DN: I think that's the
safest option for now at least.
JW: Yes. So let's say:
I need to figure out
what it's prequel id is.
I'm looking for something in
the list of episodes, that has ....
inaud code this for a second.
inaud prequel if my current host was quest on that episode.
This isn't going to be very efficient algorithmicly
But it's a small list so
it shouldn't matter too much.