Welcome to Peer to Peer,
where you can hone your
skills by watching live coding videos.
Our guest today is Jamie White,
who's a Ruby and JavaScript
developer at With Associates
and a co-organizer of the London Ember meetup.
I'm your host, Drew Neil,
And the challenge that I set for
Jamie is called Deducing Collaborations.
DN: OK, Jamie, would you like to
start by reading out the challenge?
JW: OK. Generate a data
structure representing the collaborations
between guests and hosts
in the Peer to Peer catalog.
A collaboration has an
episode, one guest and one host.
It appears in sequence, with an optional
prequel (0 or 1) and optional sequels (0 or more).
Build this data structure from the
data provided as two JSON documents:
episode.json and partners.json.
Render a simple representation
of the data structure in a web browser.
And on page 2, this is
how the sequencing should look.
Episode 1 begins a sequence,
and is follod by Episode 2.
2 follows 1 followed by 5.
3 begins a sequence followed by 4.
And a sequence is connected by guests and hosts.
DN: Effectively yes.
JW: So let's have a look at the data to begin with.
I've already got this stuff.
Let's look at past episodes to begin with.
I'm interested in the ones that
do form parts of sequences already.
We have episode one, where the
host was you and the guest was Tom.
That sequence moves on to two,
where Tom the guest becomes Tom
the host and Camille becomes the guest.
And then this one leads on to here,
where Camille goes from guest
to should have been host.
DN: Yes, unfortunately Camille was
ill today so I'm standing in as host.
In fact, this data is slightly stale.
We could have changed it so that we have
a branch where I interview Tom and also you,
but we're going to pretend
that Camille is acting as host today
and stick with the sample data that we came up with.
We can always adapt it later.
JW: Thinking of the nouns in this description,
the data structure is composed of collaborations.
The description is quite explicit about that.
Now, at the moment, an
episode isn't strictly a collaboration.
A collaboration should have an
episode but not necessarily be an episode.
And the thing that isn't explicit in
this data is the prequels and sequels.
But we know that we can determine
those from the host and guest ids.
I am going to use Ember for this.
A bit like reaching for Rails,
I won't use all of it to begin with,
but it gives you plenty of
directions to go in once you're set up.
Let me see what version of Ember CLI I'm running.
Cool... Bleeding edge Ember CLI.
And let's call this peertopeer.
Ember CLI is installing all the
tooling dependencies we need.
DN: OK.
JW: It will take a while, there's quite a few of them.
[Jamie types].
Because I'm using a local copy of
Ember CLI– (I cloned it off Github)...
With npm, what you tend to do when
working on packages that you're adapting is to...
You do npm link and it will
symlink up your copy of the repository
to the node_modules global directory.
I can't use it straight away, I need
to first enter npm link ember-cli,
and that says also use it inside this project.
Now, if you follow the
trail in this local project,
you'll find this symlink
here going to /usr/local/lib/node_modules.
[inaudible].
You'll find Ember CLI linked to my
very own copy of it. It's a nicety of npm.
So now we should be able to do ember serve...
[Silence].
DN: [Inaudible].
JW: Let's just make a quick change to
make sure we're doing what we think we're doing.
[Silence].
OK, it seems to work.
I'm inclined to get the data in first and
get it in the browser and think about it that way.
Pick up the data and put
it down again as many times as possible
until some way to handle it emerges.
Before we get going,
I'm going to install another dependency.
So Ember is about to
undergo some significant improvements,
and this Ember CLI add-on will let us use the future.
And then I need to opt-in to the future.
And I think I want to do that.
I just want to do a quick check.
Ember-htmlbars I want.
And there is another one.
[Silence].
DN: Did you just switch
to the repository for ember.js?
JW: Yes.
So I want these three features.
If you're running on Canary at the
latest build off of master of Ember,
the new things that are coming down
the pipe are hidden behind feature flags.
That allows the core team
to release things incrementally,
but it also allows people to try
them out without breaking the past.
So I want those three things.
And the other thing I want is...
I don't want this stable build of Ember,
I want the Canary build components.
DN: OK, so this is bleeding edge all the way.
JW: Yes, and the reason I think
it's going to be worth while is that
Ember will be changing shortly after we record this,
and I think it's worth seeing what it's about to become.
So I think I want that version of Handlebars.
And that version of Ember.
Let's check that has taken... yes.
I'll just have a look at all these differences.
So bleeding edge Ember opted in to
these new features and included HTMLBars,
which is the next generation template compiler.
I'll just make sure all that actually works.
I've never quite understood this side
of Bower because it doesn't have a lockfile.
It keeps the dependency
resolutions in the same file
in which they were specified in the first place.
There's not a lot of
difference to notice at the moment
but things are better under
the hood for various reasons.
I'm not going to in to tests just yet
because I don't know
quite what the target is at the moment.
I know I want a data structure.
But if it's something I want to display
then I want to let the view lead
me to what would be most useful.
Let's say for the beginning...
Let's just a display a list of episodes.
[Jamie types].
I think that's right [inaudible].
[Silence].
Thinking back to Tom's Peer
to Peer and how often he commits,
I realise that I'm already several
changes in without committing.
Let me just commit my bits of bleeding edge stuff.
DN: I didn't see you create a Git repository.
Was that done for you by the ember generate command?
JW: Yes, ember new creates a repo.
So that's my stuff to get up on the latest Ember.
[Silence].
And partly I want to demonstrate how
easy it is to use the bleeding edge of Ember.
It's modelled after Rails and
Rails's command line tooling.
So it should feel familiar to anyone who knows that.
Check in that change as well.
I'll just see what that is exactly... whoops.
So that at the moment is fine.
It's compiling. It's just that there's
nothing to render because there is no data.
So I'm going to commit that.
[Jamie types].
Let's pull in those files. I've got
them next door. Let's pull them in...
I'm going to pretend they're
coming from an API of some sort.
So we'll put them in.
[Jamie types].
DN: So we now should be able to
fetch them from lolhost/api/episodes.
JW: lolhost is because I always mistype it.
I'll concentrate on episodes for
now because it looks the most like...
I don't have an applcation route yet.
Routes are where data gets loaded in,
so I will generate one of those... route application.
I don't want to change the
template, but I do want the rest of it.
In my template I wasn't referring to model directly,
I'm referring to the episodes
and I'm going to stick with that.
So what I want to return from here is...
I'm just going to set up some aliases.
I want to return a Promise to load in that data.
So RSPV.hash and this is
episodes, and we need some ajax.
I think I have the ic-ajax library handy.
So what we want to get is [inaudible].
I think that should be enough.
Let's just see if it compiles.
Yes, it seems to.
[Jamie mumbles inaudibly as he types].
I'm going to step back to something that looks a bit more like the guides.
[Silence].
DN: Oh wow, that was quick.
JW: Yes (laughter).
Oh, of course because ... yes.
DN: The episodes.json is already namespaced.
JW: Yes, I wasn't accounting for
that but it's actually way better.
All you need to do to bring in
the model for this template to render
is promise that you're going to load it at some
point in the future and the rest will be taken care of.
Let's just look at this template.
Let's emit a little more data about this.
[Silence].
So, what else do we have to work with here?
Guest name, host name, poster frame.
Let's put host first.
[Jamie types].
This is to 'feel out' the data and see what
it suggests as a good way to move forward.
Interestingly...
You won't find this in current Ember,
I'm going to leave off the closing dl tag.
And then what you'll find here...
is that the new template compiler
has worked out that I
made a semantic mistake
in not closing my dl.
I guess I could just...
DN: It should work for all but the last one.
JW: Great.
DN: I don't have a
poster frame yet for today's episode.
JS: We'll be doing a lot of that.
This data, in a sense tells us everything
we need to know about
how to determine a sequence.
What I would like to do is be able to...
If I'm going to create this collaborators data structure.
I feel like I want to do it in a nice, clean unit test.
Now that I've got that rendering of the data
just as a good place to start.
Let's just commit that.
So I've added a route,
which brings in the episodes data.
I've added some of that data
to my template to make sure...
I fully understand it.
And I've generated some boilerplate tests which
I'll leave alone. I don't care
too much about them at the moment.
Maybe the simplest thing
for now is just to have a function
that does the job of
taking these two data sources
and producing all the right things as the output.
If I generate...
So that's going to generate
a function in its own module.
So I need a bunch of episodes to feed this thing.
and I might leave the
partners to one side for now.
It would be good
eventually, if that data is available
that the objects are re-used.
So that if I've got for example, one record for Tom
loaded into memory.
It's always that same
record, wherever I reference it.
Let's just see if the sequencing
does what we would expect for the moment.
I'm just going to refer to this again.
Episode 1 begins the sequence,
therefore it has no prequel.
but it has one sequel.
Oh no it has two sequels according to this data.
Jamie reads from screen.
Are there any that have 2 sequels?
DN: Not yet, but I think we could easily
adapt our data
to accommodate that later.
JW: OK. So let's take
some of what's in this data here.
so the episodes we're passing in are:
Let's get the prequel
side of things working first.
The challenge being...
Let's just base this entirely
on the ids to begin with.
I want to know when
I build collaborators out of this:
Basically, I want a data structure
that's exactly as described in here.
So I want something that looks like:
I'll just take away this OK.
What I'm expecting to get
at the other end is episode...
It's going to look a bit like...
Like that:
Let's just deal with the sequels.
This is an interesting aspect,
If they point at each other...
Let's find out.
It could get cyclic
DN: Yes, that's possible.
So this collaboration is
going to point to the next one.
via sequel which is going to point
back to this one, via prequel.
So I can't really expand out that,
they will have to refer
to each other by an id I think.
DN: Right.
So you don't want this
one containing its sequels?
JW: Not necessarily.
So this is an episode and
it would have this one sequel.
But then this would have...
a prequel, which is...
this one again which contains sequels.
Maybe what I want is
to simply append the id
of the prequel and ids
of sequels onto these episodes.
Otherwise it will become this cyclic thing.
Say instead that I do get episodes back...
I get the same two
episodes but with a bit more data.
I guess we should run
some tests against this.
Let's ditch that server
for now and get a test server.
I've got no need to see the container just now.
That's interesting, I'm being told I've got a jshint error
It's telling me that
the results are just true.
because I've not written a line of this method yet.
and this is the data that's expected.
Let's start by...
rather than returning true from this let's go:
Let's return the episodes back
and make it an identity function.
Let's see what the diff looks like.
I'm missing the prequel and sequel ids.
DN: So we're close.
JW: Yes.
JW: If we take this list of episodes.
We want to reduce it to some result.
The result is another list.
Each time we hit an episode...
We can figure out what its...
We've got a temporal advantage
which is that our list of episodes are in order of time,
and therefore a prequel isn't going to appear
after one of its sequels.
DN: Yes, that's true.
JW: Although if they did come in
a different order this would break down.
But let's just go for this to start with.
DN: That's a safe assumption for now at least.
JW: Yes. So let's say:
I need to figure out
what its prequel id is.
I'm looking for something in
the list of episodes, that has...
I'll pseudo code this for a second.
it's a prequel if my current
host was guest on that episode.
This isn't going to be very efficient algorithmically
But it's a small list so
it shouldn't matter too much.
So we want to find,
an episode whose guest id
matches this episode's host id.
DN: I think that find by is
going to return a record isn't it?
You're assigning that to prequel id.
JW: You're absolutely right.
Let's make sure we
actually get a prequel first.
I'm mutating the
episode that has been passed in
I want to make a shallow copy of it.
But we'll deal with that in a second.
Let's see what effect that has.
Sure enough we do have
a prequel id on one of them.
It's a weird diff to read.
DN: The second one looks right.
JW: Yes, I think this is cool.
I've got prequel id, it's
just commas it's confused about.
OK, so let's try the
same thing with sequels.
Rather than find
by we will use filter by.
I'll refer to the docs for these methods,
just to show you
where I'm getting them from.
These are extensions
to the array prototype
You don't have to opt in to extensions.
You can leave them on the floor.
If you don't want your
core object monkey-patched.
But they are so useful most of the time
So a sequel is an episode whose host id,
is equal to our guest ID.
And with this one...
Because we know it's always a list,
we don't need to check so much.
I'll just break this out a bit.
Let's see what's the difference here.
DN: It's only the "prequel_id": null.
JW: Yes, it's undefined instead rather than null.
So rather than expecting null, let's just say
the key isn't even there.
That's our data structure.
Let me commit this.
See what new stuff we've got.
I fixed a JSHint error so I'll:
DN: You're making your
commits granular there.
JW: Yes
I'm not always the best at this,
but it's such good practice.
It's probably the best habit you can get
into as a programmer
Let's have a quick look at what this did.
So I've got this...
inefficient object mutating function.
It's not a very
pure function, but it does
help us work out what the algorithm is
and what it's trying to produce.
I'll commit this.
I fancy giving it a quick refactor,
to make sure that they can be refactored.
Avoid this nasty mutation.
Ideally, what I want is...
Rather than using the
original episode let's copy it.
This will be a shallow
copy so it will be a new object.
but the values for each of
the fields should be the same.
Right, so this is telling
me I've not imported Ember,
and I'm going to try to use it here.
This is all using the ES6 module syntax
which assumes you don't
want things off the global scope.
If you want
something you have to import it.
So let's import Ember
from the Ember package.
Let's see if there's anything
else that can be tidied up there.
I think there isn't.
I was talking about
the temporal problem earlier...
If a sequel or a prequel appeared elsewhere,
out of order,
it might not find it.
But because we're looking
over the entire list of episodes each time
that doesn't matter.
If we wanted to make this more efficient
we could assume that a sequel won't appear
earlier up the list, and you
can only search after this point.
But there's very
little need in this case.
So let's just add:
So now we've got that let's...
Let's go for another test.
I want to know that...
I guess that what
might be a good thing to do...
a way to represent this in HTML,
could just be links.
So jumping back and
forth between different episodes
and making sure that
sequence is maintained correctly.
Let's see what's the best way to do this.
I'm going to side step the problem of
mocking out the data under test
because our data is static
and instead I'm going to say:
We'll call this:
It should generate me a failing test.
although this test isn't going
to mirror what we actually want
You'll notice, it's trying to look up
the URL walking sequence.
DN: It wants to live in a world of URLs.
JW: The way to prove this works is...
go to the home of the representation,
see a list of people
who have played a part in Peer to Peer
click on somebody's
name and see the episode
they first appeared in.
And then see the sequels
and be able to follow to a sequel.
Yes I think that makes sense.
So I want to be able
to click on Tom and see the...
I'll remind myself what
the name of the episode was.
Counting Tree Nodes, where he was the host,
and be able to see...
all the sequels to the episode
click on those to follow through,
and then be able to click back
to the prequel.
I think the most logical way to represent
the sequence is probably via via links.
DN: Yes, OK.
What would be nice later is to find
a way to represent the whole graph.
In one visual snapshot.
But this is a useful way to...
test being able to pull all the data in.
Let's call this one:
Let's start by
visiting the home of the app.
A link that contains the words Tom Stuart.
What we are expecting is that...
At that point we should see...
I guess what I want to do is go
from the tree episode
to the Poker ranks episode
and back again.
DN: I suppose another way to look at this is
rather than starting
with a list of all the people,
you could start with a list of all the,
episodes that have no prequels
which at the moment
Tom's episode has no prequel
and Ollie's episode has no prequel.
JW:  That sounds good, that sounds like
what I was flailing for.
DN:  If we did have a list of all the people
JW: Some of those people
don't have root episodes.
Everyone has an
episode that they first appeared on.
Yes, OK let's do that then.
We want the root episodes,
of the different sequences.
Counting Tree Nodes
is one of those roots.
That feels like a thing we click on.
When we've clicked on Counting Tree Nodes
we expect to end up on...
see what we can ask about this.
the state you've ended up in.
We could ask something about the URL
I think that might be useful.
The other thing I want to know is
does this episode
contain a link back to its prequel.
DN: So if we're starting on the home page
and we click a link
that says Counting Tree Nodes.
That is episode 1 itself.
So wouldn't we end up with
currentPath() being /episodes/1.
JW: Oh yes, of course, you're right.
Then I'd expect to be
able to click a link, of course.
I'll get there eventually.
DN: OK.
We expect to be
able to visit the home page
click on Counting Tree Nodes
then click on Ranking Poker Hands
We could say at certain points what
URL we expect to be on.
It doesn't matter too much
I'm trying to tell the story of walking
backwards and forwards
through a sequence.
to get some confidence that
we've set things up right.
Let's leave it like this for now,
and see where this leads.
DN: So we're staring at the top level.
In the directory of
episodes that have no prequel
And then we click the first one
which is Counting Tree Nodes
and that has a sequel which is
episode 2 Ranking Poker Hands?
JW: Yes.
See what kind of errors...
DN:  It doesn't like
the URL walking a sequence.
JW: Let's find out.
DN: How did it end up there?
JW: That's a very good question.
Anyway, the failure is that there is no
link containing Counting Tree Nodes.
So let's head over to this template
We want to link to a root episode.
And the model we
want to pass in for it is this:
This episode here.
We need to deliver this data down
DN: So do we need
a rootEpisodes function?
We could say that the model for
the application is the root episodes.
So if we did that:
Now it's getting stuck.
For some reason...
I'm going to do something to
the model before handing it over.
So let's say:
The first test is passing so let's
See what the world
looks like at this point.
It should be the same for each episode.
DN: Ah yes, because buildCollaborators
does return the full list.
We don't yet have
something that just returns the roots.
That's interesting,
we're passing something into
it that it doesn't understand.
That's curious, I wonder if...
undefined is not a function: what's the
exact stacktrace of that?
That is probably slightly
adrift of where it really is.
Oh, I know what I've done, again.
Let's call this:
DN: Unpack it.
JW: Yes.
Now we've got a
different kind of failure.
I'm going back to the test at this point
rather than relying
on the running application.
It's not bubbling up, but
The error is that we try
and link to a root called episode
but we've not yet said what
that root is or where it lives,
So let's do that.
Before we do that let's:
I'm happy to lump all
those together as one commit.
There's no root just yet so...
let's get that working.
Let's see what kind
of difference that makes.
Cool, now on to the next.
Right now, there's no link to
Counting Tree Nodes on here.
And technically we're on root
which doesn't do very much.
And there's only the template for it.
I'll have a running
version of the app to look at,
alongside the tests.
DN: OK.
Oh that's curious...
Oh that's interesting.
Oh right yes.
I'm going to do a bit of a maneuver here.
Let me have a look
at the tree roots again.
There's an application root
which is at the top root of everything.
DN: OK.
The episode route will
be rendered inside of it.
And the side where I want it rendered
is in outlet so I
will put the outlet here.
But I want the main
list of episodes to go away
when I step into an individual one.
Index is a route you get
for free you don't have to define it.
And it should inherit its model from its parents.
That change, I wouldn't expect to do very much.
I could be wrong, that's
why all the tests are breaking.
That looks the same.
I think it might be a case
of too many changes at once.
DN: Your test error is quite fragile I see.
JW: It is yes, but that is probably because
we're on a...
I know that at this point in time
the CLI is operating to
a new file watching strategy.
so that may be part of it.
It's probably still going
through growing pains.
So now we're on
roughly the same point I think.
I'll take one of these.
We've got the right URL, there's nothing to display,
because there's no template just yet.
So let's make a template for this route.
In fact, let's just generate a route.
So I've added that other route.
It doesn't want to display yet.
That is the right direction to head in.
I think these are all part of one step.
So far there's not much here.
What we ideally want is to be able
to go from episode...
and refer that to that acceptance test.
We're expecting to
find another link at this point
with Ranking Poker Hands on it.
DN: So the list you are doing now,
is a list of sequels for the current episode.
JW: Yes.
DN; So that's the
name of the route episode?
JW: Yes, the name of the episode
the route and the
actual instance of them.
And the model we want for that route.
I think my buildCollaborators function might
not be the thing I wanted after all, but...
I might just...
I'll just check out...
DN: Switch to different Ember CLI.
JW: Yes, I'm going to go
to last stable releases.
I have a feeling this is
the cause of my problem so...
Narrator: We're going to
speak through this section
We spent almost 10 minutes troubleshooting this issue.
But, switching to the
latest stable release of Ember CLI
didn't fix the tests however.
Narrator: We'll pick up again where Jamie
came up with a 'workaround'.
JW: Unfortunately, in the current build
of Ember CLI, or rather the current
master build of Ember CLI,
some aspects when rapidly re-loading files,
causes the build to fall over.
So for the time being, instead we will run
Ember test as a 'one off'
Like a one shot test.
so it will run the tests,
then it will tear it all down again.
That will give us
something to work against
So it's not working at the moment.
And the reason is that
Although my buildCollaborators does point to
the correct ids.
What we won't have here is...
We're asking for model.sequels,
There is no such thing right now.
DN: Of course, right.
JW: So we need to get those.
You're probably thinking
it may be possible to do something like:
We know from buildCollaborators
that we do have
the sequel ids, like this:
So based on that
first bit of work we did
that's as far as we got at the moment.
Technically, that would work.
The API doesn't
actually have an end point
for that you could load up all the data
and find the one with the correct id.
At this point I'm inclined to lean on
Ember.Data to do some of the
pulling together of records:
So I'm going to:
I'm going to put in an elbow commit.
Let's see what I added there.
Let's say:
Let's checkout a branch.
This will be quite a substantial thing
to start to add in.
I think that in order to prove
that is definitely working.
I'm going to have a play
with the inspector to begin with,
rather than the test environment.
I have a gut feeling
it will be quicker that way.
So up top, in the application route.
Rather than this quite manual process of
getting the data and it pulling it out
and building collaborators from that
I'm going to return:
The promise library
It has this hash function
which is a hash of promises.
Where they all pass on this hash
with the promises switched out
for whatever they're resolved into.
So it's quite handy.
What this let's us do is...
I want to do two things.
I want to load the episodes
And that returns the promise.
This is going to return two promises
and it's going to wait
for them both to resolve
before it finishes.
Don't need the ajax anymore.
DN: Do we now have to define a store
for each of those?
The store we get for free,
but what we do need is...
To begin with, some models,
So right now this is
going to be complaining I need... that:
I've got no such models I think.
No models found for episode.
DN: You're using
camel case deliberately here?
while the API uses underscore case.
JW: It does yes.
Just by convention Ember
tends to use camel case where possible.
Just because
that's what JavaScript looks like.
challengeName string...
What else have we got...
we've got host name and guest name.
We should be able
to infer those from the...
So let's say we've got:
That should have
made me a model for episode.
Let's generate another one of these:
Let's just have a look at the data.
It might get
confused about what I mean here.
It will think there's a model with that name,
but in fact these are:
It's referring to the partner model.
And just like in Rails, I'll have to tell it
what the names of the inverse relationships are.
If the names are substantially different.
So here, the inverse is guest.
And here the inverse is host.
At this point, I'm looking at
building collaborators
as a way to prove to myself that
following host and guest
that way is what's intended
by the description of the challenge.
But I have a feeling that using Ember
Data like this is going to
shoulder a lot of the work for me.
I'm just going to go for:
What you are seeing here is
It's trying to load episodes partners.
It assumes those are the
end points we're looking for.
DN: We've got them in the API namespace
haven't we?
JW: We have indeed.
If we add some of this:
This isn't quite the order that things
happened in.
And then this change...
It's fine, right so:
It doesn't know about the
namespace of the API just yet.
And further more it doesn't know to stick
a .json on the end.
We need to tell it, the way to do that is
an adapter
We want this to be the universal rule
so we call this the application adapter.
DN: Ah, forgot to save the inverse.
JW: Yes.
At the moment it's the REST adapter
but the data that we're working with
looks quite a lot like what
active model serializers would yield.
So let's use that instead:
It's expecting data of this form
So it should know what to do with it.
Then we need to tell it the namespace
and I think it is
just namespace like this
DN: Does it still need to add .json?
JW: It does.
Now we're getting the right path
but without the .json on the end.
And I think there's another method:
urlPrefix is not quite what we want.
There's pathForType.
Which might well do the job.
Unless there's
something more general than that.
Let's do pathForType:
Basically this calls straight
through to the superclass method.
Now some
interesting things have happened.
We've got these warnings:
It's saying you've got this data
but you've not
declared that you're going to use it.
similarly, we've got
guest episode host episode.
It's expecting, like that:
Let's generate a serializer which will
enable us to perform those kind
of transformations on the input data.
Before we do that let's stop it complaining
about those missing fields.
That's episodes, it's expecting to see
guest name, host name, poster frame url
DN: They can all be strings I suppose can't they?
JW: Yes I guess so.
DN: Again, you're using
camel case but the API has
snakecase underscores.
JW: Yes.
DN: So, where is
that inference happening
from one format to the other?
It's all happening in the serializer
DN: Ah right.
You will find that by default
there's this normalize method
which does all this kind of work,
converting snake case
into camel case.
converting plurals into singular,
whatever is appropriate for the format.
Now I've got rid of some of my warnings.
but there's still this guest
episode, host episodes problem.
So let's say:
We don't want a serializer
for everything, we just want
a serializer for partner
There has got to be some hook
where I can turn
these into what it's expecting.
I've got normalize which
takes type, hash and prop
And that's going to do this work.
So if I:
Type meaning: when you get the data through
it's going to infer the type from this key,
under which each record lives.
But we don't care too
much about that manipulation here.
All we want to do is say:
Hash is this:
We want to move this so we're saying:
Once we've done those manipulations
we just want to hand it off to the
regular class method
I've not been so careful
to dodge a mutation here
because I think you
get passed a safe hash
DN: Oh, OK.
My warnings have now gone.
It's complaining that the value each
loops over must be an array.
We passed a record array.
DN: So are we down to this
thing called model.sequel
Now I'm at template index.
I'm calling model,
which is this object here:
containing an episode's partners.
So I want to do:
DN: Ah, because now
your model is in that promise
containing both models effectively.
JW: Yes.
So this has got me back to this point.
But the advantage I have now,
Before, I got to the
point where I knew the Ids
I wanted to get to, but
I didn't have the data to hand.
And the question was, where do I go
and load in that data.
Do I have it available?
Whereas now Ember
Data is doing that work for me.
And furthermore, here I can see
the records that have been loaded.
I should also be able to see...
There will be some
computed properties here.
So you can see,
belongs to guest episode.
There you can see it has
managed to dig up the real model.
That was me just clicking through
Here's an episode, "Counting Tree Nodes".
These are its properties, here on the right.
I should be able to go to the guest,
See what episodes Tom hosts,
That's a many array,
I'll go in there.
It's an array containing
one which is "Ranking Poker Hands".
So you can see it flow through.
DN: Very nice.
JW: leaning on Ember Data makes it
a lot quicker.
Now that's in place, let me commit this
quite a lot all at once.
a new serializer, changed the template a bit.
Oh it's not too bad, OK,
JW: Right now we have an acceptance test.
Which at this point is still failing.
because we've not added the list of sequels,
nor the prequel link yet.
I've got some unit tests which are failing
simply because they are just boilerplate
that was generated for me
They need to be told
more about the rest of the world.
I could just remove them
I feel I want to get them passing
to have a clean environment
So I'll do that quickly:
When I generated the episode model
I said that it had these two relationships
and the boilerplate test
has these two dependencies in it
because I said that.
But in fact there are
no such models as those
It's just partner...
So if I do that:
I have to keep jumping back to tests.
Now episode passes
If we flip over to the partner test
you'll see a similar problem.
Really all this wants is:
Now I'm back to my
acceptance test which is
the thing that is driving us towards
the place we want to be
which is as follows:
Eventually what we want to see
is a list of just the root episodes
the episodes that begin a sequence.
Click on one of those,
and you see it's sequels.
DN: Yes,
And you click on a sequel and you see it's
sequel, and prequel as well.
I'm using so many
styles of working with git.
So let's commit those:
DN: So this is the fugitive commit feature?
JW: Yes.
It's complaining at the moment
because I can't
click on Ranking Poker Hands.
So that is...
I'm in an episode, expecting to list all the
sequels of the model.
I do have .
So it's ready to list something.
It' not going to
complain that this isn't an array.
It's more useful to just fail silently,
when your at the template point of things
because there's so little failure
handling you can do in template.
As a general principle it's best to
treat these values as monadic,
They will resolve down
to nil, or the value you want.
I think what I need to to is...
get hold of these sequels.
That's going to change
later on if I don't it now.
The question is, if I take an episode
how do I find it's sequel?
I'm going to add a computed property
to this episode
called sequels:
Effectively I want to look
at the rest of the episodes.
And filter them down to just a set
where the host is my guest.
Let's have a look at what we have
in terms of filtering.
Whenever you access records in Ember data
you always go via the store.
Which is the central book keeping object.
And it makes sure your always getting
the same instance you got last time.
DN: Right.
I do have filter here:
I want to try asking for:
The thing I'm going to
be filtering on is the host id.
Let's see what the signature of this is.
It's just going to give
me an episode to work with.
Now this is going to
return a promise of some kind.
It says it returns a live record array.
So hopefully we will be able to dump that
into the template, and it will update
Let's find out, that might not be true.
We could go potentially have ids here,
but I think they will be
hidden from us by this point.
These are fully materialized records.
I forgot to declare
that this is a computed property.
There we go, so that's my sequel.
DN: Does that give us a passing acceptance
test.
JW: Well, let's find out.
I think I might have messed up my link-to
helper there,
let's find out.
This may be a problem
with my acceptance test.
DN: Is it the exception that's failing
where it's checking the current URL?
JW: Yes.
I think it might be just my...
DN: That's why you have a commit.
JW: So we see what happened there.
We've added a
computed property called sequels,
that sets up a filter
and these filters are live.
So the idea is, if a
new episode entered the store,
this filter should update
anywhere it's used in the template.
CamelCase challenge name,
and current path apparently
really means current root.
whereas what we want is the current URL.
So:
I feel that that acceptance test
has given me enough
confidence that things are
working on the whole,
and I feel that it's going to be
more fun just to play in the UI,
and see what other properties it has.
And see what other things we can do.
So jump to episode two.
We've already got the next sequel.
This at the moment has no sequels
and we're not showing prequels just yet.
So I'm going to:
Let's give this a title.
DN: Yes it would be nice to see the title
of the current episode as well.
and maybe a poster frame.
JW: That "Welcome to Peer to Peer"
looks surplus to requirements now,
so let's ditch that.
I'm going to make a bunch
of cosmetic changes all at once.
And then bundle them in to a commit.
DN: So we've got an else branch for each
JW: Yes.
I forget where Ember inherited this from.
It's not unique to Ember
It's a little like a LISP, handlebars
templating language.
It's not really capable
of doing multiple branches.
in a conditional, it's only a binary.
But it does mean you can do this kind of
thing with an each:
I'm just going to:
Make it look a little different.
I'm going to add in the rudiments
of what the prequel looks like.
Let's make a list as well
to make it symmetric.
This needs to be:
DN: Or you could say
"this episode starts a sequence".
JW: Yes
I'm going to use an each again.
Semantically, that's wrong.
You wouldn't have more prequels.
At least at  the moment.
the way we are going to filter,
I think we are going to use the same filter.
So:
Right now this shouldn't fail
in a spectacular way.
It should just silently do not very much.
Notice the silence there...
That indicates to me a build error.
But maybe it's OK.
A bunch of cosmetic
stuff... Let's just add that.
Let's see if we can get
a prequel implemented quickly.
I'm not going to worry
about the acceptance test for this
I have a feeling it will be extremely
similar to sequels.
Here we're filtering on a guest instead.
In the episode 2s guest is our host.
DN: Looking good.
So I guess the missing
element there is that list of root.
Those episodes without a prequel.
JW: Yes.
There is one little thing about this...
these prequels and sequels
If the host of either episode was changed
on the fly, so if this became an editing
interface.
these would stop being in sync with things.
So I have to declare
that this is a computed property
that depends on the value of host.
And this one depends on the value of guest.
Technically it depends on store
but store not going to change.
That's very interesting.
Oh, I know what I've done there, oh well.
DN: So that second argument...
JW: Yes, I think it's if you want to
send a different request off to the server.
DN: I see.
JW: It looks like it's
requesting back and forth repeatedly.
Let's kill that off.
That's better.
Excellent.
Right, so that second argument...
Jamie reads the last paragraph (above examples).
So it allows you to use
the data you already have
and make a query in the background.
Just covering all the bases I think.
So let's add that:
That implements prequels.
Here, rather than
looping over the episodes,
we want to loop over
something like root episodes.
DN: Yes.
JW: I'm going to say that we're going to
loop over simply the model.
This is going to fail at first.
We'll go back to:
So it's saying:
we're trying to each over an object,
just a hash.
Right now, we are
not in the application route.
We are one down in the index route.
So if I generate a route:
That's like  a real live route for that.
So by default a route will take a model
of its parent routes, as its own.
If we say instead, the model for this
is going to be:
We'll get the model for the application.
and then we want to pluck off the
Episodes let's say, that should be
more or less, back to where we started.
I think the best way to
perform that transformation is here.
Let's think...
We could use that filter again
We can say:
Actually, do you know what,
at this point these
things are already loaded.
Therefore we could do something like this:
It's this kind of thing.
I don't even quite call that,
So let's say:
The problem with that is that this is
probably not quite what we think it is.
Let's find out.
At this point in time.
I've got a strong feeling that if we ask for
prequels.length, you wont get back
an ordinary array of ordinary length.
So:
This is a...
I don't know what it is.
That seems OK.
So that's true for at least one of them.
DN: It seems to be
returning true every time.
JW: It does doesn't it?
So Ranking Poker
Hands should not be in here.
(Some sounds of confusion)
DN: Ah, it's working! (laughter)
JW: It suggests you
have to ask some question
before it completes the operation.
I think you may well find that it's these prequels.
It might be returning
something asynchronous.
Some kind of promise.
Let's think, what's the
best way to deal with this?
Let's go for:
I'm going to add:
See what else is available.
It might be there's another primitive
for doing this kind of thing.
Maybe we ought to add a
computed property to the episode model
We'll call this:
And this is true...
This is going to run into
kind of the same problem.
DN: If they were
prequels rather than sequels...
JW: Yes...
So let's see...
DN: I wasn't anticipating that
this would be the hard part.
It's a surprise.
What is it... When we start with a list
and it's got all five
episodes, and we click on one
and then go back again.
What is it that's changed at that point?
And then if we go back.
JW: Yes so...
DN: Now it's OK.
JW: At this point...
We've got these
two computed properties.
And the way they are bound into the DOM
gives them a chance to fully resolve.
To turn from promise to a real value.
Whereas in our route,
(sort of) inherited route environment,
we don't
we're saying get host.
sorry, rather we're saying...
I've still got all that to save.
I was expecting to see
the full list at this point.
What we are not doing is...
giving that promise
a chance to resolve itself.
before we return the
model data to the template.
I was hoping that this filter would
change dynamically, as
new data becomes available.
DN: Right.
It seems that isn't quite the case.
DN: Is there some way you can
do something before the model loads?
Maybe on initialization or...?
JW: Yes.
The dirty way to do it
would be to do something like this:
DN: And that forces the
computed property to be...?
JW: It's going to
kick start all those promises.
And change the state of all those models.
What's going on there?
Oh it's saying that I've still got no model.
DN: Oh that does it.
Unfortunately, because the model is
a little state machine,
to account for the fact that
you may have data landing later on...
other models may change around
it, that it needs to know about.
In order to get this
richness of relationships,
it can't be just a pure object.
You end up with these sort of situations,
where your having to wait
for a model to get into the right state.
Which is tricky, because in this case
we know that we have all the data up front.
But Ember Data is so geared up for the idea
that you don't know when data will arrive.
I have a feeling there probably is a way to...
There are extra properties you can add.
So you could say explicitly that
these are asynchronous dependencies.
But for us, because up in
the application route,
we have very deliberately
loaded in an entire store of data.
We shouldn't need to ever worry about that.
It's a shame that we're
having to do that but...
It gets us to the point we want,
which is to get these root episodes.
DN: Yes.
JW: So let's make that very explicit:
So, Solving Word Chain puzzles...
then it goes on to
Building a Basic Calculator.
And back there and... For good measure:
DN: We can link back to the top one?
JW: Yes.
Something like that.
JW: Cool, so now I would be interested to know...
To see what we're getting for our money
I'll quickly do this:
It would be interesting
to add another episode in.
And see if our
representation updates as we expect it to.
DN: So how about we imagine an episode
where Tom sets a challenge for Steve Purcell?
That will mean we have
a single root in that case.
But there will be a branch where
Tom has interviewed Camille and also Steve.
JW: Yes, right.
So, I want to try and do this in the inspector.
It's a useful way to check that
your app is behaving as you want.
The Ember inspector
gives you introspection
on everything in your living system.
These little $E buttons
will emit an object out
into the global scope, so you can play with it.
So this is my store.
I could do createRecord,
I could use store.createRecord,
let's try this.
Create record implies
that you're going to pass in
other concrete objects.
Like if there's a relationship.
I'm going to literally
give it Steve to work with.
But I think it might be more
interesting to push a new payload in.
This is a case where, you would have for example,
new data coming in over a socket.
Imagine that Peer to
Peer was produced so often,
that you had a web socket,
telling the browser that the episode...
You can use, I believe it's pushPayload.
So this is the idea of imagining a new
chunk of data coming into the store.
Let's see...
We've got pushPayload there,
I think we can get it on store as well.
Let's pushPayload,
What did we say, Tom interviewing Steve?
DN: Yes.
We'll go back to Counting Tree Nodes,
and we'll pushPayLoad which looks like:
DN: So the nice thing about this is
we don't have to create any new partners.
We can re-use the ones that exist.
JW: We're saying it will have an id of 6.
Challenge name: some challenge
that Tom would set for Steve
which would probably be
something really hard. (laughter).
Invent a new monad.
DN: Sounds interesting!
Guest name and host
name we don't really use,
so I'm going to leave them be.
Let's just say there's no
poster image for this one.
So we'll say host_id is
going to be Tom, who is 2.
and guest id is going to be Steve...
who is 4.
DN: Yes.
I think that to get this to work
I'll have to wrap it in an episode:
Namespace...
DN: You didn't just lose all that did you?
JW: I did.
DN: Oh dear.
I think it will be episode singular.
Maybe not, let's try episodes plural:
That is the end of the array.
There we go, Inventing a New Monad.
DN: And it just fits right into the sequence.
Very nice.
JW: And we should be able
to have a look in Data here.
There we go, yes.
These aren't the
computed guest and host names,
these are the ones
that are stored on the objects
that we're not really using in this case.
DN: We can probably ignore those.
JW: Yes, we genuinely have Steve the guest
and Tom the host.
I'm just going to add one
more little cosmetic thing
to enrich this.
I'm going to drop...
Because this was all about
collaborations to begin with,
Let's say:
DN: I would say featuring guest name.
JW: There is a little thing
which is going to happen here
which is that guests don't
have a name, I don't think.
DN: Yes, that's right, first name and last name.
But we could compute that.
JW: Yes.
That's gone from memory now,
so I've lost that new episode.
Featuring... There's no name, so I'll add that.
DN: That one has two dependent keys then?
JW: Correct.
Then, with a little bit of luck ....
This gives us the other nicety which is...
How does Camille spell her name,
is it CAMI?
DN: Good question, I don't know,
it's certainly pronounced Camille.
JW: We can now edit these details
in one central place.
DN: OK... Check it in.
JW: Yes.
This is where we:
DN: We've got the root, that's a major change.
DN: You misspelled featuring
I'm afraid (laughter)
DN: So we've reached a
good place to call it a day I think.
But if you had more time, how
would you like to continue with this?
For anyone familiar with building this style of
view on data in Rails, it probably
seems relatively simplistic.
If wouldn't be too
hard to do this with Rails.
The point is we are getting these potentially disparate
data sources into memory and turning them into
a data structure that we can then
wander around in
Without having to do any more re-loads
or fetches of data.
So now we have these
relationships between these objects.
It wouldn't be too hard to
render them out in other ways.
The way we have it right
now, linking between them
I feel like it's the...
simplest way to represent
a graph of different entities.
That's (kind of) the web way,
its most basic form.
But we could render
out a visual graph of this stuff.
I would be inclined to reach for Graphviz
or potentially D3 which has some
modules in it for rendering
directed graphs.
I know Graphviz and its dot language
better than I know D3
So that's what I would err towards.
The other thing I would like to get rid of,
but I just can't think of how you go about it,
is the reliance on this here.
I'm sure there is a way, probably an
idiomatic way, but in
essence it's because of this odd
thing of needing to... In the
same way you want to carry a monad,
up until the final moment, to finally unpack it,
and get the value inside it.
Similarly here, we want to
be dealing just in terms of promises
until the last possible moment,
when they are put into the template.
and eventually allowed to
be unpacked and rendered.
So, I'm sure there's a way around this.
but, it probably doesn't
hurt too much at this point.
DN: The idea will probably
will spring into your head
just as we turn the camera off (laughter).
JW: In terms of the UI, it would be...
You could render a tree out here of
blobs connected by sticks.
DN: Well, it's been really interesting watching you work
and how you use Ember.
And thanks a lot for coming on the show.
JW: Thanks for inviting me.