Welcome to Peer to Peer, where you
can watch our experts solve tech problems.
Our guest today is Camille Baldock
who by day writes Ruby and
Java script for the British Government.
And by night mentors junior
developers and teaches programming in schools.
Our host is Tom Stuart.
And the challenge that we set for Camille is called ..
TS: So Camille, would you like to
read out the problem statement ?
Do you know the standard poker ranking rules ?
CB: I do !  Which is fortunate.
CB: OK, right, so this is nice and vague !
CB: If I'm doing something like that
I need some way of knowing
this is hand A and this is hand
B and the program will sort it out.
And I need to think of how to
tell people to tell me what their hand looks like.
TS: OK
The first 'off the top of my head', easy thing,
is to you have some sort of string or array.
you have an array of 5 things,
that says I have a 5 of Hearts and the 6 of Diamonds
I could put that in an array or
represent that as 4H5D. (4 Hearts 5 Diamonds).
Put that in an array and then two arrays.
And create the problem.
So we'll get started with that.
So, I want to switch to input code.
What I'm going to do is make sure
I've got a couple of things in place
Like a spec helper.
And then, we can get started.
The first thing I want to
do is enter some kind of array 'thing'
and it creates .... we'll I don't know what it creates.
So, if I'm going to be comparing hands
A hand has several cards in it, and I need
some way to represent what a card is
and a hand that has several cards in it.
And then I want to be taking the hand,
and taking the other hand object
and then somehow comparing them.
So the first thing I probably want
to have in place is some kind of
hand object and some kind
of card object in which I can put 'things'
So the first thing I want to do is .....
I have an array that says 5H and 6 Diamond
And in the other hand, and
this is my hand object with those
card 'things' inside it.
So we'll start with that I think.
TS: Are you talking about an array of strings?
CB: As an input or .....
TS: Yes
CB: I'm not too
concerned about that at the moment
I don't think it matters that much
Since I don't want to keep
them as an array of strings
but do interesting things afterwards so
I don't think it matters that much.
TS: So this is just going to be a serialisation format.
CB: Yes, a hand parser type thing. Let's call it that.
So, if I have a hand parser 'thing'.
Ok, so this is the 'I can't type moment'. (laughter)
So if we have some kind
of object called hand parser
It probably should parses
the array of strings representing
the cards (this is quite
verbose), but let's get to that.
Actually this is going to
fail so how about we run this
And this is not very happy and inaudibleible
Yes, this is my first failure - here we go !
So I'm going to have to have
a hand parser sitting somewhere
I need to create that file in there.
And let's create a  parser
that does absolutely nothing.
But that should make my test happy enough,
unless I don't require it, obviously
inaudibleible - know where to look
So let's give that a try....
OK zero example zero failures.
So far so good.
What I probably want to do is ....
If I create a hand parser
and I give it the array of cards.
Of string things
that will represent cards then
on the other hand I want
to check what the output of that is.
So the subject is hand parser, so if we have
describe class.
If create hand parser and
hopefully have some kind of thing
that says pars and
it will take the array of cards
Which I need to define.
Let's have a look at how
I'm going to put those cards in.
So we can have those as 5 Hearts 6 of Diamonds
That's not an array (Laughter).
You choose the cards.
TS: King, Queen, Ace.
CB: King of Spades,
what's the other suit?
Clubs, that's the one.
So Queen of Clubs, and then we can have
let's have an annoying card in there.
Just so we have a bit of fun.
Which is Ace.
let's keep Ace as one
and see where that takes us.
I reckon that matters somehow.
But I have no idea, so we shall see.
And this should give me some kind of 'thing'.
This is already going to fail
so I'm not even going
to put an expectation in there
I'm going to go ahead and
run my tests and this should fail nicely,
because I don't have method parts.
I have a group of cards that
takes an array of things (cards).
It's not these things.
well - this test tests nothing.
But at least it's not giving error any more
On the other hand - I want it to be a hand and ....
I want this to be some
kind of hand 'object' type of thing.
So, I want to create a
hand object type of thing.
TS: OK.
Oh, how do we even do this in our spec.
I don't want to do something like this, right.
How do you get a thing
and check the class of it.
I expect my hand cards.count.
2 or 5 for example,
this doesn't test that anymore
so let's rewire this thing a little bit.
We'll just give this 5 cards
and it returns back a hand of cards.
So here we want it to have exactly
the same number of things that we have.
I'm going to gloss over the issue
and give it an array of
cards that only has 4 cards
if it falls over,
let's just not go there for now!
We'll just assume that our users
are going to put correct the things in there.
TS: OK.
CB: So yes let's just start with that,
this will already fail quite nicely.
Right, excellent.
This needs to return a
thing that quacks dot cards.
TS: OK.
CB: Look at me failing,
that's sublime, beautiful. (laughter)
OK, so if it has that then ......
This should complain
for different reasons now.
No shortcut, OK
inaudible parser hand ... so far so good.
This doesn't know what hand
it is so let's quickly acquire it.
And now back to our tests.
And if I make the count, it has nothing in it.
This should fail for
a slightly nicer reason now.
So here we have an
array that has nothing in it.
And we should have 5 things, inaudible
it's about time!
So if we have an array of cards
and has 5 things, then
I want to do is create a hand
with some cards in it.
So if we have ....
some 'thing' that takes the array of cards
which is essentially
an array of string cards.
or however you want to call that.
And I want it to basically ....
find that string of cards
and say, make me
a card object type 'thing'.
TS: Right.
and then eventually I'll want to inaudible hand.
but one thing at a time.
OK, so that can live here.
So if I  have make a card thing,
this is going to move to card object later.
Let's get to that in a second.
TS: OK.
I don't like the interface
of this, it is quite unnatural.
I quite like the fact that my parsing object
is going to sit somewhere else.
I don't want to have to do
crazy inaudible and things like that
as part of a thing that is
supposed to be comparing cards.
But, at the same time,
like here, I'm creating a new card
TS: So why are you
approaching it in this particular way ?
if your saying you don't
want this method to be here,
why are you putting it here?
CB: I'm not quite sure how much logic
what my card.new type
method should be accepting.
CB: In a perfect world, I would
like it to say 'if it's a 5 of Diamond' it takes
card.move 5 and a
diamond symbol type thing.
So I want a tiny bit of
pre-processing before hand.
To check that there are
two things in this string
H maps to Hearts, and something like that.
TS: Fine
So this is where I want
this to live. I'm not quite sure yet.
TS: So your expecting later on
that your going to have a better idea
of what's going on here.
CB: Yes.
TS: Ok let's see what happens.
This is a thing, and it takes a card string.
And, if I remember rightly,
my card string has 5 H or something like that.
So what I'm going to do is ....
create card.new and I'm
taking card string zero
card string one but actually not.
How do I want my cards to look,
how do I want them to quack.
It's going to be easier
for me as a human, to have
my suits (as in Hearts/Diamonds etc)
written out in plain letters
not as H and D etc.
TS: OK
I just want to do a very quick pre-parsing
if this is H then just
give me a Heart symbol.
and this is D give me a Diamond symbol.
Actually, this could be
variable, hash Y might do it
and switch.  Let's have a hash sitting here.
We have other suits, so we have
H, Diamonds, Clubs, Spades.
That seems correct.
TS: That's all of them yes.
CB: This is the slightly tedious typing part.
Oh right ! Spades.
So, this goes bye bye.
TS: So now you can just look up with hash
rather than using a inaudibleible set.
And I actually want it
to fall over quite loudly,
If I have something crazy as my suit.
TS: How are you going to make it fall over?
With 'fetch'. It means that if I put
say 5 A in there that,
fetch is going to complain.
because there is no suits with key A
and therefore it will throw an exception.
I should probably be handling this
in a different way if I'm doing that.
I definitely don't want to have a default value
because there's no such thing.
I should be thinking about things like,
do I want capital H in
there and little things like that.
But for now I'm doing
it with the minimum viable
array string parser.
And see where that takes me.
TS: So your motivation here sounds like
you don't want it to 'silently' fail ?
But you want it to complain.
CB: Yes, that's it.
In the same way here, for example,
So if someone puts H5 for example,
That would also fail quite loudly.
If someone puts HH however,
it's not going to fail loudly.
But, I'm not entirely inaudible,
and I don't want to spend time on it now.
I'll clean it up a bit later,
what I would usually do
If I'm writing things I want to ship.
I would put fail loudly and with better
errors with unexpected
inputs, much in the same way
I would probably be happy having
to do a fail nicely when not 5.
There's other things .... of there's
two 5 of Hearts .... you have cheat.
and things like that,
but let's not even go there !
Let's assume that that our players
are trying to be honest, at least.
TS: we'll, I don't know enough about the
variance of Poker to
say whether that's illegal.
CB: I think if you have one deck
and you have 2 x 5 of Hearts
you can reasonably assume that
somebody's messing with the game.
So that's going to fail quite nicely
because I'm obviously
missing quite a lot of objects.
But let's see where it's failing.
So, undefined method ....
Oh of course, I did something here ...
Here I'm assuming
that make card is available
on my string, which it isn't.
TS: You want to make it available.
I thought you were going to
do some monkey patching and ....
we'll, if you want to do it for
fun, to do crazy things. (laughter)
and then see how I fail later, then sure, but
I love myself too much
to do that to myself.
inaudible,
Now it's complaining that
we don't have whatever that is.
so we should re-create a 'whatever that is'.
To be honest I don't see it doing anything really smart
so it's just going to have ....
It's called 'Pips' in English,
that's the number on the
face of the card, is it not ?
TS: I think I've heard the word
'rank' but 'Pips' also seems sensible
I'm going to stick with 'Pips'
Since I'm also doing hand ranker,
rank is going to confuse things.
TS: Oh .. that's a good point.
Separate words for separate ideas.
I believe that's helpful. (laughter)
OK, so I have some kind of
silly strap that doesn't do much here.
I just want to acquire it -
rather than leave it sitting around here.
And let's go back to our spec.
Excellent, we still have nothing and that is simply inaudible
because I still haven't implemented it.
we're just going to initialise it with cards.
I can get rid of that.
And make that cards available.
this should hopefully stop complaining
because it did a zero failure,
so that is the one I want.
Let's have a look.
I'm creating my hand ...
My favorite way is
also to spell initialize with 's'.
and then I spent 2 minutes thinking
it's all American spelling.
TS: Yes.
Yes, good, certainly more convincing isn't it?
TS: Yes, very good.
CB: I now have some 'thing' and
it has the right number of things.
I don't actually know that
it does pars the cards correctly.
And if the array
looks like I want it to look.
so what I can do is ....
because, currently
my parser doesn't care
how many cards I'm parsing in
I can do a very quick check.
so it returns the right cards.
as a test, and if my
array of cards is just the one,
let's say 6 of Diamonds.
then I go inaudible exact same.
And what I want is ...
I take my hand,
I take the cards in there,
I take the first one and I
want to check the suit is Diamonds
I also want to check that
my Pips are equal to six.
TS: OK.
And I reckon that we're going
to have a surprising 'thing'
because I haven't cast it to an integer.
Since we're going to compare them,
it's a lot easier to
look at if they're integers.
That's strings - expected an
integer and got a string !
What I'm going to do
is not really good practice,
but that should please it for now.
So now I can have a 'thing'
and when I put several things in there,
it puts them in a hand
with cards, and then I can
check that if I do put
a card it seems relatively OK.
CB: If I wanted to be really
exhaustive I would go through
and check Spades,
check Hearts, check Clubs.
Just to see that that matching is OK.
And that would give
me a bit more certainty
about what on Earth I am doing !
TS: Ok
But that kind of does the
thing, that is good enough.
Now I'm going to start focusing on ....
If I have those two hand objects
and I can look at cards on them.
I have a nice interface with
my cards, it gives me Pips and Suits
How do I compare them.
Step away from the
computer for a second.
TS: Yes, it felt like this
was an administrative thing.
Your warmed up now,
you can make two hands of cards.
And now it's back to compare them ?
CB: Yes, that's about it.
The first thing we can do is have some way
of having a hand, and
it tells me 'you have a Flush'
or 'you have a Pair' and
that is actually your best thing.
Not just 'you still happen to have a Pair'
because the last thing I want to do is,
I have a card that has, for example,
3 of a kind which is better than 2 of a kind
inaudible which isn't very nice (laughter)
TS: I am roughly
familiar with the rules of Poker.
CB: I'm just being unnecessarily verbose.
TS: No, no, talk me through it.
CB: If I have 3 of a kind,
the last thing I want to do is
for my hand to tell me,
"We have two of a kind, excellent".
whereas the best thing I
could do with this is 3 of a kind.
ST: So for any individual hand
there might be several possible
classification of
the cards in it, but we want
to use the one that is most likely to
cause this hand to beat another one.
CB: Yes, you want the
highest possible rank of things
you can get in Poker.
so if I have 4 fours then I can't inaudible
I want 4 of a kind,
not 3 of a kind, and definitely not a Pair.
Definitely not a high card.
TS: It sounds like your first line
of interest, is classifying these hands
according to what kind they are.
How were you expecting to approach that ?
Essentially I want to look at a
hand and it gives me what the rank is.
so it tells me if it's a straight or thing
So it feels to me like we're going
to have some kind of rank method
on the hand that is going to return a
"and this is the thing that you can do with it".
That is the best possible one,
which we can half implement for now.
The first thing I'm going to
do is create a spec for my hand
because we're going
to start adding stuff to that.
Quick housekeeping.
TS: Yes.
CB: And I'm going to be describing my hand
And, I want some kind of method inaudible
I'll call it 'Rank'.
I have no particular reason to know whether
that's a good idea or not now.
So I'll keep it as it is.
And what it does is ....
returns the best type of hand,
from it's own cards.
ST: Ok. (laughter)
Which seems easy.
And I might regret this
because maybe it's not
the easiest choice I could have made.
I'm not going to put in a context for now
I'm not sure where I'm going.
So, I have a hand and .......
So this is where things get a bit annoying.
I have some kind of hand around.
For now I'm going to use the hand parser
which makes me feel this is
not the right interface for the problem,
If I have to use it in such a way, but if I have
say, 5 of Hearts, 5 of Diamonds,
we're actually going to take a Pair.
and see where it takes us.
7 of Diamonds,
8 of Diamonds.
This should just say "we have a Pair
and by the way that Pair is a Pair of 5s".
For now let's start with 'you have a Pair'
TS: As you said, that
might be enough information.
If there's another hand
that doesn't have a Pair in it,
you've already determined that.
CB: Yes.
The first thing you want to
know is do I have a better hand?
and then if your two
hands are not the same rank,
then you try calculating it.
My initial reckoning is that
it will be easier to calculate
what the highest card is at the
time I'm also establishing the rank.
So for now I want my interface
to just return the type of hand.
But in the future, I also want it to say,
this is the type of hand and
this is the highest card that counts.
Just in case there's a tie.
TS: Alright.
CB: Let's assume that's my
hand and I want hand.rank.
So 'expect' hand.rank.
to equal, and then ...
It turns information about
the winning potential of the hand.
This is a terrible description !
I'm just going to let it go, because in a minute,
I will probably change my
mind about what this should look like.
So if I expect the hand equals that .......
Not that.
This is failing quite nicely ....
because I haven't
done all my requiring correctly.
I'm doing silly thing with
silly shortcuts here (laughter).
I also don't have my hand parser.
What I don't like about that
is that now I can call this extra
class and I have this extra thing
that has all this logic here.
So rethinking it now I would
probably move that logic around
And have my hand.new
that handles things like that.
and my hand.new can take a hand parser
as one of it's attributes of the method
and I can make sure that
the logic of if it's H it's Hearts,
and if it's D it's Diamonds,
just goes somewhere else.
I'm not happy about that interface.
Because I don't like
stopping in the middle of a 'thing'
to do .........
This is not a nice interface,
not what I wanted to do.
TS: So your queuing up a
bit of re-factoring to do ?
CB: Yes, my tests have passed so
I can't afford to just go off on a tangent
and go to fix all the things.
So let's just have a quick ....
So that's parsing, and that's failing.
inaudible returns nil
which is pretty much what you'd expect
because it returns nil.
OK, so I've got all my cards
and how do I want to detect a Pair?
Array of cards - if I want to detect a Pair,
all I care about is the Pips on the cards.
I have all the cards, I can look
at how many Pips there are
for each of those cards and
I can count for each possible Pip value,
how many of that Pip I have.
TS: Ok.
So if I have say, 5678 here.
There was 2 x 5s, 1 x 6, 1 x7 and 1 x 8
TS: I see so your counting them
barring how many Pips they have.
you want to somehow say
I've got 2x5s, I've got 1x6 etc.
CB: Yes, I want some kind of Pip counter
that sort of mashes them up in
some structure they can read nicely.
Ideally, if I had a thing
like that then I would have
something along the lines of .....
I'm going to do that as a hash
but I would expect my
result to look a bit like this.
I would like a magical
thing that does that for me.
And once I have that
then I can check if I have
any things that so
happen to have 2 of the 'thing'.
And if I do then it's a Pair.
Otherwise, it's a highest card.
So that's about it.
I want to implement a thing that does that.
So what does this do ?
I would say it's a 'Pip counter',
but it's not a great word for it.
I'm going to call it Pip counter and ............
This is a silly thing I do,
and I may as well do it on camera,
(the world will laugh),
so when I have a
terrible name for a thing,
I just put a hash hash bob.
I was given the clean code
thing when I started programming.
And it has this amazing thing about how
you should not name your methods.
Things like holy hand grenade for destroy,
and silly things like
that, so I always put a bob
when I have bad name thing, and I usually
have fun, inaudible my interface.
when I'm finishing off an object.
So let's say it's a Pip counter thing, for now.
TS: Ok.
So what does my Pip count do,
Hey, we've run a test !
That is going to do that for me.
So if I have a Pip count ....
now whether that should be
in the public interface is debatable.
ST: Right.
CB: But I'm just going to keep it there for now.
As I don't yet know where we're going.
So if I have a pip count and I am ...
parsing exactly that hand then
this is exactly the thing I want.
I'm going to stop returning that.
There we go...
That should fail quite loudly, let's this test.
There we go ....
Yes, we've got nil, excellent.
So how are we going
implement this.  I have my cards
And for each of those cards I have Pips.
I can just inaudible
Suddenly here I have an array of numbers,
For a thing like this I need my documentation,
in case I don't remember everything
There is a Ruby collect on Ruby array
This is dash ....
It's a documentation tool that I like to use.
TS: So you have all of the Ruby inaudible.
CB: This is just a quick
reminder for me because
I reckon this has already been solved.
But maybe not, who knows.
Essentially I want to loop over my array
and count the number
of incidences of each 'thing'.
Which actually I could
do in any number of ways.
I can't remember off the top of my head
how I would do that
in pure Ruby. Any suggestions welcome !
TS: I don't know that there is a method in the
array that does that.
the only thing that comes to mind is
a 'group by' method,
which won't do what you want
but will do a related thing, which is
group together all of them
All of the 5s, all of the 6s and all of the 7s,
but that doesn't give you what you want.
CB: Does that give me
an array of arrays then ?
TS: It gives you a hash,
where the keys of the hash are
So the key in the hash would be
5 and the elements in the array would be
all of the 5 pip cards there.
and then it would be six and the array inaudible.
CB: I could map on that quite easily.
let's do a 'group by' and see how that works.
So group by ....
inaudible an array.
TS: It will be in the new model I expect.
CB: Let's just search ....
No it's not letting me search.
I'm in the wrong scope for it.
Numerable group by .... no, no no.
It's just giving me answerable stuff.
TS: Maybe that was a bad idea.
CB: All of the documentation.
TS: If you can implement it yourself.
CB: I shall implement it
in the space of a minute.
That should be fine, I've got all my Pips.
What I'm wondering is, do I want
just 52617181 or do I want
all of the keys of all the possible things.
and then how many cards I have,
but I don't think it
makes a lot of difference.
TS: It depends what you want.
CB: Group by, I was very excited by this.
OK, yes fair enough.
TS: That's not quite what
you said, but it's close.
in that you would get the right keys
but your values
instead of being how many
cards there were it would
be an array of those cards.
CB: I'm just wondering inaudible which is
this is not particularly pretty
It probably has a better way of doing it.
it might be the default for that.
Let's run a test and
see what that returns.
Yes, that gives me arrays.
Now we can just have a 'thing'.
This is my grouped cards, and then I can
say group cards and
then for each of my things,
I can say ....
TS: Ah, OK,
So you are turning each of those arrays
into a number by counting it.
CB: Yes so let's see how that works.
It's not very elegant
but it should meet the test.
and pass, so that's close enough.
We still have a failure
because we're not ranking stuff.
We are in the magical world
where only 1 rank exists.
There is Pair and high card.
If these are all my grouped cards,
and if I have 'anywhere',
in the number of group cards I have
a 2, then it's a win,
and otherwise it's not.
This is my minimal viable code,
it's something along the lines of ....
so this should return ....
I have a rank of type Pair, otherwise
I have a rank of type highest.
I'm not quite sure about line 10 now.
So I have all the values, I need to find ....
I think this is where tests help me.
TS: Yes (laughter).
I want to inaudible group of cards.
I've done something silly.
Of course ..... this is called Pip count.
Let's try that again.
So it does something,
and for the sake of completeness
I also want to start
using better names now.
Here I have a hand with a Pair.
and here I will have
a hand with nothing in it,
which I will call highest, as a type.
So if I have a highest hand,
I essentially want it to be pretty much this,
but I'm just going to put something there,
which as you see actually is a straight.
So, this shouldn't be ranking as highest.
TS: Does that matter at this point?
CB: No I'm quite happy about that.
It's fine, it's just setting
the scope of the problem
to solving a very small type 'thing'.
TS: Like you said before,
your imagining  a smaller version
of Poker that only has 5 cards right?
CB: Yes, a simpler and more boring world.
And now we have no failures.
I have a way of getting
arrays and then suddenly
I have one Pair, inaudible and another with nothing
and it does rankings.
So now we have some kind of way,
in an oversimplified game of Poker
to say I have a Pair and I have a highest.
So what I would really like to do
is start implementing a few more things.
So I think the super easy way to go is
we're not going to do just Pairs
but we're going to find 3 of a kind, and 4 of a kind.
and make sure the right thing comes out,
and by that I mean,
if I create a 3 of a kind,
let's call it a '3 hand'.
So if we have a 3 of a
kind hand, it's going to be ....
I need 5 of Hearts Diamonds and Spades.
and that at the moment it's
going to return a Pair, I presume.
but actually we want to return 3 of a kind,
so this, if I have the
rank, should be type 3.
so if I start running this file now....
Not like this,
and not like this either.
I think I'm doing
something wrong .... there we go.
I do have a failure because it is assuming
that I have type highest and not type 3.
because I am matching for exactly 2,
and obviously it's 3.
This might make my life a bit easier
because I don't need to make sure
that I'm doing things in the right order,
for that specific comparison.
I reckon it does matter for other things but,
let's get to that when we get to that.
I'm staring to write
some pretty terrible code now.
Shameless green ....
so if I have 3 then it becomes 3 of a kind
and if I have 4 then
suddenly it becomes 4 of of a kind.
but that is pretty bad.
I'm just going to check
that my tests do pass nicely.
And as they don't .... it is 3 of a kind.
This is 3, so this should now parser inaudible.
This now knows what a 3 of a kind is.
I could write a quick 4 of a kind
that we haven't covered for the future
when we're going to
be adding more things.
I want to make sure
that I'm not breaking things
let's just create some
test data with a 4 of a kind hand.
This is terribly verbose,
but we should have here
5 of Clubs and that should pass.
This is working out fine,
This however, looks pretty terrible.
So there must be a
smarter way of doing this.
I could jump in right there
and try to do some kind of ....
look at the Pip count and the values
and then if it's 2 it's a Pair,
3 of a kind, 4 four of a kind.
What I'm thinking now is that it matters
about things along the lines of for example
I'm going to take a problematic
example of the full house, where
at the moment my code
would give me back a 3 of a kind.
I definitely don't want it to say that.
I want it to be a full house.
What I want to avoid
now is making an abstraction
on this logic of pit counts, when actually,
it's not clear to me as
to where that should live.
What I would like to try doing now is
try implementing full house
which has 3 of a kind, two of a kind
in the same hand.
Get that working and then at that point
hopefully, I will know
how I want to look at those card counts.
TS: Ok.
CB: So I can extract that.
I'm going to leave this
horror in a tiny bit longer
until I know with more
certainty where I'm heading.
TS: So even though
your unhappy with your code
your going to hold of from re-factoring it
because you're not
confident that your solution to it
is complete yet.
You don't want to introduce
an abstraction that won't fit.
Your worried that if you extract it at this point,
then you will end up with something
that won't support full house.
CB: Yes, absolutely.
My initial premature abstraction is
I just map the number
of pip count values to a type.
and I can sense that that's
going to fail when I get to full house.
I want to see how I
will implement full house,
which is going to create
more inaudible in this code,
but I think it would help
me finding the right abstraction.
if there is such a thing as inaudible structure,
I find myself guilty of it a lot of times.
TS: Ok.
CB: I'm going to do a quick
test for my full house hand.
and it has 5 of Hearts, 5 of Diamonds,
5 of Spades, 6 of Clubs and 6 of Hearts.
So we have inaudible 6s, and here we go.
This is going to fail nicely.
because we haven't inaudible that yet and it's detecting a Pair.
which is not what we want.
Right now with my code I'm saying
if there's 2 let's go there, if there'
three let's go there, if there's four let's go there.
This feels counter
intuitive because in Poker,
what I want to check is do I
have an array or flush, or a straight flush etc.
There is an order in which you would check
because you would start
(in your head) with the highest hand
and if you don't have the best possible thing,
you would lower the expectations of your hand
and try to get as far down as you can.
The way I have written
this code is wrong in terms of
how a human would try to solve the problem.
I can also see it as part of a full house.
so if we do a bit of reshuffling,
and by that I mean check things,
(this is terrible code by
the way), but check things in a way
so I start with
the nicest possible outcome.
and as I go along I get less
desirable outcomes from my hand.
then that would have given
me 3 of a kind, as a full house
which is less wrong but still pretty wrong !
TS: But what you've done
there is burn into your code
because you were expecting it ....
then your saying
there is this implied thing.
But if you're explaining what a 3 of a kind is
there's this implication,
well it's not 4 of a kind
a Pair is not 4 of a kind,
nor 3 of a kind, and so it seems
now your code
more accurately reflects that.
whereas before it was
just working what by accident?
CB: It was working only in
the case where a specific hand
only has for example, only
3 of a kind and nothing else.
TS: I see, it's the full house
that's going to bring this out.
CB: The full house is bringing this out
and I think that other hands
are going to bring this out anyway
because if you have a flush that
also happens to have a Pair in there
you want to check flush first,
it doesn't matter if you have a Pair.
In the case of a full house,
terrible code would go along the lines of
if I happen to have 3 in my pip count values
then two things can happen.
Either I have also in my
pip count a value that is
2, so I have a 3 and a
2 and therefore a full house.
Otherwise, the best thing I do have
is 3 of a kind.
So that would make my
test pass, but it's beginning to look terrible
First let's check that I didn't get this one wrong.
so now that parses nicely and this looks awful !
I believe there's a
problem in how I'm testing those
TS: What's the problem ?
CB: I'm checking that an
array includes a certain number.
and what I want to know is does my array,
in the case of 4 of a kind it includes 4, for sure.
and I don't need to look at the rest,
but in the others there are a
number of things that we want to look at.
What I want to try doing is...........
TS: It sounds like you're
switching into re-factoring.
CB: Yes.
TS: Why have you chosen this point.
because you said
there are some other hands
that you haven't implemented yet.
Do you feel that you
have come to a point now
where you have sufficient confidence
in your implementation
so far to start factoring it ?
CB: I think I have sufficient
confidence to start thinking about it.
But I might hit a mental
block in a few seconds (laughter).
I want to see how the
other hands are going to work out.
All my other hands are along the lines of
straight and flush, and we can
assume that's already out of the way.
By the time the code will hit those
and now we're counting the
cards we've already excluded.
a couple of those things.
I still don't like this.
I don't like entering
this type of code because
if 4 of a kind is better
than a flush, for example,
so I want to look at those things later.
I am starting to imagine that I am creating
as I go along - this is a list of all the things
you can do in Poker,
and this is how well
they rank in the world of poker.
the highest and the lowest ranking.
And a straight flush is as high as it gets.
What I am creating in
my head is some kind of 'thing.
along the lines of
a thing called Poker ranks
which is something along the lines of.
The most desirable
'thing' is a straight flush.
Let's give that a rating of .....
I don't know how many
different types of cards
there are in Poker. Let's say 10
but I think that's wrong,
and then we have 4 of a kind
and that would be a rating line, and then
so on and so forth.
Each of those can have a method
that checks the card is what it is.
But that would re-use quite a lot of code
and I'm not happy about that either.
So, let's not do that.
TS: OK, so you're
talking about having some sort
of scoring system.
TS: What was your motivation
for wanting to score them ?
CB: I'm motivated to have
some defined order which
looks for the best
and worst possible outcomes
other than it checks for them
in a different order in the code.
TS: So you want to make that more explicit
rather than writing a method that looks like
you could do it in any order.
CB: Yes.
I'm going to start doing inaudible method.
Just so I can see where things are going
This is all going to be private.
I'm going to quickly go through those
That was a bit odd ......
Now we are assuming
that we have those magical
methods. It has 4, has 3 has 2
And checks whether there is a Pair
or a 3 or a combination of 4 in there.
which doesn't mean it's a three of a kind.
it means there happens to be
3 cards of the same kind in there.
So if we have 'has 4', then this is
still include 4 and in much the same way
inaudible has 3 and has 2
and that's going to be
pretty much what the pick is.
and that's a bit verbose
but I'm not so bothered about that
because it's inad private methods and I can get round to it later
if I feel it is necessary.
This feels more readable to me.
It feels like a 4 kind type
It has the Haskell check.
And for the full house, this needs
to be true and this needs to be true.
3 of a kind check this only needs to be true
Pair has pair needs to be true.
So suddenly I have all my cards,
all of the types of things I can do in Poker.
and I have a combination of methods
that can tell me exactly why that would be.
CB: So the easy way of doing it would be:
If has 4 then that.
This is still verbose.
I start re-factoring
and then usually I think
add a lot of stuff, make it very explicit
then start compressing later.
So inaudible full house
then type full house.
inaudible has 3 then....
3 of a kind, inaudible has Pair, then Pair
I'm going to have to
implement full house quickly,
missing def here.
Here we go, it has 3 and ....
maybe not multiply these.
I don't know what that does actually.
inaudible methods.
It complains loudly but I don't know how.
This feels more readable.
That's kind of what I would like inaudible
It doesn't.
That's because question marks are nice
it's maybe not the day to invent new methods in inaudible
undefined inaud has Pair simply because I called it has 2 and has Pair
let's keep it that way.
Go ....
and now were back in action.
this is more readable.
We're checking things in order.
there is a better way
of doing that but let's wait
until I have a couple more hands
and I can drive out something a bit better.
inaudible with the ranking but I'm quite happy with it yet.
TS: Ok.
CB: Do you have a favorite
hand that you want to go next.
TS: Well I don't want to prejudice you.
What's your favorite hand ?
CB: A straight flush.
TS: Then go with that.
CB: We'll have a straight flush.
TS: Seems a bit optimistic as you
don't have straights or flushes yet
but if you want to yes.
I think that's going to
drive out the changes quickly.
But yes your right, may be a bit optimistic.
In much the same way that full house
has 2 or 3 situations of straight flushes in
there's a straight and there's flush
TS: Is straight or flush easier to do?
I reckon flush.
TS: Why don't we do flush then.
CB: Alright.
Let's quickly create a flush hand.
The test definition is right at the top.
This file is getting verbose.
TS: It's a good job you've got that
hand parser otherwise it would be inaudible
CB: I don't want to imagine what it would look like
if we had to do doubles for this.
So flush, let's go for all Hearts.
I'm going to give
myself a very disappointing hand.
If you had that hand
in Poker, you would say WHY !!!
So that should give me a flush
and I'm going to check
that it's definitely failing.
TS: What does it think it is
CB: That's an interesting one.
We have a new problem now.
TS: What's going on?
CB: well, 10, it's got two numbers.
so it's not parsing it properly.
I'm taking the first character only
and in the second I'm
taking the second character only.
There's two ways we can solve this
I represent 10 in another
way, like zero or something.
inaudible that very quickly change the parser
so that it doesn't take the zero, and the one
and it takes something a bit smarter.
TS: The error that's coming out there
is that because you
did the fetch on the hash ?
CB: Yes, if I hadn't done a fetch on a hash.
and I had put a default value.
who knows what would happen in that
inaudible fail loudly.
TS: Yes, it's already coming on.
CB: It is failing loudly, so OK ....
here we're taking only the first character,
and here only the last character.
What I want to do is
take the last one.
inaudible I can do something along the lines of:
Oh, I don't even know.
Now how I would do that,
and I know that's incorrect
would be something along those lines.
There must be a better way though.
I know there's a way
of doing it with minus ones
but I don't want to do that right now.
I'm feeling particularly lazy.
Here, I want to go up to cards.
String length minus
one, take that as a string.
I want to run the spec quickly because
I reckon I've got this wrong.
inaudible arguments, what have we done now,
This is still a string.
I will make sure I've got a
test that does the 10 again
might as well....
let's just run this file now.
Now we have a hand
parser 20 length, so that's not right.
So hand parser on
line 20 calling length on ....
It's an array, no.
No it's called card string
inaudible
so one inaudible for zero, why
does it think it has an argument?
because parenthesis
Ah, inaudible method, this is terrible.
so last number of ....
This is terrible, I
should just do it in minus ones.
TS: How does the minus one thing work ?
I believe it puts you in
an imaginary space between
the start and end of your
row, but I might be wrong.
So what I will do is:
it's the end of the card number index.
this should be something along those lines.
and here I want to go up
to the end of card number index
and here I want to go front
zero to the end card index minus
No, I want to go to the end of card index
and here I want to go to this.
So this should still fail.
TS: That's not very optimistic.
CB: We have key not found
that's just failing again.
so my card string of this is not working out.
So this is nil because
end of card number plus one is
not quite what I want it to be.
Why is old code popping up ?
It has been returning inaudible laughter.
Let's get back to our tests
It's lucky that I spotted that when I did.
this is the failure which led us
to another failure.
But this is good.
Now, where is our flush ?
This is where I don't know Poker
quite as we'll as I would like to
so inaudible flush, type flush.
Where does flush
belong on this sort of thing
It is above full house. Yes.
TS: It doesn't actually matter.
No, that's right but it would matter
to someone who plays Poker perhaps.
TS: At the moment you don't have any code
that compares your hand
to find out which one is better.
as long as they are
correctly classified that's OK.
CB: Yes, so let's implement inaudible very quick flush.
so what my flush is ....
in much the same way as I'm
asking do I have two of the same thing.
I'm saying can you look at all my suits
and tell me if they're all the same.
and that's about it.
Much in the same way
I'm doing the pip count,
I probably want something
along the lines of a suit count.
that does this but with suits.
and here I'm going to do the dupe flag which is inaudible. this
inaudible a better abstraction to use here.
so here I'm grouping my suits.
I'm going to write a quick test to
make sure this is doing what I think it is
because I'm not confident enough
to reckon that it's all going to be fine.
So in this hand I have
my Pair hand which I am using
It has 4 Diamonds and 1 Heart.
so I should have Heart 1 and Diamonds 4.
It shouldn't be the pip
count, it should be the suit count
I believe that's what I called it. Yes.
Now I have two failures.
This is the expected failure
inaudible method suit.
Not the interface I was programming to
So this should be suit and not suits.
And now it seems to be
working and we're back on our problem.
which is permitting flush.
but now if I have some kind of flush count
rather than suit count then
suddenly my life is quite a lot easier.
I can implement this .... let's see
Now I have a flush.
Very quickly a straight
inaudible was more interesting and more complicated
not something we've done so far
so I have 5 of Hearts,
6 of Hearts 7, of Hearts, Ace of Hearts
and a 9 of Diamonds.
because it's not a straight flush.
Let's check if this is failing nicely. Yes.
And let's put our
straight somewhere in there.
There we go.
and if flush and straight
in much the same way
Let's have a look and see if those ones
what I care about is the inaudible and not the suits.
inaudible list of cards and their face values
and I need to make
sure they are consecutive.
TS: Ok.
CB: How will I do that?
TS: Good question.
The first thing I would
probably want to do is extract out
or if the cards are just the array of values.
because this is what I care about.
Let's see, where are our cards ?
What I want is this:
Now I have a sort of array
that is 3567, something like that.
In all likelihood it could be 47892
and completely unsorted.
so let's just sort that really quickly.
and we have a sorted card that leaves
I don't know why I'm
doing it in a destructive way.
I just like inaudible a bit silly.
So I have a inaudible card
What I want to know is are they consecutive.
Is there something that does that for me ?
inaudible to re-implement it.
TS: I'm not sure.
CB: OK, so what I care about
if I'm trying to determine
if things are consecutive
Let's assume we live in
a world where Aces don't exist.
TS: Ok.
CB: Because Aces .... no I don't want to go there
So if I have 12345 as
in Ace 2345, that's a straight
but I can also inaudible the high card, the King.
inaudible I could just have a bunch of numbers
and all I need to care about is ....
I look at the face
value on there and on there,
they are sorted, so
if the difference between
this Pair and this Pair
and this Pair is always one,
then I've won and it's a straight.
but I can't re-do that if I'm doing Ace because
my Ace would potentially sit on
one side or other of the array.
Let's assume Aces are just ones for now.
and then I'm going to make sure that I
write a test which is
"it works with a straight with high Ace".
and it works with a straight with low ace.
TS: Which one of those is the special case ?
CB: It depends how I classify an Ace.
If Ace is a one in the way I write it
then low Ace isn't my special case.
But if I write Ace as an A for example,
which then puts it in
the category of King Queen....
which I would assign a higher point value.
So then 10 is 10, Jack is 11, Queen is 12, King is 13.
then this is both one and 14.
TS: Ok.
Which might be how I implement it.
If you see an Ace in there ....
look at the array and count it as a one,
and then look at the
other array and count it as 14.
and see where it takes you.
You can't really have a
straight that takes both anyway
so that should sort us out nicely.
We might be looking later
at where's my high card, on hand.
then that's also going to inaudible
this is both 1, and 14 type of thing
Let's assume that we are taking Aces as ....
(do I have any examples here?) No.
So I'm going to write Aces with an A
because of just personal preference.
No particular reason.
My special case is going to be inaudible sting with a low Ace
I've just realized something
that I had completely forgotten about
right now if we look at the hand parser....
I've chosen cards that
translate in a lovely way
to integers, but if I do something like that....
Let's say Queen of Diamonds.
Let's say 10 is 10 Jack is 11, Queen is 12
I actually would want this to happen.
number 12, got zero, excellent.
Let's go back into my hand parser
this is going to be another
one of those special cases.
So let's say Pips for heads.
TS: What does that mean?
CB: this is terrible English I think inaudible
If it has only now Jack, Queen and Ace.
Let's say, if you get a Q card.
then inaudible assign it the value of 12 explicitly.
Let's start with a Jack, and that's an 11
and then I have Queen and that's 12,
and that's a King and that's 13
and the Ace is 14.
So this is number of Pips.
I'm going to put it into a different variable.
because this is getting too crowded.
Number of Pips equals this now.
Just to check I haven't done something stupid.
There we go.
So expected 12, got zero, perfect, so now
what I want is "check if
the beginning of that string
is one of those special cases',
otherwise you should just go with face value
so I can have something like
Pips for heads and dot fetch.
This is what we said at the beginning,
before I specified suit.
This is my Pips string.
and this is what it looks like.
I take Pips for heads
and I fetch my Pips string
So, if it's in there inaudible forward.
and if it's not then I want it to fail gracefully
and do this:
Now, the issue with that is, for example
if someone goes along the lines of
entering a queen with a capital Q.
That would not work.
It will try to translate it.
into an integer and that
would not work very nicely.
If I want to do something foolproof
I would put something along the lines of
and by the way 'can you check that
the pip string only has digits in it,
before I cast it to an integer
which will save me the worry of
how do I handle Queens -  a bit later on.
TS: Are you worried about that ?
CB: No. (laughter)
If I was shipping this then yes, but no.
Assumes correct
capitalisation,
correct letters all kinds of assumptions.
and that's fine.
I'm making that compromise for now
because I don't think that's part
of the problem that I'm most interested in.
So now we have a 'thing' and it parses queens
12 of Diamonds and that's all working out fine
Now, I've got my card values.
Let's go back to our hand spec and see where
that leaves us.
TS:  Is your policy now
to implement ordinary straights
or are you going straight for
the one that has an Ace in it ?
CB: I'm going with an ordinary straight.
So my straight hand in here just has....
56789, which is quite reasonable.
I've accidentally broken things because
my straight is broken and
tells me that everything is fine.
but now other tests are failing.
inaudible or irrelevant.
This is a more sensible place to be in.
I have assorted card values
and I want to look at each of the things
They are in assorted order and I'm
going to calculate the
difference between all of them
If at the end I am in an array of only ones.
I will be quite happy.
TS: I see.
CB: And if it's not then.... I'm not happy.
So far so good.
I'm going to go for a
naive implementation of this now
because I don't
quite know where I'm going yet.
I look at my card values.
Actually that's not what I want to do.
I want to know each of the decks
because I want to know where I am in that inaudible.
I have my value and my index
and I am looking at
my assorted card values
and what I want is....
inaudible
and I want to
compare it to the next card value
So I want to compare those two values.
and I only want to go....
this is going to throw a very ....
reached the end of the array situation.
which is not where I want to be.
This is silly, I always have 5 cards, it's a hand
so I'm going to put a magic number in there.
I'm sorry.
TS: No, no.
This is the kind of thing that
you would have in productions
you have something that defines what 5 is somewhere and inaudible
So magic number 4 ....
OK 5 inaudible
It is reasonable for me to say,
and by the way do this 4 times.
I need to start with an
assumption that's just wrong
and then I have some kind of integer.
and then, Oh ....
there's got to be a better way of doing this,
but this is the first thing that comes to mind.
So I'm looking at my sorted card values
and also at my other sorted card value.
This is it.
Let's try something like ....
this, the zero index, and
TS: I see.
So these two things I want to compare.
Just get rid of that.
I want the absolute
difference between the two.
They are sorted.
What I want is ....
So the first naive thing is...
actually the result is ......
inaudible
This is equals to one, so now
This will have to go somewhere else
because it's getting verbose.
What this chock of code
is doing there is saying ....
difference between cards.
And different Pips on a card.
Dislike.
TS: Yes, it's getting the value of that ....
CB: Yes, I absolutely don't like this.
For now inaudible unnecessary.
This should be the loop.
Let's get rid of that.
A slightly misguided abstraction.
If my difference between Pips is one,
then I continue.
Actually I don't like how I'm doing this
inaudible
difference is always one.
So what I want to do is say:
difference of one is true to start with
and the second I get a difference that is not
one between the cards, I exit out of the loop
and get out of there.
So I start with true
and while it's true
And my index is below 4
on sorted card values.count
Magic number 4 that's fine.
While difference is always one we do that.
So if difference between Pips is that
and difference is always one is ....
and the new difference between Pips is one.inaudible
This we no longer need.
Those we no longer need.
This is called 'I' because I don't
want to remember all the variables.
Where is my loops.
And now what I want to do is....
maybe initialise that,
that seems like a good idea.
I still haven't inaudible zero
I'm assuming that
it is going to be a straight.
and then I continue until
something proves me wrong.
so either I'm done with my calculation.
or that's failed.
So if it's not equal to one it should be false.
inaudible quite nice.
So now, test time.
And now the computer fails (laughter).
TS: It looks like it's got stuck in a loop
CB: Maybe because I have an internet loop.
I think I have an increment
in being dense, but there we go
Every time, just failing.
This is now still failing
but this is OK.
Still seeing failure.
So different strait.
TS: When that loop finishes, how do you know
whether or not it was a straight?
Ah, OK.
CB: I'm missing a return value
By the time we get there, I want, if it's a straight
to exit because of this failing.
and then it should return the result.
Which is still wrong.
OK, so let's have a look.
So I start an index here and as I go along
my difference is....
have I sorted them....yes.
I would do something naughty now
print the thing out so I know
where I'm heading.
I've got 56789 which seems 'straightish'
Now let's walk through this.
So difference is always one is always true.
While this is true,
the difference between Pips is
this minus this
this should be one
inaudible is one, this is
It goes to one
Yes, this returns as false.
I'm going to run one test
that one 5679
I'm going to shell out a few things.
Because I don't know what's going on.
TS: It looked like it passed there.
CB: Yes, this is why I'm a bit confused.
TS: Is it a different test that's failing ?
CB: Good point.
Maybe one of my cases is actually a straight.
Let's get rid of those.
I'm going to run this entire file
and where is my failure?
Should be a highest and it got a straight.
Oh yes, one of my test cases inaudible
I'm feeling really clever
now because it enters a flush,
but it's not a flush so it's not
going to cause me sorrow at any point.
Yes, it's all fine.
TS: Great.
I have an Ace which is a 14
but it's also a 1 when I want it to be
So straight hand no Ace,
still straight, same result.
If we do this, and we have a hand parser.
Actually, no we don't want to do that.
We have an Ace now, we don't want a one.
So we have 2345 and A.
TS: Ok,
The order doesn't matter
CB: The order shouldn't matter
because I'm sorting them anyway.
TS: So that's going to show up as
just being a high card hand.
CB: Correct.
This is showing up as a highest,
and I want it to be a straight.
Let's go in there and implement that.
This is a method that takes sorted card values
then it can work out if it's a straight or not.
Now if I have an Ace in my hand,
I want it to work out,
is this a straight if inaudible 14 ?
and is this a straight if it behaves like a one ?
If this fails, if I treat my Ace
as a 14, then just do again with a one.
let's extract that method out.
and this takes an array of cards
and determines if they are consecutive.
So, consecutive cards
This says my cards are consecutive.
I don't like the fact that it's living here.
This is just odd.
If I had more time I would want to move this to inaudible somewhere.
This is a utility type function.
which has no business being here.
TS: It doesn't have to be an instance method?
CB: it's got nothing to do with the hand.
The concept of numbers being consecutive
The hand needs it in order to rank itself.
but the actual
implementation of it does not live here.
TS: It could be any numbers?
CB: Absolutely, it could
be just some random thing,
That takes an array and
determines whether they are
in some sort of nice order.
TS: OK.
I'm just going to check that it is still
behaving nicely.
In the case where sorted card values include
the value 14, which is the Ace, I also want to
change that array and do
the same thing with the one.
and then check if it's a straight.
So let's say assorted card values.
I'm going to do
something naive, if it includes 14
This is where I want to know
what my array let's me do.
No that's drop a certain number of things.
I want to delete a thing from an array.
inaudible the array, documentation
I do this all the time.
I have a bad memory,
when it comes to
remembering all the things.
TS: it's probably not a good idea to try
to memorize them anyway.
CB: Once you start programming
in more than three languages,
it becomes a little difficult.
TS: So you're going to
delete all of the 14s from the array ?
CB: Yes, and I need to know
how many 14s I'm deleting
That exact number of 1s on the other side.
Otherwise I might end up with such
as an array and maybe three cards
It's expecting a certain
number of things in there
remember my magic number in there?
It would not be a good idea.
delete ....
According to the Ruby
documentation this is deleted.
This gives me back all the
documentation that's it deleted.
TS: It returns the last deleted item?
CB:  Yes, but it doesn't
tell me how many, interesting.
I want to know how many 14s I have,
So I want to count the
number of things that match.
How do I do that?
My implementation is this.
This can go somewhere else,
and be called what it actually is
and if my number of Aces is bigger than one.
then I want to delete all the Aces.
and add two sorted card values once,
but I want to do that
exactly the number of aces times.
I could do it in a better way by inaudible
two card values in an array of exactly
the number of aces as ones.
but let's leave that for now
and let's check if things have gone wrong.
They have.
This is terrible parenthesis use.
because it turns out
blocks don't take round brackets.
It's not working but it's not failing any more.
TS: Is it because your
number of Aces is equal to one
not greater than one ?
CB: Yes, and there is also the fact that
I think it's going to fail another way.
And let me explain why,
I think what I just wrote
is going to fail in the case of
highest, because of how I've implemented it.
To prove my point I'm going to write
There we go inaudible, high ace.
What I mean by that... and do that.
inaudible add for array.  Interesting.
TS: There are two failures,
on both of those Ace tests.
CB: Correct.
So this is you cant inaudible and insert. Yes.
it's going in the loop which is good news.
I want to find my inaudible pass
Let's de-bug our way through this
It's happening on consecutive cards
and it's happening on my eighty three
Which is here.
TS: What does the document for insert say?
CB: it's not destructive is it ?
TS: it's not inaudible the values with an index
so you have to inaudible an index.
CB: OK, alright.
I'm going to insert it at the
start because it doesn't really matter
I could go for the lazy option.
TS: Has that fixed it?
CB: No, so many things going wrong right now.
This is take my sorted
card values and give me
other possible card values for Aces.
bit premature.
If the number of Aces is bigger than one
then I want to have ....
Aces as ones.
Which is just like sorted card values
I want to manipulate that.
TS: So your going to
leave the original one alone?
CB: Correct. I don't want to touch that.
And then in the case
of straight I want to check
either it works out fine
with the usual way of doing it.
Or it works out with using
Ace as ones, way of doing it.
So either is true.
If the number of Aces is none,
then its the usual check ....
do I have consecutive cards.
Now that's going to fail
nicely in places, excellent.
It still doesn't work with a straight with low ace.
I want to check what my Aces as ones is like.
This is my best chance of
understanding what's going on.
Aces as ones looks like 123, aha !
it's not sorted
I'm doing my sort here and I am doing
my sort again.
How about .... we just don't sort them here
TS: And then consecutive cards
is going to be in charge of that.
I'll give it any number of cards
in any odd number called card values
and inside here my job is just to sort them.
TS: OK.
And then go ahead with the rest of the code.
Which I have changed variable names
so it should be less angry at me.
Straits with high Aces
straights with low Aces.
TS: Ok so we are nearly out of time now,
what would you like to do to wrap this up.
I was going to run hand
comparer, and about to write hand ranker,
I'd like to try that out and see what happens
TS: So ranking the hands you've inaudible
There are a few hands missing
but not a lot of work left to do.
Let me just correct this
inaudible
I've got a hand, it's told me what the rank it is
but if I had two cards, I want to give my
hand to my other hand and say
Are you better than that hand.
TS: Ok.
In my public interface with
my hand I would like
to have is, better than other hand.
TS: And it's going to return true or false.
CB: Yes, exactly.
How about we have a very quick,
I will describe 'better than'
We can just say:
It tells me if the hand is better.
We already have some very handy hands
We know, for example, 4 of a kind hand
It should be better than full house.
let's start with those
so full house.better than 4 of a kind hand
So I expect
all of this to be true.
TS: Is that the right way round?
A full house is better than 4 of a kind.
CB: No it's not - thank you.
That looks more sensible.
Let's run this.
I want to find a 'better than' for hand
Oh that's because I've
implemented it as a Poker method
let's run this
and now it's inaudible excellent
So I have the rank of both hands
and I want to know which is the better.
This comes back to the thing
which I was thinking about an hour ago.
If only I'd known there was a
ranking that told me the best hand.
and next possible best hand.
So this is what we want.
If we have big poker ranks
and it's an array and ordered thing for now.
and if we go forward and say.....
this is a naive implementation
So if we have 4 of a
kind, full house and straight.
What I could do is inaudible
I can just get the index of rank
and compare that to the Poker rank.
index of the other hand
and that would give me a straightforward answer for inaudible
I'm assuming that the
index is here, I'm not really sure
This is me, this is
my rank, and this is confusing.
TS: Your putting the worst first
CB: Yes because inaudible
And if it's a high rank
I want to be happier with it.
TS: The the question will
be is my index greater than
CB: Yes and I am going to
say it's strictly greater than
I'll get back to that in a second
Yes, index one doesn't exist obviously.
Let's now assume if we
have some method on the array
That is find index, that's the
one I probably want
Yes, it returns the index of a thing,
so just index would have worked better.
Let's go back here ....
Go and define method inaudible. excellent.
This is apparently nil.
TS: Because it was not
finding the rank in that array.
CB: Correct.
I am comparing four of a kind and full house.
I'm going to print out the
rank of the other hands because
I'm running out of time so
I don't want to spend ages
debugging this.
Oh of course it's a hash.
So I'm not comparing that.
I'm just assuming there is a type.
If there is a type then I should
be wary so I'm going to let that fail.
And we have no failures.
Now we can compare two hands.
There is a tiny bit of work left
there's a few hands I haven't implemented.
And there's a bit of work left in terms of:
we should probably
have all the rankings in nice order.
There's an obvious re-factoring step
which is, we'll now I have a list of things.
that rank things and then
my rank method is executing
and checking for things in a certain order.
The order that I'm
defining in this Poker ranks array
Is the exact same one which
I want to be ranking those cards
so I should be something really clever here.
The big piece of functionality that's missing is ....
If I have two straights, how do I know who has one.
and this is why I'm returning
this rank as type something
because I had in mind, I
don't only care about the type of hand
I also care about
the highest card in that hand
For a straight, for example,
I would get the highest card in that hand.
With the mix of Ace
should be counted as 1 or 14
depending on the
kind of straight that I have.
and I would return that as inaudible rank.
and if my rank method gives
me back not just the type of my hand
but also the highest possible tie breaker
in some hands but in
others it's different things,
then I can definitely determine
if my hand has won or not.
TS: Ok, great.
TS: Well I think that would
be a good place to wrap it up.
Thank  you very much
for showing us this today
It's been fascinating watching you work.
So again, thank you very much.
CB: Thanks.