Welcome to Peer to Peer, where you
can watch how experts solve tech problems.
Our guest today is Camille Baldock
who by day writes Ruby and
JavaScript for the British Government.
And by night mentors junior developers and
teaches programming in schools.
Our host is Tom Stuart.
And the challenge that we set
for Camille is called
Ranking Poker Hands
TS: So Camille, would you like to
read out the problem statement?
CB: Sure. A"hand" in poker consists of five
playing cards drawn from a standard deck.
Apparently today I'm going to implement a
system which can decide which of two
hands has the highest ranking, according
to standard poker ranking rules.
Do you know the standard
poker ranking rules?
CB: I do!  Which is fortunate.
CB: OK, right, so this is nice and vague!
CB: If I'm doing something like
that I need some way of knowing
this is hand A and this is
hand B and the program will sort it out.
And I need to think of how to tell people
to tell me what their hand looks like.
TS: OK
The first 'off the top of my head', easy
thing, is to have and array of 5 things
that says I have a 5 of Hearts
and the 6 of Diamonds.
I could represent that as ['4H', '5D'].
(4 Hearts 5 Diamonds).
Put that in an array and then
two arrays. And create the problem
TS: OK.
CB: So we'll get started with that.
So, I'm just going to switch to
where I put code.
We'll have our own folder today.
What I'm going to do is make
sure I've got a couple of things in place
Like a spec_helper.rb.
And then, we can get started.
The first thing I want to do is enter some
kind of array 'thing' and it creates...
I don't know what it creates.
So, if I'm going to be comparing hands...
A hand has several cards in it, and I
need some way to represent what a card is
and a hand that has several cards in it.
And then I want to be taking
the hand, and taking the other Hand object
and then somehow comparing them.
So the first thing I probably want to have
in place is some kind of Hand object
and some kind of Card
object in which I can put 'things'.
Yes, so we can go ahead and start that.
So the first thing I want to do is...
I have an array that says
5H and 6 Diamond.
And on the other end, and this is my Hand
object with those card 'things' inside it.
So we'll start with that I think.
TS: Are you talking about
an array of strings?
CB: As an input or...
TS: Yes
CB: I'm not too concerned about that at
the moment. I don't think it matters much,
Since I don't want to keep them as an array
of strings, but do interesting things
afterwards. So I don't think it should
matter that much.
TS: So this is just going
to be a serialisation format.
CB: Yes, a hand parser type thing.
Let's call it that.
So, if I have a hand parser 'thing'.
Ok, so this is the 'I can't type moment'.
[laughter]
So if we have some kind
of object called HandParser
It probably should 'parses the
array of strings representing the cards'
(this is quite verbose),
but let's get to that.
Actually this is going to
fail so how about we run this.
And this is not very happy and
'uninitialized constant HandParser'
Yes, this is my first failure -
here we go!
So I'm going to have to
have a HandParser sitting somewhere.
I need to create that file in there.
And let's create a  parser
that does absolutely nothing.
But that should make my test happy enough,
unless I don't require it, obviously.
Because otherwise it wouldn't know
where to look.
So let's give that a try... OK, zero
examples, zero failures. So far so good.
What I probably want to do is...
If I create a HandParser and I give it the
array of strings that will represent cards
then on the other hand I want
to check what the output of that is.
Let's have... so the subject is
HandParser, so if we have described_class.
If I create HandParser and hopefully
have some kind of thing that says parse
and it will take the array
of cards, which I need to define.
Let's have a look at how
I'm going to put those cards in.
So we can have those as
5 Hearts 6 of Diamonds.
That's not an array [Laughter].
You choose the cards.
TS: King, Queen, Ace.
CB: Yes, King of Spades, what's
the other suit? Clubs, that's the one.
So Queen of Clubs, and then we can have...
let's have an annoying card in there.
Just so we have a bit of fun.
Which is Ace.
Let's keep Ace as one and see where that
takes us. I reckon that matters somehow.
But I have no idea, so we shall see.
And this should give me
some kind of 'thing'.
This is already going to fail so I'm not
even going to put an expectation in there
I'm going to go ahead and run my tests and
this should fail nicely, because
I don't have a method parse.
TS: OK.
[Camille types]
If I have a method parse that
takes an array of things (cards).
It's not these things.
[Camille ponders]
Well - this test tests nothing.
But at least it's not erroring any more.
On the other hand -
I want it to be a hand and...
I want this to be some
kind of Hand object type of thing.
So... [Camille ponders]
So, I want to create
a Hand object type of thing.
TS: OK.
Oh, how do we even do this in RSpec.
I don't want to do
something like this, right.
How do you get a thing and
check the class of it?
Actually, do I even care about the class
of it? No, I care about how it quacks.
So I expect:
(hand.cards.count).to equal 5
And actually...
this doesn't test that anymore
so let's rewire this thing a little bit.
We'll just give this 5 cards
and it returns back a hand of cards.
So here we want it to have exactly
the same number of things that we have.
I'm going to gloss over the issue where I
give it an array that only has 4 cards
and it falls over.
Let's just not go there for now!
We'll just assume that our users
are going to put correct things in there.
TS: OK.
CB: So yes let's just start with
that, this will already fail quite nicely.
Right, excellent.
This needs to return a thing
that quacks .cards
TS: OK.
[Silence]
Look at me failing... that's
sublime, beautiful. [laughter]
OK, so if it has that then... This should
complain for different reasons now.
No, wrong shortcut, OK
uninitialized constant
HandParser::Hand... so far so good.
This doesn't know what Hand
is so let's quickly require it.
And now back to our tests.
OK, undefined method count,
it has nothing in it.
Right, so...
This should fail for a slightly
nicer reason now.
[Silence]
So now we have an array that has nothing
in it. And we should have 5 things.
and now I'll actually implement
the things because it's about time!
So if we have an array of cards
and it has 5 things,
then what I want to do is
create a hand with some cards in it.
So if we have some 'thing'
that takes the array of cards
which is essentially an array of string
cards, or however you want to call that.
And I want it to basically...
[Camille ponders]
from that string of card be able to
say, make me a Card object type 'thing'.
TS: Right.
and then eventually I'll want
to feed it into Hand.
but one thing at a time.
OK, so that can live here.
So if I have make_card thing, this is
going to move to Card object later.
Let's get to that in a second.
TS: OK.
I don't like the interface of
this, it is quite unnatural.
I quite like the fact that my parsing
logic is going to sit somewhere else.
I don't want to have to do
crazy regexes and things like that
as part of a thing that is
supposed to be comparing cards.
But, at the same time, like
here, I'm creating a new card.
TS: So why are you approaching it in
this particular way?
if you're saying you don't want this
method here, why are you putting it here?
CB: I'm not quite sure what my Card.new
method should be accepting.
In a perfect world, I would like it
to say 'if it's a 5 of Diamond' it takes
Card.new 5 and a
Diamond symbol type thing.
So I want a bit of pre-processing to check
that there are 2 things in this string.
And H maps to Hearts,
and something like that.
TS: Fine
CB: So this is where I want this to live. I'm not quite sure yet.
CB: So this is where I want this to live.
I'm not quite sure yet.
TS: So you're expecting that later you'll
have a better idea of what's going on.
CB: Yes.
TS: OK let's see what happens.
CB: OK, so this is a thing,
and it takes a card string.
And, if I remember rightly, my card
string has 5 H or something like that.
So what I'm going to do is...
Card.new and I'm taking card_string[0]
card_string[1] but actually not.
How do I want my cards to look,
how do I want them to quack.
It's going to be easier for me as a
human, to have my suits (as in Hearts/Diamonds etc)
written out in plain letters
not as H and D etc.
TS: OK
I just want to do a very quick
pre-parsing of...
if this is 'h' then just give me
:heart. and this is 'd' give me :diamond.
Actually, this could very well live in
a hash, why am I doing a terrible switch?
Let's have a hash sitting here.
We have all the suits, so we
have H, Diamonds, Clubs, Spades.
That seems correct.
TS: That's all of them yes.
[Camille types]
CB: This is the slightly tedious
typing part.
Oh right! Spades, cool.
So, this goes bye bye.
TS: So now you can just look up with a
hash rather than using a switch statement.
CB: I want it to fall over quite loudly,
if I have something crazy as my suit.
TS: How are you going to
make it fall over?
CB: With fetch. If I put, say, '5a' in
there, fetch is going to complain
because there is no suit with key 'a'
and therefore it will throw an exception.
This is a bit...
I should probably be handling this in a
more graceful way than doing that.
I definitely don't want to have a default
value because there's no such thing.
I should be thinking about things like,
do I want capital H in
there and little things like that.
But for now I'm doing it with
the minimum viable array string parser.
And see where that takes me.
TS: So your motivation here sounds
like you don't want it to silently fail?
If there's bad input,
you want it to complain.
CB: Yes, that's it.
In the same way here for
example, it takes the first symbol.
So if someone puts H5 for example, that
would also fail quite loudly.
If someone puts HH however,
it's not going to fail loudly.
But, I'm not in a statically typed language
and I don't want to spend time on it now.
I'll clean it up a bit later.
What I would usually do If I'm
writing things I want to ship is...
I would put a TODO and 'fail loudly and
with better errors with unexpected inputs'.
much in the same way I would probably
be happy having #TODO: fail nicely when not 5.
TS: Right.
CB: There's other things, like: if there's
two 5 of Hearts, you have a cheat!
And things like that,
but let's not even go there!
Let's assume that that our players
are trying to be honest, at least.
TS: we'll, I don't know enough about the
variance of Poker to say whether that's illegal.
CB: I think if you have one deck
and you have two 5 of Hearts
you can reasonably assume that
somebody's messing with the game.
TS: Fair enough.
CB: So that's going to fail quite nicely because
I'm obviously missing quite a lot of objects.
But let's see where it's failing.
So, undefined method...
Oh of course, I did something...
Here I'm assuming that make_card
is available on my string, which it isn't.
TS: You don't want to make it available.
I thought you were going to
do some monkey patching and...
Well, if you want to do it
for fun, to do crazy things, [laughter]
and then see how I fail later, then sure,
but I love myself too much to do that to myself.
So, "uninitialized constant..."
Here we go.
Now it's complaining that
we don't have whatever that is.
so we should re-create a
'whatever that is'.
card.rb and for now, to be honest
I don't see it doing anything
really smart so it's just going to have...
It's called 'Pips' in English, that's the
number on the face of the card, is it not?
TS: I think I've heard the word
'rank' but 'Pips' also seems sensible.
I'm going to stick with 'Pips'.
I reckon, since I'm also doing hand
ranker, rank is going to confuse things.
TS: Oh... that's a good point.
Separate words for separate ideas.
CB: I hear that's helpful. [laughter]
OK, so I have some kind of
silly strap that doesn't do much here.
I just want to acquire it -
rather than leave it sitting around here.
And let's go back to our spec.
Excellent, we still have nothing and that is
simply because I still haven't implemented it.
Now Hand takes cards and we're
just going to initialize it with cards.
I can get rid of that.
And make that cards available.
This should hopefully stop complaining.
No, because it did a zero
failure, so that is the one I want.
[Camille ponders]
Let's have a look.
I'm creating my hand...
[sounds of realization]
My favorite one is also to spell
initialize with 's'.
And then I spend 2 minutes thinking...
Oh! American spelling.
TS: Yes.
[Silence]
CB: Yes, good, slightly more
convincing isn't it?
TS: Yes, very good.
CB: I now have some 'thing' and
it has the right number of things.
I don't actually know that
it does parse the cards correctly.
And if the array looks
like I want it to look.
so what I can do is...
Because, currently my parser
doesn't care how many cards I'm parsing in
I can do a very quick check so
it returns the right cards as a test.
I can just do a very quick...
And if my array_of_cards is
just the one, let's say 6 of Diamonds.
Then I go for exact the same test.
And what I want is...
I take my hand, I take the cards in there.
I take the first one and I
want to check the suit is Diamonds
I also want to check that
my Pips are equal to six.
TS: OK.
CB: And I reckon we're
going to have a surprising 'thing'
because I haven't cast it to an
integer or anything like that.
Since I want to compare them, it's easier
to do if they're integers than strings
Yes, expected an integer and got a string!
What I'm going to do is not really
good practice,
but that should please it for now.
So now I can have a 'thing' and
when I put several things in there,
it puts them in a hand with cards,
and then I can check
that if I do put a card
it seems relatively OK.
If I wanted to be really exhaustive I would go
through and check Spades, check Hearts, check Clubs.
Just to see that that matching is OK.
And that would give me a bit more
certainty about what on Earth I am doing!
TS: Ok.
But that kind of does the thing,
that is good enough.
Now I'm going to start focusing on...
If I have those two hand objects
and I can look at cards on them.
And I have a nice interface with
my cards, it gives me Pips and Suits
How do I compare them?
This is time to step away from
the computer for a second.
TS: Yes, it felt like this was an
administrative thing you needed to do.
Your warmed up now. You can make two hands
of cards. Now it's time to compare them?
CB: Yes, that's about it.
The first thing we can do is
have some way of having a hand,
and it tells me 'you have a Flush' or 'you
have a Pair' and that is actually your best thing.
Not just 'you still happen to have a
Pair' because the last thing I want to do is...
I have a card that has, for example,
3 of a kind which is better than 2 of a kind
which I'm assuming you know,
which isn't very nice [laughter]
TS: I am roughly familiar with
the rules of Poker.
CB: I'll keep being unnecessarily verbose,
if you get bored you can stop me.
TS: No, no, talk me through it.
CB: If I have 3 of a kind, the last thing
I want is for my hand to tell me
"We have 2 of a kind, excellent!"
when the best I could do is 3 of a kind.
TS: So for any individual hand there
might be several possible classifications
of the cards in it, but we want to use the one that's
most likely to cause this hand to beat another one.
CB: Yes, you want the highest possible
rank of things you can get in Poker.
so if I have 4 fours then I want 4 of a kind,
not 3 of a kind, and definitely not a Pair.
Definitely not a high card.
TS: It sounds like your first line
of interest, is classifying these hands
according to what kind they are.
How were you expecting to approach that?
CB: Essentially I want to look at a
hand and it gives me what the rank is.
so it tells me if it's
a straight or thing.
So it feels to me like we're going to
have some kind of rank method on the Hand
that is going to return a "and this
is the thing that you can do with it".
That is the best possible one.
which we can half implement for now.
The first thing I'm going to
do is create a spec for my Hand,
because we're going to start
adding stuff to that.
Quick housekeeping. TS: Yes.
CB: And I'm going to be
describing my Hand.
And, I want some kind of method
I'll call it 'Rank'.
I have no particular reason to know
whether that's a good idea or not now.
So I'll keep it as it is.
And what it does is
it returns the best type of hand
from it's own cards.
There is no way I'm going to implement in
just one test, all the rules of Poker.
TS: OK. [laughter]
CB: I'm going to assume that I'm playing in
a simplified world where the only thing is a pair.
Which seems easy.
And I might regret this because maybe it's
not the easiest choice I could have made.
[Silence]
I'm not going to put in a context
for now I'm not sure where I'm going.
So, I have a Hand and...
[Camille ponders]
So this is where things get
a bit annoying. What I want is...
I have some kind of hand around.
And what I want on that hand is...
For now I'm going to use the HandParser.
Which makes me feel this is
not the right interface for the problem,
if I have to use it in such a way, but if
I have say, 5 of Hearts, 5 of Diamonds.
We're actually going to take a
Pair. And see where it takes us.
7 of Diamonds, 8 of Diamonds.
[Camille ponders]
This should just say "we have a Pair
and by the way that Pair is a Pair of 5s".
For now let's start with
'you have a Pair' in there.
TS: As you said,
that might be enough information.
If there's another hand that doesn't have
a Pair in it, you've already determined that.
CB: Yes, that's exactly it.
The first thing you want to
know is do I have a better hand?
and then if your two hands are not the
same rank, then you try calculating it.
My initial reckoning is that it will be
easier to calculate what the highest card is
at the time I'm also establishing
the rank.
So for now I want my interface
to just return the type of hand.
But later I'll want it to say, this is the
type of hand and this is the highest card.
Just in case there's a tie. TS: Alright.
CB: Let's assume that's my hand
and I want hand.rank.
So 'expect' hand.rank  to equal,
and then...
It turns information about
the winning potential of the hand.
This is a terrible description!
[Silence]
I'm just going to let it go,
because in a minute
I will probably change my
mind about what this should look like.
[Camille ponders]
So if I expect the hand equals that...
Not that.
This is failing quite nicely because
I haven't done all my requiring correctly.
[Camille ponders]
I'm doing silly thing with
silly shortcuts here [laughter].
I also don't have my HandParser.
What I don't like about that is
that now I can call this extra class
and I have this extra thing
that has all this logic here.
So rethinking it now I would
probably move that logic around.
And have my hand.new
that handles things like that.
And my hand.new can take a HandParser as
one of it's attributes of the method.
and I can make sure that
the logic of if it's H it's Hearts,
and if it's D it's Diamonds,
just goes somewhere else.
I'm not happy about that interface.
Because I don't like stopping in
the middle of a 'thing' #TODO...
This is not a nice interface,
not what I wanted to do.
TS: So your queuing up a bit of
re-factoring to do?
CB: Yes, my tests have passed so
I can't afford to just go off on a tangent
and go to fix all the things.
So let's just have a quick...
[Silence]
OK, so that's parsing,
and that's failing. Cool.
rank returns nil which is pretty much
what you'd expect because it returns nil.
OK, so I've got all my cards,
and how do I want to detect a Pair?
Array of cards - if I want to detect a
Pair, all I care about is the Pips on the cards.
I have all the cards, I can look
at how many Pips there are for each of those cards
and I can count for each possible
Pip value, how many of that Pip I have.
TS: OK.
So if I have say, 55678 here.
There was 2 x 5s, 1 x 6, 1 x7 and 1 x 8
TS: I see so you're counting
them by how many Pips they have.
You want to somehow say
I've got 2 x 5s, I've got 1 x 6 etc.
CB: Yes, I want some kind of Pip counter
that sort of mashes them up in
some structure it can read nicely.
Ideally, if I had a thing like that then I
would have something along the lines of...
I'm going to do that as a hash but I would
expect my result to look a bit like this.
I would like a magical
thing that does that for me.
And once I have that then I can check if I
have any things that so happen to have 2 of the 'thing'.
And if I do then it's a Pair.
Otherwise, it's a highest card.
So that's about it.
I want to implement a thing
that does that.
So what does this do?
I would say it's a 'Pip counter',
but it's not a great word for it.
It's a... who knows [laughter].
I'm going to call it Pip counter and...
[Silence]
This is a silly thing I do, and I may as
well do it on camera, (the world will laugh),
so when I have a terrible name
for a thing, I just put a ##bob.
I was given the clean code
thing when I started programming.
And it has this amazing thing about
how you should not name your methods.
Things like holy hand grenade
for destroy, and silly things like that,
so I always put a bob when I have
bad naming thing, and I usually have fun
figuring out the interface
when I'm finishing off an object.
So let's say it's pip_count, for now.
TS: OK.
So what does my pip_count do,
Hey, we can write a test!
That is going to do that for me.
So if I have a pip_count...
now whether that should be
in the public interface is debatable.
TS: Right.
CB: But I'm just going to keep it there
for now. As I don't yet know where we're going.
If I have a pip_count and I am parsing exactly
that hand then this is exactly the thing I want.
I'm going to stop returning that.
There we go...
That should fail quite loudly,
let's run this test.
There we go...
Yes, we've got nil, excellent.
So how are we going
implement this.  I have my cards
And for each of those cards I have Pips.
I can just...
Suddenly here I have an array of numbers,
[Camille ponders]
For a thing like this I need my documentation,
because I don't remember everything.
There is a Ruby collect on Ruby array.
This is dash... It's a documentation tool
that I like to use.
TS: So you have all of the
Ruby API documentation.
CB: This is just a quick reminder for me
because I reckon this has already been solved.
But maybe not, who knows.
Essentially I want to loop over my array
and count the number of incidences of each 'thing'.
Which actually I could do
in any number of ways.
I can't remember off the top of my
head how I would do that in pure Ruby.
Any suggestions welcome,
before I re-invent the wheel!
TS: I don't know that there is a
method in the array that does that.
the only thing that comes to mind is a
group_by method, which won't do what you want
but will do a related thing, which is group
together all of the 5s, all of the 6s and all of the 7s,
but that doesn't give you what you want.
CB: Does that give me an
array of arrays then?
TS: It gives you a hash.
The key in the hash would be 5
and the elements in the array would be
all of the 5 Pip cards that it had found.
and then the key would be 6
and the value would be...
CB: I could map on that quite easily.
Let's do a group_by
and see how that works.
So group_by...
[Camille ponders]
TS: Does it not exist?
CB: It's not in Array.
TS: It will be in Enumerable I expect.
[Camille ponders]
CB: Let's just search...
No it's not letting me search.
I'm in the wrong scope for it.
Enumerable group_by... no, no no.
It's just giving me Ansible stuff.
TS: Maybe that was a bad idea.
CB: All of the documentation.
TS: If you can implement it yourself.
CB: I shall implement it in like a minute.
That should be fine, I've got all my Pips.
What I'm wondering is,
do I want just 52617181
or do I want all of the keys of all the
possible things and then how many cards I have.
But I don't think it makes
a lot of difference.
TS: It depends what you want.
CB: I want to use group_by,
I was very excited by this.
So... here we go...
OK, yes fair enough.
TS: That's not quite what you said,
but it's close.
In that you would get the right keys but
for the values, instead of being how many
cards there were it would be
an array of those cards.
CB: I'm just wondering...
I basically need group_by...
This is not particularly pretty.
It probably has a better way of doing it.
it might be the default for that.
Let's run the tests and
see what that returns.
Yes, that gives me arrays.
Now we can just have a 'thing'.
This is my grouped_cards,
and then I can say grouped_cards
and then for each of my things,
I can say...
[typing]
TS: Ah! OK,
So you are turning each of those
arrays into a number by counting it.
CB: Yes so let's see how that works.
It's not very elegant but it should make
the test pass... so that's close enough.
We still have a failure
because we're not ranking stuff.
We are in the magical world
where only 2 rankings exists.
There is Pair and high card.
TS: Right.
If these are all my grouped
cards, and if I have 'anywhere',
in the number of group cards I have a 2,
then it's a win, and otherwise it's not.
This is my minimal viable code,
it's something along the lines of...
so this should return...
I have a rank of type Pair,
otherwise I have a rank of type highest.
I'm not quite sure about line 10 now.
So I have all the values,
I need to find...
[Camille types]
I think this is where tests help me.
TS: Yes [laughter].
CB: Undefined local variable
grouped_cards. I've done something silly.
Of course... this is called Pip count.
Right, let's try that again.
So it does something,
and for the sake of completeness
I also want to start using
better names now.
Here I have a hand with just a Pair.
and here I will have
a hand with nothing in it,
which I will call 'highest', as a type.
So if I have a highest hand, I essentially
want it to be pretty much this,
but I'm just going to put something in
there, which as you see actually is a straight.
This shouldn't be ranking as highest,
but...
TS: Does that matter at this point?
CB: No I'm quite happy about that.
It's fine, it's just setting the scope
of the problem to solving a very small 'thing'.
TS: Yes, you said before, you're
imagining a smaller version of Poker
that only has 5 cards right?
CB: Yes, a simpler and more boring world.
And now we have no failures.
I have a way of getting arrays
and then suddenly I have 'one pair',
'one thing with a pair' and 'another with
nothing' and it does rankings.
So now we have some kind of
way, in an oversimplified game of Poker
to say I have a Pair and I have a highest.
So what I would really like to do
is start implementing a few more things.
So I think the super easy way to
go is we're not going to do just Pairs
but we're going to find 3 of a kind, and 4 of
a kind and make sure the right thing comes out,
and by that I mean,
if I create a 3 of a kind,
let's call it a three_of_a_kind_hand.
So if we have a three_of_a_kind_hand, it's
going to be...
I need 5 of Hearts, Diamonds and Spades.
and that at the moment it's
going to return a Pair, I presume.
but actually we want it to
return 3 of a kind, so this should be...
If I have a rank there should be
a type three.
So if I start running this file now....
Not like this,
and not like this either.
I think I'm doing something wrong...
There we go.
I do have a failure because it is assuming
I have type :highest and not type :three.
because I am matching for
exactly 2, and obviously it's 3.
This might make my life a bit
easier because I don't need to make sure
that I'm doing things in the right
order, for that specific comparison.
I reckon it does matter for other things
but, let's get to that when we get to that.
I'm starting to write some
pretty terrible code now.
Shameless green is...
so if I have 3 then
it becomes :three_of_a_kind
and if I have 4 then
suddenly it becomes :four_of_a_kind.
But that is pretty bad.
I'm just going to check that
my tests do pass nicely.
And as they don't... it is :three_of_a_kind
and this is 3, so this should now pass.
This now knows what a 3 of a kind is.
I could write a quick 4 of a kind
that we haven't covered for the future
where we're going to be
adding more things.
I want to make sure that
I'm not breaking things.
let's just create some test
data with a four_of_a_kind_hand.
This is terribly verbose, but we should
have here 5 of Clubs and that should pass.
This is working out fine.
This however, looks pretty terrible. So
there must be a smarter way of doing this.
I could jump in right there and try to do some
kind of look at the Pip count and the values
and then if it's 2 it's a Pair,
3 of a kind, 4 four of a kind.
What I'm thinking now is that it
matters about things along the lines of,
for example I'm going to take a
problematic example of the full house,
where at the moment my code
would give me back a 3 of a kind.
I definitely don't want it to
say that. I want it to be a full house.
What I want to avoid now is making
an abstraction on this logic of Pip counts
when actually, it's not clear to
me as to where that should live.
What I would like to try doing
now is try implementing full house
which has 3 of a kind,
2 of a kind in the same hand.
Get that working and then at that point hopefully,
I will know how I want to look at those card counts.
TS: Ok.
CB: So I can extract that.
I'm going to leave this horror in a tiny bit longer
until I know with more certainty where I'm heading.
TS: So even though you're unhappy with your
code you're going to hold off from refactoring it
because you're not confident
that your solution to it is complete yet.
You don't want to introduce
an abstraction that won't fit.
You're worried that if you extract
it at this point, then you will end up
with something that won't
support full house.
CB: Yes, absolutely.
My initial premature abstraction is I just
map the number of pip count values to a type.
and I can sense that that's
going to fail when I get to full house.
I want to see how I will implement full house,
which is going to create more cruft in this code.
but I think it would help
me finding the right abstraction.
I think there is such a
thing as premature abstraction,
I find myself guilty of it a lot of times.
CB: I'm going to create a quick
test for my full house hand.
and it has 5 of Hearts, 5 of Diamonds,
5 of Spades, 6 of Clubs and 6 of Hearts.
So we have three 5s and two 6s,
and here we go.
This is going to fail nicely, because we haven't
implemented that yet and it's detecting a Pair.
Which is not what we want.
So a couple of things to start with,
the first thing is...
Right now in my code I'm saying:
If there's 2: let's go there. If there's
3: go there. If there's 4: go there.
This feels counter intuitive
because in Poker,
what I want to check is do I have a royal
flush, or a straight flush etc.
There is an order in which you would check because
you would start (in your head) with the highest hand
and if you don't have the best possible thing,
you would lower the expectations of your hand
and try to get as far down as you can.
The way I have written this code is wrong in
terms of how a human would try to solve the problem.
I can also see it as part of a full house.
so if we do a bit of reshuffling,
and by that I mean check things.
(This is terrible code by the way), but check things
in a way so I start with the nicest possible outcome.
And as I go along I get less
desirable outcomes from my hand.
then that would have given
me a 3 of a kind, as a full house.
Which is less wrong but
still pretty wrong!
TS: But what you've done there is you've built
into your code because you were explaining it...
then you were saying there is
this implied thing.
But if you're explaining what a 3 of a kind is
there's this implication, well it's not a 4 of a kind
a Pair is not a 4 of a kind,
nor a 3 of a kind,
and so it seems now your
code more accurately reflects that.
Whereas before it was
just working what by accident?
CB: It was working only in the case where
a specific hand only has for example,
only 3 of a kind and nothing else.
TS: I see, it's the full house
that's going to bring this out.
CB: The full house is bringing this out and I think
that other hands are going to bring this out anyway
because if you have a flush that
also happens to have a Pair in there
you want to check flush first,
it doesn't matter if you have a Pair.
In the case of a full house,
terrible code would go along the lines of
if I happen to have 3 in my pip
count values then two things can happen.
Either I have also in my pip count a value that
is 2, so I have a 3 and a 2 and therefore a full house.
Otherwise, the best thing I do have
is 3 of a kind.
So that would make my test
pass, but it's beginning to look terrible
First let's check that I didn't
get this one wrong.
So now that passes nicely and
this looks awful!
I believe there's a problem in
how I'm testing those.
TS: What's the problem?
CB: I'm checking that an
array includes a certain number.
and what I want to know is does my array,
in the case of 4 of a kind it includes 4, for sure.
and I don't need to look at the rest.
But in the others there are a
number of things that we want to look at.
What I want to try doing is...
TS: It sounds like you're
switching into refactoring. CB: Yes.
TS: Why have you chosen this point?
Because you said there are some other
hands that you haven't implemented yet.
Do you feel that you have come to a point
now where you have sufficient confidence
in your implementation
so far to start refactoring it?
CB: I think I have sufficient
confidence to start thinking about it.
But I might hit a mental
block in a few seconds [laughter].
I want to see how the
other hands are going to work out.
TS: I see, alright.
CB: All my other hands are
along the lines of straight and flush,
and we can assume that's already
out of the way.
By the time the code will hit
those and now we're counting the cards
we've already excluded
a couple of those things.
I still don't like this.
I don't like entering this type of code because
if 4 of a kind is better than a flush, for example.
So I want to look at those things later.
I am starting to imagine
that I am creating as I go along,
this is a list of all the
things you can do in Poker.
and this is how well they rank
in the world of poker.
The highest and the lowest ranking
And a straight flush is as high as it gets.
What I am creating in my head is some kind of
thing along the lines of a thing called Poker ranks
which is something along the lines of...
The most desirable 'thing'
is a straight flush.
Let's give that a rating of...
I don't know how many different
types of cards there are in Poker.
Let's say 10, but I think that's wrong.
and then we have a 4 of a kind and that
would be a rating 9, and then so on and so forth.
And then each of those can have a
method that checks the card is what it is.
But that would re-use quite a lot
of code and I'm not happy about that either.
So, let's not do that.
TS: OK, so you're talking about
having some sort of scoring system.
What was your motivation for
wanting to score them?
CB: I'm motivated to have
some defined order
which looks for the best
and worst possible outcomes
other than it checks for them
in a different order in the code.
TS: So you want to make that more explicit
rather than writing a method that
looks like you could do it in any order.
CB: Yes.
I'm going to start doing a tiny bit
of extract method, for my own sanity.
Just so I can see where things are going.
This is all going to be private.
I'm going to quickly go through those...
[Silence]
That was a bit odd...
There we go.
Now we are assuming that we have those
magical methods: has_four, has_three, has_two.
And checks whether there is a Pair
or a 3 or a combination of 4 in there.
Which doesn't mean it's a three of a kind.
it means there happens to be
3 cards of the same kind in there.
So if we have has_four, then this
is still include(4) and in much the same way
let's assume I have has_three and has_two
and that's going to be what you think.
and that's a bit verbose but
I'm not so bothered about that
because it's hidden away in private
methods and I can get round to it later
if I feel it is necessary.
This feels more readable to me.
It feels like the 4 of a kind
type has the has_four check.
And for the full house, this needs
to be true and this needs to be true.
3 of a kind check this only needs
to be true. Pair has_pair needs to be true.
So suddenly I have all my cards. All
of the types of things I can do in Poker.
and I have a combination of methods that
can tell me exactly why that would be.
So the easy way of doing it would be:
If has_four then that.
This is still verbose.
I start refactoring and then usually
I add a lot of stuff, make it very explicit
then start compressing later.
So elsif full_house.
Then :type => :full_house.
Elsif has_three then... 3 of
a kind, elsif has_pair, then Pair.
I'm going to have to implement
full house quickly.
Missing a def here.
Here we go, it's has_three and...
Maybe not multiply these [laughter].
I don't know what that does
actually, if you multiply two methods.
It complains loudly but I don't know how.
This feels more readable.
TS: Does it work?
CB: That's what I would like to check!
[Laughter]
No it absolutely doesn't.
That's because question marks are nice
[Camille ponders]
It's maybe not the day to invent
new methods in Ruby.
Undefined local variable or method
has_pair simply because I called it has_two.
Let's keep it that way.
Go...
And now we're back in action,
this is more readable.
We're checking things in order.
There is a better way of doing that
but let's wait until I have a couple more hands
and I can drive out something
a bit better.
I had an idea with a ranking
but I'm not quite happy with it yet.
TS: Ok.
CB: So, what are our next hands?
Do you have a favorite
hand that you want to implement next?
TS: Well I don't want to prejudice
you. What's your favorite hand?
CB: A straight flush.
TS: Then go with that.
CB: We'll have a straight flush.
TS: Seems a bit optimistic as you
don't have straights or flushes yet
but if you want to yes.
I think that's going to
drive out the changes quickly.
But yes you're right,
may be a bit optimistic.
In much the same way that full
house is a has_two and has_three situation.
a straight flush is a straight
and is a flush.
TS: Is straight or flush easier to do?
I reckon flush.
TS: Why don't we do flush then.
CB: Alright.
Let's quickly create a flush hand.
The test definition is right at
the top. This file is getting verbose.
TS: It's a good job you've got that
hand parser otherwise it would be even worse.
CB: I don't want to imagine what it would
look like if we had to do doubles for this.
So flush, let's go for all Hearts.
[Camille types]
I'm going to give myself
a very disappointing hand.
If you had that hand in Poker,
you would say WHY!
So that should give me a flush and
I'm going to check that it's definitely failing.
TS: What does it think it is?
CB:  Oh! That's an interesting one. So...
We have a new problem now.
TS: What's gone wrong?
CB: Well, 10, it's got two numbers.
So it's not parsing it properly.
I'm taking the first character only and in
the second I'm taking the second character only.
There's two ways we can solve this...
I represent 10 in another way, like zero
or something silly. I don't want to do that,
We can just very quickly change the
parser so that it doesn't take the zero, and the one,
and it takes something a bit smarter.
TS: The error that's coming out there is
that because you did the fetch on the hash?
CB: Yes, if I hadn't done a fetch on
a hash, and I had put a default value.
Who knows what would happen
in that parser #TODO: fail loudly.
TS: Yes, it's already paying off.
CB: It is failing loudly, so OK...
So here we're taking only the first
character, and here only the last character.
What I want to do is take the last one.
So how do I get the last char out
of a string? I can do something along the lines of:
[Camille ponders]
Oh! I don't even know.
Now how I would do that,
(and I know that's incorrect),
would be something along those lines.
There must be a better way though.
[Camille types]
I know there's a way of doing it with minus
ones but I don't want to do that right now.
I'm feeling particularly lazy.
Here, I want to go up to cards.
String length minus one,
take that as a string.
I want to run the spec quickly
because I reckon I've got this wrong.
Wrong number of arguments,
what have we done now?
[Silence]
This is still fetching a string.
I will make sure I've got a test
that does the 10 might as well...
Let's just run this file now.
Now we have a hand parser...
line 20...length, so that's not right.
So hand parser on
line 20 calling length on...
[Camille ponders]
It's an array, no.
No it's called card string,
I would suspect that it's a string.
So wrong number of arguments one for
zero why does it think it has an argument?
because parentheses...
Ah, extract method, this is terrible.
So last number of...
This is terrible,
I should just do it with minus ones.
TS: How does the minus one thing work?
CB: I believe it puts you
in an imaginary space between
the start and end of your
array, but I might be wrong.
So the end_of_the_card_number_index
is where I want to be.
And here I want to go up to the
end_of_card_number_index
[Silence]
And here I want to go from
zero to the end card index minus one
No, I want to go to the end of card index
and here I want to go to this.
So this should still fail.
I reckon I've got something else wrong.
TS: [Laughter] That's not very optimistic.
CB: We have key not found.
[Camille ponders]
Fetch is failing again.
That's relatively good news.
So my card string of this
is not working out.
So this is nil because end of card
number plus one is not quite what I want it to be.
Why is old code popping up?
So now that it has been
determined that I am terrible at array indexing
Let's get back to our tests.
It's lucky that I spotted that when I did.
[Silence]
This is the failure which led us
to another failure.
But this is good.
Now, where is our flush?
This is where I don't know Poker
quite as we'll as I would like to
So elsif flush, type flush.
Where does flush belong on
this sort of thing?
It is above full house. Yes.
TS: It doesn't actually matter.
CB: No, that's right but it would
matter to someone who plays Poker perhaps.
TS: At the moment you don't have any code
that compares two hands to find out which one is better.
as long as they are correctly classified
that's OK.
CB: Yes, so let's implement
a very quick flush.
So what my flush is... in much the same way as
I'm doing do I have two cards of the same thing.
I'm saying can you look at all my
suits and tell me if they're all the same.
and that's about it.
Much in the same way I'm doing
the pip count, I probably want something
along the lines of a suit
count, that does this but with suits.
And here I'm going to do the dupe
flag which means I've copy/pasted this.
Maybe there's a better abstraction
to use here.
So here I'm grouping it by suits.
I'm going to write a quick test to
make sure this is doing what I think it is
because I'm not confident enough
to reckon that it's all going to be fine.
So in this hand I have my Pair hand
which I am using.
It has 4 Diamonds and 1 Heart.
So I should have Heart 1 and Diamonds 4.
It shouldn't be the pip
count, it should be the suit count
I believe that's what I called it. Yes.
Now I have two failures.
This is the expected failure.
Expected method suits.
Not the interface I was programming
to. So this should be suit and not suits.
TS: OK.
CB: Now it seems to be working and we're
back to our problem: permitting flush.
But now if I have some kind of flush count
Oh no, suit count, then
suddenly my life is quite a lot easier.
Because...
If I can type! [laughter]
I can implement this... let's see...
Now I have a flush.
[Camille types]
So very quickly a straight.
This should be more interesting and more
complicated. It's not something we've done so far.
So I have 5 of Hearts, 6 of Hearts 7,
of Hearts, 8 of Hearts and a 9 of Diamonds,
because it's not a straight flush.
Let's check if this is failing nicely.
Yes.
And let's put our straight
somewhere in there.
There we go.
And if flush and straight
in much the same way...
Let's have a look and see if those...
What I care about is the straight
and not the suits.
I'm going to look at the cards and their face
values and I need to make sure they are consecutive.
TS: Ok.
CB: How will I do that?
TS: Good question.
CB: The first thing I would
probably want to do is extract out
of the cards array just the
array of values.
Because this is what I care about.
Let's see, where are our cards?
What I want is this:
Now I have some kind of array
that is 3567, something like that.
In all likelihood it could be
47892 and be completely unsorted.
So let's just sort that really
quickly... And we have sorted card values
I don't know why I'm doing it
in a destructive way.
I just like bangs, but that's a bit silly.
So I have sorted card values.
I want to know if they are consecutive.
Is there something that does that
in ruby or do I need to re-implement it?
TS: I'm not sure.
CB: OK, so what I care about if I'm
trying to determine if things are consecutive.
Let's assume we live in
a world where Aces don't exist.
TS: OK.
CB: Because Aces...
No I don't want to go there.
So if I have 12345 as
in Ace 2345, that's a straight.
but I can also count Ace as the high card,
so after King.
My initial idea was I could just have a bunch
of numbers and all I need to care about is...
I look at the face
value on there and on there,
they are sorted, so if the difference between
this Pair and this Pair and this Pair is always one,
then I've won and it's a straight.
But I can't really do that if
I'm doing Aces because
my Ace would potentially sit on
one side or other of the array.
Let's assume Aces are just ones for now.
And then I'm going to make sure that I
write a test
which is "it works with a straight with high
Ace", and it works with a straight with low ace.
TS: Which one of those is
the special case?
CB: It depends how I classify an Ace.
If Ace is a one in the way I write
it then low Ace isn't my special case.
But if I write Ace as an A for example,
which then puts it in the category of King Queen....
which I would assign a higher point value.
So then 10 is 10, Jack is 11,
Queen is 12, King is 13, then ace is both one and 14.
TS: OK.
CB: Which might be how I implement it.
If you see an Ace in there...
look at the array and count it as a one,
and then look at the array and
count it as 14, and see where it takes you.
You can't really have a straight that takes
both anyway so that should sort us out nicely.
We might be looking later at
what is my high card, on a hand,
then that's also going to come into
play, this both 1 and 14 type of thing.
Let's assume that we are taking Aces
as... (do I have any examples here?) No.
So I'm going to write Aces with an A because
of just personal preference. No particular reason.
My special case is going to be it
works with straight with a low Ace
I've just realized something
that I had completely forgotten about.
Right now if we look at the hand parser.
I've chosen cards that
translate in a lovely way to integers,
but if I do something like that....
Let's say Queen of Diamonds.
Let's say 10 is 10 Jack is 11, Queen is 12.
I actually would want this to happen.
Number 12, got zero, excellent.
Let's go back into my hand parser, this is
going to be another one of those special cases.
So let's say Pips for heads.
TS: What does that mean?
CB: This is me being terrible at English
for heads I mean Jack, Queen, King, Ace.
Let's say, if you get a Q card, then
I'm going to assign it the value 12.
Let's start with a Jack, and that's an
11 and then I have Queen and that's 12,
and that's a King and that's 13,
and the Ace is 14.
So this is number of Pips.
I'm going to put it into a different
variable because this is getting too crowded.
Number of Pips equals this for now.
Just to check I haven't done
something stupid. There we go.
So expected 12, got zero, perfect, so now
what I want is "check if the beginning
of that string is one of those special cases,
otherwise you should just
go with face value.
So I can have something like
Pips for heads dot fetch.
This is what I said at the
beginning, before I specified suit.
This is my Pips string.
And this is what it looks like.
So what I'm going to do is...
I take Pips for heads and
I fetch my Pips string.
[Silence]
So, if it's in there we can go forward
and if it's not then I want it to fail gracefully
and do this...
Now, the issue with that is, for example
if someone goes along the lines of
entering a queen with a
capital Q, then that would not work.
Because it will try to translate it into an
integer and that would not work very nicely.
If I want to do something foolproof
I would put something along the lines of...
"and by the way can you check
that the pip string only has digits in it",
before I cast it to an integer. Which will save
me the pain of how do I handle Queens a bit later on.
TS: Are you worried about that?
CB: No. [laughter]
If I was shipping this then yes, but no.
So this assumes correct capitalization,
correct letters all kinds of assumptions.
And that's fine.
I'm making that compromise for now
because I don't think that's part
of the problem that I'm most interested in.
So now we have a 'thing' and it parses queens,
12 of Diamonds and that's all working out fine.
Now, I've got my card values.
Let's go back to our hand spec
and see where that leaves us.
TS:  Is your priority now
to implement ordinary straights
or are you going straight for
the one that has an Ace in it?
CB: I'm going with an ordinary straight.
So my straight hand in here just
has 5,6,7,8,9, which is quite reasonable.
I've accidentally broken things because
my straight is broken and
tells me that everything is fine.
But now other tests are failing.
So I could do something like that.
TS: Now you'll only have 1 failing test!
CB: Yes. This is a slightly
more sensible place to be in.
I have sorted card values
and I want to look at each of the things
They are in a sorted order and I'm going
to calculate the difference between all of them
If at the end I am in an array
of only ones. I will be quite happy.
TS: I see.
CB: And if it's not then... I'm not happy.
So far so good.
I'm going to go for a naive implementation of
his now because I don't quite know where I'm going yet.
I look at my card values.
Actually that's not what I want to do.
I want to use each_with_index because
I want to know where I am in that array.
I have my value and my index and
I am looking at my sorted card values.
And what I want is...
I have my card in sorted_card_values
and I want to compare it to the next card value
So I want to compare those two values.
And I only want to go...
This is going to throw a very...
reached the end of the array
situation. Which is not where I want to be.
This is silly, I always have 5 cards,
it's a hand
So I'm going to put
a magic number in there.
I'm sorry.
TS: No, no.
[Camille types]
CB: This is the kind of thing
where going to production
you have a thing that defines
what 5 is somewhere.
So magic number 4...
OK always 5 cards per hand.
It is reasonable for me to say,
and by the way do this 4 times.
I need to start with an assumption
that's just wrong,
and then I have some kind of
integer and then...
There's got to be a better way of doing this,
but this is the first thing that comes to mind.
So I'm looking at my sorted card value
and also at my other sorted card value.
This is it.
Let's try something like this...
the zero index, and...
TS: I see.
CB: So these two things I want to compare.
Just get rid of that and...  basically if I
want the absolute difference between the two.
They are sorted, so actually
So what I want is...
[Camille ponders]
So the first naive thing is...
actually the result is...
old result and...
This is equals to one, so now...
This will have to go somewhere
else because it's getting verbose.
What this chunk of code
is doing there is saying:
difference_between_cards.
And different Pips on a card.
And basically...
Dislike.
TS: Yes, it's getting the value of that...
CB: Yes, I absolutely don't like this.
For now use a variable before
I do something silly and unnecessary.
This should be the loop.
Let's get rid of that.
A slightly misguided abstraction.
If my difference_between_pips is one,
then I continue.
Actually I don't like how I'm doing this.
It's: while(difference_always_1)
So what I want to do is say
difference of one is true to start with.
And the second I get a difference
that is not one between the cards,
I exit out of the loop and
get out of there.
So I start with true and while it's true
And my index is below 4.
Or sorted_card_values.count.
[Camille ponders]
Magic number 4 that's fine.
OK, so while difference_always_one
we do that.
So if difference_between_pips is
that and difference_always_1 is...
And the new difference_between_pips
is one.
This we no longer need.
Those we no longer need.
This is called 'i' because I don't
want to rename all the variables.
I need to close my loops.
And now what I want to do is....
Maybe initialize that,
that seems like a good idea.
I start at index zero. I'm assuming
that it is going to be a straight.
and then I continue until
something proves me wrong.
So either I'm done with my
calculation or that's failed.
So if it's not equal to one it should
be false and then exit, and it's all quite nice.
So now, test time...
No...
And now the computer fails [laughter].
TS: It looks like it's stuck in a loop.
CB: Maybe because I have an infinite loop.
I think I haven't incremented the index...
There we go.
[Silence]
Every time, just failing.
This is now still failing.
But this is OK.
Still the same failure.
So different straight.
TS: When that loop finishes, how do
you know whether or not it was a straight?
Ah, OK.
CB: I'm missing a return value.
By the time we get there, I want, if
it's a straight to exit because of this failing.
And then it should return the result.
Which is still wrong.
OK, so let's have a look.
So I start an index here
and as I go along.
My difference is....
have I sorted them....yes.
I would do something naughty now...
print the thing out so
I know where I'm heading.
I've got 56789 which seems 'straightish'
Now let's walk through this.
So difference_always_1 is true, fine.
While this is true, the difference
between Pips is this minus this.
This should be one difference_always_1,
this is equals to one.
[Camille ponders]
Yet, this returns as false.
I'm going to run one test,
just that one 5679.
I'm going to shell out a few things
because I don't know what's going on.
TS: It looked like it passed there.
CB: Yes, this is why I'm a bit confused.
TS: Is it a different test that's failing?
CB: Good point. Maybe one of
my cases is actually a straight.
Let's get rid of those.
I'm going to run this entire file...
And where is my failure?
Should be a highest and it got
a straight... Ah!
Oh yes, one of my test cases
is a straight.
I'm feeling really clever now because...
and it's not a flush so it's not
going to cause me sorrow at any point.
Yes, it's all fine.
TS: Great.
CB: I have an Ace which is a 14
but it's also a 1 when I want it to be
So straight hand low
Ace, still straight, same result.
If we do this, and we have a hand parser.
Actually, no we don't want to do that.
We have an Ace now, we don't want a one.
So we have 2345 and A.
TS: Ok,
The order doesn't matter?
CB: The order shouldn't matter
because I'm sorting them anyway.
TS: So that's going to show
up as just being a high card hand.
CB: Correct.
This is showing up as a highest,
and I want it to be a straight.
So let's go in there and implement that.
This is a method that takes sorted card
values then it can work out if it's a straight or not.
Now if I have an Ace in my hand,
I want it to work out: is this a straight
if it behaves like a 14?
and: is this a straight
if it behaves like a 1?
So what I want to do is basically...
If this fails when I treat my Ace
as a 14, then just do again with a 1.
Let's extract that method out.
And this takes an array of cards
and determines if they are consecutive.
So, consecutive cards...
[Camille types]
This says my cards are consecutive.
I don't like the fact that it's living here.
This is just odd.
If I had more time I would want
to move this to a helper somewhere.
This is a utility type function
which has no business being here.
TS: It doesn't have to be
an instance method?
CB: Correct. The concept of consecutive
numbers has nothing to do with the hand.
The hand needs it in order to rank itself.
But the actual implementation
should not live here.
TS: It could be any numbers?
CB: Absolutely, it could be just
some random thing, that takes an array,
and determines whether they
are in some sort of nice order.
TS: OK.
CB: I'm just going to check
that it is still behaving nicely.
So now what I want is...
In the case where sorted card values
include the value 14, which is the Ace,
I also want to change that array
and do the same thing with the 1.
And then check if it's a straight.
So let's say sorted card values.
I'm going to do
something naive, if it includes 14
This is where I want to know
what my Array lets me do.
Just to have a bit of drop...
No that's drop a certain number of things.
I want to delete a thing from an array.
That is not the array documentation.
I do this all the time.
I have a relatively bad memory,
when it comes to remembering
all the things.
TS: It's probably not a good
idea to try to memorize them anyway.
CB: Once you start programming in more
than three languages, it becomes a little difficult.
TS: So you're going to delete
all of the 14s from the array?
CB: Yes, and I need to know
how many 14s I'm deleting,
In order to add that exact
number of 1s on the other side.
Otherwise I might end up with something
crazy such as an array with only three cards
which will explode because it is
expecting a certain number of things in there;
remember my magic number in
there? It would not be a good idea.
Delete 14.
According to the Ruby
documentation this is deleted_aces.
This gives me back all that it's deleted.
TS: It returns the last deleted item?
CB:  Yes, but it doesn't
tell me how many, interesting.
[Camille ponders]
I want to know how many 14s I have,
So I want to count the number of
things that match.
How do I do that?
My implementation is this...
[Camille types]
This can go somewhere else, and be called
what it actually is which is number of Aces.
And if my number of Aces is bigger
than one, then I want to delete all the Aces.
And add two sorted card values, ones.
But I want to do that
exactly the number of aces times.
I could do it in a better way by
concatenating two sorted card values
in an array of exactly the
number of aces as ones.
But let's leave that for now and
let's check if things have gone wrong.
They have.
This is just terrible parenthesis use.
Because it turns out
blocks don't take round brackets.
It's not working but it's not
failing any more.
TS: Is it because your number of Aces
is equal to one not greater than one?
CB: Yes, and there is also
the fact that here...
I think it's going to fail another way.
And let me explain why...
I think what I just wrote is going to fail in the
case of high ace, because of how I've implemented it.
To prove my point I'm going to write...
There we go straight_hand_high_ace.
What I mean by that... and do that.
Undefined method `add` for array...
interesting.
TS: There are two failures,
on both of those Ace tests.
CB: Correct.
So this is you can't add and I expect
it's insert. Yes.
So now it's actually going
in the loop which is good news.
Undefined '-' method class.
Let's debug our way through this.
It's happening on consecutive cards.
And it's happening on line eighty three...
Which is here.
TS: What does the documentation
for insert say?
CB: It's not destructive is it?
TS: It sets the given value with the
given index so you have to provide an index.
CB: OK, alright, so...
I'm going to insert it at the
start because it doesn't really matter
Or I could go for the lazy option
[laughter]
TS: Has that fixed it?
CB: No, so many things going
wrong right now.
This is take my sorted card values and
give me other possible card values for Aces.
A bit premature.
I want to count the number of Aces and...
If the number of Aces is bigger
than one then I want to have...
Aces as ones.
Which is just like sorted card values.
I want to manipulate that.
TS: So you're going to leave
the original one alone?
CB: Correct. I don't want to touch that.
And then in the case of straight
I want to check
either it works out fine
with the usual way of doing it.
Or it works out with the using
Ace as ones, way of doing it.
So either is true.
If the number of Aces is none,
then it's the usual check
"do I have consecutive cards"?
Now that's going to fail nicely
in places, excellent.
It still doesn't work with
a straight with low ace.
I want to check what my
Aces as ones is like.
This is my best chance of
understanding what's going on.
So my Aces as ones looks like 123, aha!
It's not sorted
I'm doing my sort here and
I am doing my sort again.
How about... we just don't sort them here
TS: And then consecutive cards
is going to be in charge of that.
CB: I'll give it any number of cards
in any odd number called card values
and inside here my job is
just to sort them.
TS: OK.
And then go ahead with
the rest of the code.
Which I have changed variable
names so it should be less angry at me.
Good, straights with low Aces
and straights with high Aces.
TS: Ok so we are nearly out of time now,
what would you like to do to wrap this up.
CB: I was supposed to write a hand
comparer, and now I've written a hand ranker,
I'd like to try that out and
see what happens
TS: So ranking the hands
you've already implemented?
CB: Yes, there are a few hands
missing but not a lot of work left to do.
Let me just correct this so that
we are following the rules of poker.
Which might be helpful with ranker.
I've got a hand, it's told me what
the rank it is but if I had two cards,
I want to give my hand to my other
hand and say "Are you better than that hand".
TS: Yes.
In my public interface with my hand
I would like to have, is_better? than other hand.
TS: And it's going to return
true or false.
CB: Yes, exactly.
How about we have a very quick...
I will describe 'better than'.
We can just say...
It tells me if the hand is better.
We already have some very handy hands.
We know, for example, the 4 of a
kind hand should be better than full house.
Let's start with those, so
full_house.better_than? 4 of a kind hand.
So I expect all of this to be true.
TS: Is that the right way round.
A full house is better than 4 of a kind?
CB: No it's not - thank you.
That looks more sensible.
Let's run this.
I want to find a 'better than' for hand.
Oh, that's because I've
implemented it as a Poker method.
Let's run this...
and now it's getting nil, excellent.
So I have the rank of both hands
and I want to know which is the better.
This comes back to the thing
which I was thinking about an hour ago.
If only I'd known there was a ranking that
told me the best hand. and next possible best hand.
So this is what we want.
If we have big poker ranks...
and it's an array and
ordered thing for now.
and if we go forward and say.....
This is a naive implementation. So if
we have 4 of a kind, full house and straight.
What I could do is in
POKER_RANKS I can just get the index of rank,
and compare that to the
POKER_RANKS index of the other hand.
And that would give me a straightforward
answer for hands that, you know...
I'm assuming that the
index is here, I'm not really sure.
This is me, this is my rank,
and this is confusing.
TS: You're putting the worst first.
CB: Yes because it's a lower rank. And if it's
a high rank I want to be happier with it.
TS: The the question will be
is my index greater than?
CB: Yes and I am going to say it's strictly
greater than. I'll get back to that in a second.
But yes, index 1 doesn't exist obviously.
Let's now assume if we have
some method on the array,
that is find index, that's
the one I probably want... Is it?
Yes, it returns the index of a thing,
so just index would have worked better.
Let's go back here...
Go and define method
something for nil class, excellent.
This is apparently nil.
TS: Because it was not finding
the rank in that array?
CB: Correct.
Do I not have...
what am I comparing in my hand spec?
I am comparing four of a kind
and full house.
I'm going to print out the rank of the
other hands because I'm running out of time
so I don't want to spend ages
debugging this.
Oh of course it's a hash [laughter].
So I'm not comparing that.
I'm just assuming there is a type.
If there isn't a type then I should
be wary so I'm going to let that fail.
And we have no failures, so
now we can compare two hands.
There is a tiny bit of work left.
There's a few hands I haven't implemented.
And there's a bit of work left
in terms of...
well, we should probably
have all the rankings in nice order.
There's an obvious refactoring step which is,
well, now I have a list of things that rank things
and then my rank method is executing
and checking for things in a certain order.
The order that I'm defining
in this POKER_RANKS array
Is the exact same one which
I want to be ranking those cards.
So I should be doing something
really clever here.
The big piece of functionality
that's missing is...
If I have two straights,
how do I know who has one?
And this is why I'm returning this rank
as type something because I had in mind,
I don't only care about the type of hand.
I also care about the highest card in that hand.
For a straight, for example, I
would get the highest card in that hand.
With the mix of Ace should be counted as
1 or 14 depending on the kind of straight that I have.
And I would return that as
the type of rank.
And if my rank method gives
me back not just the type of my hand
but also the highest possible tie breaker in
some hands but in others it's different things,
then I can definitely determine
if my hand has won or not.
TS: Ok, great.
Well I think that would be
a good place to wrap it up.
Thank you very much for
showing us this today.
It's been fascinating watching
you work. So again, thank you very much.
CB: Thanks.
Captions produced by Bonnie Roworth